RICHARD ACHEE: Hello, everyone,
and thanks for joining.
Today, we're going to
learn about Progressive Web
Apps, or PWAs for short.
And we'll look at an example
of a major health care solution
provider that is building a
progressive web app to overcome
the challenges of
moving to the cloud
while meeting the needs
of mobile workers.
So I spend a lot
of my time working
with health care solution
providers and their customers.
Based on what we're
seeing in the market,
the benefits for health care
systems to move to the cloud
is clear.
First, let's look
at the patients.
Based on a study by
Accenture, the opportunity
to improve the experience
for digitally-savvy patients
can boost margins by 50%.
For clinicians, the shift to
cloud apps and mobile devices
can reduce paperwork by 60%
and increase patient face time
by 29%, helping to mitigate
the risk of physician burnout
while improving the
quality of care.
But moving to the cloud from
traditional desktop apps
has not been easy
in health care.
So for example, let's think
about the day in the life
of an emergency
medical technician,
or EMT, moving from
helicopter to ambulance
to hospital while updating
vital patient information.
To address the needs of mobile
health workers while shifting
mission-critical
applications to the cloud,
health care solution providers
and IT leaders need a way
to deal with a
variety of issues--
flaky networks, lots
of mobile workers,
clinicians using
multiple form factors,
ensuring the security and
privacy of patient data
while making it accessible
anywhere and on any device,
and making it feel like
a native app experience.
We're now seeing
health care solution
providers shift to
progressive web apps
to address these issues.
But what do we mean by
progressive web apps,
and how can they help?
Progressive web apps are
just like any other web app.
The key difference is
that they have adopted
progressive features,
such as service workers
to enable background
processes and offline access,
and a web app manifest
to allow for the web app
to be installed
alongside other apps
on a computer with the look
and feel of a desktop app.
Service workers ensure that
PWAs are always up to date
and can be accessed offline,
mitigating flaky network
issues.
This feature increases
reliability and speed
for workers on the go.
And with web app manifest,
you can enable your web app
to be installed just like
any other desktop app.
So with a few changes to
your existing web app,
you can bring the progressive
web app experience
to any OS and form factor,
all with a single code base.
So let's look at an example.
One major health care
solution provider
decided, two years ago, to use
Electron for their NextGen EHR.
At the time, they felt
Electron would give them
increased control of
the user experience
and help them keep their
product up to date.
But since two years ago, the
web has rapidly advanced.
And they took another
look at the capabilities
of PWA and the advanced
enterprise security
and management features now
available on Chrome browser.
After doing the research,
they came to the conclusion
that with progressive
web apps, they
can realize the
benefits they had hoped
to achieve with Electron while
greatly enhancing the security
and portability of
their application.
So they decided to shelve
their Electron plans
and pivot to PWA.
It provided the same
benefits that they
were trying to get from
Electron while making
it much easier to
ensure their app
is highly secure and
accessible from any device.
So what did we learn?
Adopting progressive
features in your web app
creates a native-like
experience.
To start your
journey, look at what
you can do with service
workers and web app manifest.
Service workers for
background processes
and offline access, web app
manifest for installability.
With a little
development effort,
you can provide a
native-like experience
to any user on any device,
all from a single code base.
Thanks for watching.
I've included links
in the description
for details on how to integrate
any of these features.
See you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]