[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANIL SABHARWAL:
The year was 1993.
Now I realize that
some of you may not
have even been born yet.
But for me, it was the year that
my parents first brought home
our internet-capable computer,
the Commodore Amiga 4000.
Frogger never looked so good.
Yeah, sure,
WordPerfect was still
on 19 3 and 1/2
inch floppy disks.
But I had a 9,600 baud
modem for the first time.
The possibilities
were limitless.
Now, I grew up in Canada.
So like any
self-respecting Canadian,
I have a healthy
obsession for hockey.
And my team is the
Edmonton Oilers.
And if I'm honest with
myself, my love for computers
started because of
hockey bulletin boards.
Weeks after I got
my first computer,
I had a friend of
mine who said to me,
I have to download this
so-called browser, called
Mosaic, and visit this
thing called a URL.
Well, 22 seconds and 37
beautiful modem beeps later,
it was everything I
hoped it would be.
I was on the web.
I was hooked.
I checked this website every
single day before class.
That's a big deal for
me, because I'm not
a morning person.
But every morning, I
would wake up and have
a look at this website.
And my friends and
I, we would actually
start exchanging notes in
class with URLs on them
that we had found
the day before.
Which was a big deal,
because this is 1993,
so there are no search engines.
So finding a URL
that actually worked
and had interesting content
was a pretty big deal.
Now, about a month
of this went on.
And I thought to myself, I want
to create my own site, too.
So I started researching
stuff, like FTP servers,
and domain registrars, and
Hypertext Markup Language.
But what I remember
most was the first time
that I viewed source.
[HUMMING ANGELIC CHORD]
It was like being let into
this open secret club where
I could see the HTML for
the site, warts and all,
and being invited in.
It was where-- source code
was where people knowingly
allowed you to see and share all
of this really interesting code
that allowed you to
accelerate your own work
and share the expertise.
So I did what most
first-timers did.
I copied the HTML
into VI, I edited
to make it look
like it was my own,
and I pushed my changes
live, with a link
back to the original
site, of course.
And my code, by the way,
didn't look anything like this.
This looks way
too nice for 1993.
I had a lot more
table and break tags.
Well, today, nearly
25 years later,
we're all members of this
amazing, vibrant, global,
and growing community.
Now, we all have our own story
for how we first got started.
But I bet, for many of you,
it's not too dissimilar to mine.
It was because you wanted to be
part of this broader community.
And that's why,
today, we're all here,
to take a moment to
recognize and really
celebrate the we in web.
Because the web is so much more
than any one company, any one
product, or any one person.
It's all of us.
What started with Mosaic
and Navigator in the '90s
has grown to dozens of web
browsers across the globe,
each stretching and
improving the end user
experience in significant ways.
Microsoft and IE actually
jumpstarted the Ajax era,
with the XML HTTP
request, bringing
powerful interactive
apps to the web.
Apple and Safari ushered
in the mobile web
with key technologies like
offline and geolocation.
And of course
Mozilla and Firefox,
who continue to shape the modern
web, from the initial Phoenix
Project, to SVG, and Canvas,
and to their critical privacy
and security work.
Meanwhile what started off
as a small group of coders
has now grown into a family of
more than 17 million developers
worldwide.
And we're on track to more
than double in the next decade.
About 1,000 of us are here
in San Francisco today.
And tens of thousands
more are watching
on the livestream in meetups
in places such as Amsterdam,
Brazil, and Uganda.
Hello, everyone.
And of course the
fact that each of us
can contribute to this amazing
community and this web's future
is what makes all
of this so unique.
When you consider our
contributions together,
they are staggering.
There are now more than 1.5
billion active sites and web
applications on
the internet today.
And they're serving more
than 4.5 billion users all
over the world.
It is a tremendous
responsibility and opportunity,
and one that's only possible
because of this incredible web
platform that we have.
Now, as a community,
we're going to debate
and we're going to even argue.
But that is how we create
something truly great.
After all, the
contributions to the web
come from everywhere, with no
single company or individual
owning it.
And that is very much
working as intended.
Celebrating the we
in web is naming
how we're better together
because of this diversity.
Because we're all here to
move the web platform forward.
And events like CDS, with
many different companies
and developers represented, are
really critical to reminding us
of this fact.
If you remember only one
thing from this morning,
please note that Chrome is here
today and every day to show up
as one small member of this
much, much bigger community.
And so with that in
mind, we're here at CDS
to highlight some of
our recent contributions
in three key areas.
So today we're going to talk
first about the platform
itself.
And as developers, we're highly
motivated to address some
of the web's key challenges.
For example, diversity
and reach of the web
is core to what is great
about the internet,
but it's also one of the
reasons why interoperability
remains a top concern.
This morning, Jon is going
to share some of our efforts
to improve interop, as well
as key investments we're
making in platform performance
and discoverability.
The second is
developer experience.
And Dion is going to share
some of the recent work we've
done on productivity,
frameworks, and open source.
And finally, the
Chrome browser itself.
Parisa is going to share
some of our investments
in a more helpful, inclusive
experience for our users.
But more importantly,
more than all of that, I
want to say thank you.
Thank you for all of you
for being here with us
this morning, and for spending
two very important days with us
as you continue and we continue
to invest in this broader
community.
As I said, the web is so
much more than one company,
one product, or one person.
And it's about how
we come together
to move the platform forward.
We're really grateful for a
chance to share with you today.
And so let's go ahead and
get started with Platform.
[MUSIC PLAYING, APPLAUSE]
JON KRAFCIK: Thanks, Anil.
The most exciting
part about the web
is that it enables
frictionless routing.
You can share any
experience through a link,
or discover it through
a search result,
and go right in with one tap.
The web's billions of
users and millions of sites
have been around for a while.
So where do we expect
the next wave of growth
to come to the web?
It's estimated that most
of the new internet users
globally will be coming online
in countries like India,
Indonesia, Mexico, and Nigeria,
users in developing markets,
across access to internet
through smartphones
with constrained
memory and storage.
So it's critical that web
applications are lightweight
and have great performance.
And in both developing
and developed markets,
teenagers and young adults are
growing up with smartphones
and frequently
computing cross-device.
These users have very
high expectations
around the overall
web experience.
So it's important for us
to equip the web platform
with powerful app
capabilities, and to ensure
the experiences remain
smooth, responsive, and easy
to navigate.
We see big brands
recognizing this shift.
With 65% of their first-time
users landing on mobile web,
Airbnb recently
built their website
into a progressive web app,
delivering better performance
and user experience.
Seeing the results that they
and many of our partners
have achieved by
investing in the web
inspires us to keep
pushing the web forward
and continue making
it more powerful.
With this in mind,
here are the themes
of our recent and future
developments to the web
platform.
We want to power fully
capable web applications,
deliver to users instant and
responsive web experiences,
and make transactions
between users, and merchants,
and payment providers
seamless and smooth.
Let's dive into the first one.
To ensure the web apps
ecosystem continues to thrive,
developers need the
same capabilities
as those found in native apps.
This includes application
installation, discovery,
integrations, and
multi-language support
to fully achieve feature parity.
Install is a foundational
feature of a progressive web
app.
And Chrome has supported
Install on mobile since 2016.
With the web, you can
focus on building your app,
and the browser takes care
of the details of how it
will work on the user's device.
And over the past year,
we've taken a step further,
with the launch of Progressive
Web App Install for desktop
directly from the browser.
You can now install on
Windows, Mac, Linux,
and of course Chrome OS.
To take installation and
discovery of web applications
to where your users truly
are, earlier this year, we
launched Trusted Web Activities.
Web content has been part
of the Android ecosystem
for a long time via WebView.
Trusted Web Activities offers a
high-performance, more secure,
and user-choice-preserving
way to build
apps that use the web stack.
This is our recommended way
to upload and distribute
high-quality PWAs in Play.
Partners such as Myntra, the
leading Indian e-commerce
brand, have used
Trusted Web Activities
to target their users
on lower-end devices,
and increased conversion rate
for these users by over 115%.
Other early adopters include
Latin-based publisher Terra,
and Indian affordable
hotels chain Oyo Rooms.
Oyo will be joining us later
today to share their story.
We're particularly excited
about the cross-browser support
Trusted Web
Activities is getting.
Our friends at
Mozilla have confirmed
they're experimenting with
TWA in their Firefox Preview
Nightly browser.
And Samsung has committed to
ship their own Trusted Web
Activity in the near future.
In 2015, we enabled
notifications
through service workers to
allow meaningful re-engagement
for web apps.
Over the past few years,
we've added many features
to notifications, including
action images, buttons,
and most recently, notification
triggers that give developers
the ability to
schedule notifications
even if your user's device
is on airplane mode.
With this last
addition, we believe
that notifications have
achieved feature parity
with their native
app counterparts.
And what's even more exciting
is a Trusted Web Activities
get all these
benefits by default.
We're committed to improving
the signal-to-noise ratio
of notifications, and we'll
share more through our CDS
Lightning Talk series.
We want web developers to
create the best app experiences.
And we've been
working thoughtfully
to bring APIs that unlock
OS-level capabilities.
Contact Picker API
allows your users
to share contacts and limited
details with a web app,
as you can see here
in Twitter's PWA.
We're putting a lot of care into
the design and implementation
of this API to ensure users have
full transparency and control.
And we're working closely with
some of our early adopters
to get this right.
Desktop apps, especially
those focused on productivity,
have long wanted
to come on the web.
But a major blocker has been
a lack of local file system
support.
So I'm happy to
announce that we're
bringing the very popular Native
File System API to Chrome.
This will allow web apps
to interact with files
on their user's local device.
Great for photo and
video editors, IDEs,
productivity tools, and more.
You can see it in action here
with apps like Corel's Graphic
Designer.
In addition to giving developers
powerful OS capabilities
and deeper integration,
we want developers
to be able to port
over their applications
with greater performance
and reliability.
WebAssembly allows you to bring
your existing mobile and/or
desktop applications
and libraries to the web
without needing to rewrite
them in JavaScript.
It uses a combination
of low-level primitives
and strong static
typing to deliver
predictable performance.
With additional features
like threads and SIMD,
applications can make full use
of modern multicore processors.
We're seeing many
web apps, especially
those focused on desktops
or large screens,
taking advantage of WebAssembly
to bring their apps to the web.
We're announcing at
the first WebAssembly
summit will take place
at the Google office
in Mountain View on
February 10, 2020,
to discuss upcoming features
and share more examples.
You can join this public
group to learn more.
Moving on to our second
theme, let's talk
about what we're
doing to make web
experiences instant,
rich, and more responsive.
We're moving the web towards
fast, beautiful, jank-free
navigation animations,
as well as great offline
and low-bandwidth experiences.
At I/O this May, we announced
that signed exchanges, services
that load your content faster
through privacy-preserving
prefetch, were available
in Chrome to all users.
We also gave a preview
of an experimental API
called Portals, enabling
you to dramatically improve
the user experience of
navigations across your site.
Portals allow you to create
seamless navigation experiences
by pre-rendering content
and optionally embedding it.
And like IFrames,
portals give you
the ability to navigate
users into this content,
and all at lightning speed.
Early Portals
partners like Fandango
built this fun new transition
style for their users
while navigating
within their site.
Notice how there
is no load time,
and the page rotates
to the right, a style
you don't see on
the web too often.
We're pleased to
announce that the Portals
API is available behind a
flag for you to experiment
with, and will soon be
available in origin trial
for same-origin use cases.
We are excited to
get your feedback.
With Portals, you can build
amazing user experiences.
But getting users to discover
and try these new experiences
can be challenging,
especially on mobile.
So we've been working
on a collection of APIs
and browser features
designed to improve
the discoverability of the web.
Imagine you're building
an app that periodically
has new content, and you want
to deliver this content even
when the browser isn't open.
For example, you could
deliver that content
while the user is
connected to home Wi-Fi,
before they go for their
commute, which might not
have great connectivity.
This is why we've been working
on an API call Periodic
Background Sync.
This API can practically cache
content at regular intervals,
making the content instantly
available for the user.
And to help users find the
best content, whether online
or offline, we've built
the Content Indexing API.
It allows you to make
your offline-enabled and
instantly-available content
visible to the user.
And we're exploring showing some
of this content on the New Tab
page and other
surfaces in Chrome.
Now, these readily
available pieces of content
are quite handy for discovery.
But what if you want to make web
loading disappear, supporting
completely online users?
What if you wanted
your content or app
to be flexibly
distributed, including
shared virally between users?
A web bundle is a new platform
primitive for packaging up
a website or web app.
It's blazingly fast to load,
unlocks easier offline support,
and is highly shareable.
Developers can use these
self-contained web bundles
to solve a flaky
connection issue for users.
And a web bundle can change
content distribution entirely.
A bundle can be shared between
devices, over chat or email,
on blogs alongside
a review, or even
on physical storage
like a USB stick.
In fact, we've bundled the
web.dev website, as well as
Squoosh, an image
optimization web app
that we demoed at CDS last
year on a dino-shaped USB flash
drive that you have
in your swag bag.
And we would love your feedback.
Our dino wanted a gaming
friend, so we also
threw in PROXX, the
Minesweeper-inspired web game
that we launched at
I/O earlier this year.
Form controls have long been
the bane of developers' lives,
to the point where many build
their own versions of controls
that are already in the browser.
We've worked with our
friends at Microsoft
to re-skin and improve the
accessibility of all form
elements.
And we're excited that
these will be shipping soon
in both Edge and Chrome.
We're also [INAUDIBLE]
features that you
need to improve the look
and feel of your sites.
Earlier this year, we
launched Backdrop Filter
so developers can build new
visual effects without having
to hard-code images.
And we're continuing our
investments in Houdini,
where you can now use
the Register Property
API to animate CSS variables
that were previously
impossible to animate.
We've been working on
making rendering and layout
performance, faster.
Earlier this year, we landed
the first phase of LayoutNG
in Chrome.
LayoutNG is a new implementation
of Chrome's layout algorithm
that promises much greater
performance and reliability.
It's optimized for
modern, dynamic content
and the wide variety of text
languages now on the web,
and most importantly, improves
the speed of rendering emojis.
Semicolon, close parentheses.
Display Locking
is a new API that
can have a massive impact
on rendering performance
on the web.
By locking an area of the DOM
and stopping it from rendering,
users can experience a
much higher frame rate
when scrolling through
long documents.
When a locked DOM
isn't rendered,
it is still searchable, which
is great for accessibility,
and page search, and
infinite scrollers.
And the best part is,
with Display Locking,
you can now perform
batch rendering updates.
Moving on to our third
theme, let's talk
about seamless and smooth
transactions on the web.
One of the biggest
opportunities we
have to increase web
developers' success
is to improve their
overall transaction volume,
reducing the friction between
merchants and their users,
making it easier for users
to let us know who they are,
to authenticate their
identity securely,
and to complete their purchases
by assisting with payment
handling and fraud prevention.
WebAuthn allows
hardware-secured, second-factor
authentication using
biometrics like fingerprints,
or hardware keys like a YubiKey.
WebAuthn continues
to see great growth.
Businesses like GitHub
and many more sites,
including Google Google
itself, have integrated it
into their authentication
flows to vastly improve
security for their users.
We've also heard that many
companies all over the world
need a way to validate the
user's phone number, especially
in countries like India, where
not all users have email.
So we're pleased to announce
this SMS receiver API.
This API allows you to verify
a phone number automatically,
and with less user abandonment,
using the SMS verification
codes that users
input manually today.
It's great to see
early partners,
like India's food delivery
service, Swiggy, implement it
into their PWA.
We're working on making payment
on the web simpler and safer.
Three years ago, we launched
the Payment Request API.
We're now seeing great adoption,
with over 15,000 origins
using web payments to complete
a transaction in Chrome.
Even better, web payment
API transaction volume
has doubled since the
beginning of the year.
Our focus for the next year
is to add more capabilities
to Web Payments API, enable
more sites and native apps
to be able to process payments.
The web's success
relies on the principle
of open source, transparency,
collaboration, and most
importantly, community.
We launched Chromium as
an open-source project
with the vision to allow
everyone to contribute,
and anyone to share
our foundations.
And today we're happy
to see that almost
every individual browser
project is open source.
We believe that working
successfully with other browser
vendors can unlock significant
innovations on the web.
Working with Firefox,
Chrome was able to implement
a difficult-to-ship feature,
stale-while-revalidate,
that, based on
experimental data,
has lifted publisher
revenue by 0.5% thanks
to a 2% increase in
early ad script loads,
and resulting 0.3% ad
impression increase.
We're also excited to see
the amazing contributions
from our friends at Edge,
who we recently welcomed
to the Chromium ecosystem.
They're already making
major improvements
to accessibility, scrolling,
and media battery life.
We want to continue working
with our browsers and ecosystem
partners to bring many more wins
for our developers and users.
And to speak more
about what we're
doing to unlock
developer success,
let me invite Dion to the stage.
[MUSIC PLAYING, APPLAUSE]
DION ALMAER: Thanks, Jon.
I considered rebranding myself
the Caps Lock Dion today,
but probably shouldn't do that--
little cheap, I know.
So as we've heard, we think
the open web is pretty special.
Jon mentioned the low friction
of links, and how they get you
immediately into an experience.
And when someone browses
from my site to your site,
they feel the web as one.
So how does the
web feel in 2019?
We use the HTTP Archive to
see how the web is built,
and the Chrome User
Experience Report, or CRUX,
to see how it's experienced.
And this story feels promising.
Over the past year, we've
seen positive growth
in the percentage of sites,
with fast first contentful paint
and first input delay,
our core metrics
for loading and interactivity.
Now, it's great that the
web at large is improving.
But we also know there's a
little bit of work to be done.
And do you know how
your sites are doing?
One simple way to
find out is just
to enter a URL into
PageSpeed Insights
to get actionable
recommendations
for a single page.
Now, if you need help
identifying hotspots
or potential problems
across your site, good news,
we just released a new speed
report in the Search Console,
which will give you insights
by showing groups of pages
and how they perform
for each key metric that
is captured by CRUX.
Now we know that measuring
user experience quality
is multifaceted,
and we're always
working to integrate metrics
that tell a fuller picture.
This week, you'll hear us
talking about some new metrics.
For example, LCP, or
Largest Contentful Paint,
measures how quickly users
see the largest and often most
meaningful content on a page,
like a hero image or main text.
LCP is built on top of the
element timing API, which
allows you to manually annotate
elements that you care about.
Now, we've all experienced this
moment, when a paint changes
just when you tap.
It's always incredibly
frustrating.
It'll happen to me, probably,
again this Black Friday.
So with CLS, or
Cumulative Layout Shift,
it measures the degree
to which content
may be shifting on the screen.
This metric is built on
top of the Layout Stability
API, which enables you to
identify and fix such issues.
So each of these new
metrics are backed
with specs and web
platform tests,
allowing run providers
to collect them.
And we're really happy
to see key ecosystem
players such as
Calibre and SpeedCurve
integrating these metrics
into their products.
And we spend a
lot of time diving
into data from the
HTTP Archive and CRUX,
as it gives us insights on where
to focus our platform efforts.
This real-world data, we
think, is really critical,
which is why we ensure that
it's fully available to you
and the entire community.
Now, it's also kind
of fun to poke around
in the data little bit.
For example,
hypothetically speaking,
maybe you're up late
the night before
giving a talk in the keynote,
trying to think about things.
And you find yourself
wondering, like,
what is the largest
z-Index value on the web?
So you take a look at HTTP
Archive, and what do you think?
Any guesses?
10?
Maybe higher?
[LAUGHTER]
Anyone?
1,000?
A million?
Would you be shocked
at 780 digits?
That's more than a
googol of digits.
That's a lot of digits.
And so I just got thinking
about how, like, there's
some poor web
developer, and they're
shouting at the screen,
div, I need you on top.
[LAUGHTER]
And then you got to take a
look at the actual code, right?
This is the actual code.
And I love the "important" at
the end, the "!important--"
make sure.
And the comment at the top--
"FIXED."
Done, we're all done.
It's fantastic.
Love the web.
So data is great, but insights
lead to fixes and improvement.
We're often asked,
how do I actually
act on this information?
So we collaborated with experts
from across the community
to build what we're
calling the Web Almanac.
We're launching the
first 17 chapters today,
on topics from markup, to
HTTP, to PWA, and many more.
Now I want to give
a big shout-out,
because there's tons
of collaborators
from across the industry.
And I want to thank them for
not only the amazing work
they did on this
project, but all they
do for the web in general.
So can we give around of
applause for the collaborators?
[APPLAUSE]
So, many of you also
go the extra mile
to move the metrics in
the right direction.
And we want to reward
you for the hard work
that results in great
web experiences.
So we've been looking at how
can we highlight and surface
more quality
signals to our users
across search and Chrome's UI,
with speed as a core metric.
So we've been playing around
with UI explorations like this
to make sure that we give
you even more of an incentive
to work on perf.
You're going to be
excited about this.
So next up, we want to talk
more about the ecosystem
and the tooling that's going to
help you create this great web
content.
I think it's pretty safe to
say that no other platform has
quite the same level of
innovation in user space,
through frameworks, libraries,
and CMSes, many of which
have become household names.
Adam Bradley from Ionic
recently asked for feedback
on the history of
web frameworks, which
sparked a typical healthy
discussion on Twitter
and a trip down memory lane.
And we love how each
framework innovates and learns
from each other.
We've been excited to see
the innovation continue
across the board, especially
in the area of performance
and developer experience.
This is very much
true for Next.js,
an impressive framework
that gives React developers
an end-to-end system to allow
for scalable performance.
We've been working
with the Next.js team,
and thought it'd
be fun to invite
Guillermo Rauch
from Zeit onstage
to take us through
the journey so far.
Let's welcome Guillermo.
[MUSIC PLAYING, APPLAUSE]
At Zeit, we have a
very simple mission.
We want to empower
developers like you
to build, deploy, and scale the
best websites and applications.
About three years ago, we
identified an opportunity
to foster this mission
in the React space.
We identify that creating a
React website or application
was very tedious.
It required bringing all these
different components together,
every time, for
every single project.
But we had a very unique idea.
What if it just took one command
to start developing a React
app, one command to build
it, and your interface
to the project was a very
simple file-system-based API,
where you just create
a folder and put
a bunch of React components
in there, and get everything
figured out for you.
And I'm happy to report that
that same idea we had three
years ago is still true today.
So we kept that simplicity
with a remarkable attention
to backwards compatibility.
This project, Next.js, has
always been about that.
We wanted to capture the
spectrum of complexity
and evolution of your projects.
We thought that you
needed to have an easy way
to start, but then an easy way
to evolve your project, that it
should be good
for an individual,
but it should also
be great for a team,
and as well as capturing
the complexities
and intricacies of React
rendering technologies,
like going from
static site generation
to advanced server rendering.
We've done this so well
that every time you
go onto your favorite
websites today,
you're probably interfacing
with Next.js, sometimes
in a small way,
sometimes in a big way.
We have customers that
span from media, to SaaS,
to maybe your favorite streaming
service for music or video.
If it's a static app, or if
it's something very complex,
Next.js has found its place in a
variety of different industries
and use cases.
And this has been
possible, as Anil
was saying, because we took
this approach, which is
the approach of the open web.
We have an internal
team that has
seen a lot of amazing
stewards of this project
propel Next.js
forward, but we've also
included hundreds
of contributors
from the open source community,
and incredible partners,
companies like GoDaddy and Hulu,
that bet massively on Next.js,
but then also
decided to give back.
If you're curious about how
they're using our framework,
I encourage you to check out the
Hulu case study on our website.
But my favorite partner is
a very special and prolific
partner.
They're very, very
productive people.
So Google Chrome
reached out to us
earlier this year
with an intention
to make the web better.
And they shared our key view
that great developer experience
has to marry great performance.
And they know this
better than anyone
because they built
the Web Inspector.
But it's very, very
important, just like Next.js
goes from small to big,
it has to be easy to use,
and it has to be very
fast for the end user.
So we've been
really busy working
on a different set of features
for improving Next.js.
Some of them have to do
with developer experience,
like an easier way to import
CSS into your React project.
Some of them have to do with
staying close to the cutting
edge of their latest and
greatest React features,
like adding support for
Concurrent and Strict mode.
And some of them have to do
with just bundling and compiling
your projects better.
So I'm really excited
about these changes,
in particular
because earlier I was
talking about great support
for backwards compatibility.
So some of the changes the
Google Chrome team has helped
us land, such as
improved web bundling,
have helped people
in the real world.
So one of our favorite
customers, Barnebys,
they run an incredible
search engine
for arts and collectibles.
And being in the
e-commerce space,
performance is of the essence.
After they upgraded Next.js--
with zero code changes,
thanks to the contributions
that Chrome made--
they saw nearly 25%
to 30% improvement
in size of the bundles
of the main application.
But that also translated into
just a snappier and smoother
experience that helped everyone
that visited their website.
This is possible thanks for
those amazing contributions.
If you want to learn more
about what specifically went
into making these improvements,
please check out our session
tomorrow at around 11:00 AM,
led by Hussein and Tim Neutkens,
who are going to talk about
all the internals of what
went into making and
landing these improvements.
Finally, if you're interested
about Next.js and want to check
it out, please go
to nextjs.org/learn,
where a five-minute tutorial
will just guide you through all
the essentials.
And you'll be productive
building React applications
in no time.
Thank you.
DION ALMAER: Thank
you, Guillermo.
[APPLAUSE]
That's awesome.
So we want to support
as many ecosystem
players to unlock
performance wins by default,
and so much more.
We announced the Framework Fund
at the last Chrome Dev Summit.
We've been really
excited to see the impact
that these projects are
having, and we're really
keen to fund more.
Now you live in content
creation and app development
tools all day.
And the breadth of the
tools that the web has
are pretty phenomenal, from no
code, to low code, to pro code,
whatever those mean.
And of course, for Anil, Vim.
Yes, and Emacs-- anyway,
we're not going to go there.
[CHUCKLING]
We want these tools to thrive,
and for them to get access
to everything they need from
the web platform and our data
and insight tools.
We also want to ensure that
our tools are doing everything
they can to help you.
First, the metrics
that I mentioned
will now be reflected
across our tools,
including Lighthouse
and Chrome DevTools.
And to help you
understand these metrics,
we're adding clear guidance on
web.dev, our primary developer
website, which expanded
today with great content.
Now in Lighthouse, we recently
announced our very first
stack pack.
This one was for
WordPress, and allowed
us to extend the general
guidance to include
actionable WordPress advice.
Today we're releasing
a stack pack
for the open-source
e-commerce platform Magento,
as well as expanding
our coverage
to include packs for web
frameworks such as Angular,
React, and AMP.
Now, content
platforms are actually
powering more than
half of the web.
And we've been
working really closely
with dozens of them, in some
areas, investing deeply.
At WordCamp US,
just two weeks ago,
we announced the 1.0 release
of Site Kit for WordPress,
which helps content
creators by making
it easy to set up and access
multiple Google tools directly
in WordPress.
Now, we've also been working
with the WordPress community
to improve site health and
performance by simplifying
HTTPS migrations,
prototyping image lazy load,
using font display
swap to accelerate
text rendering, and much more.
And then there's Shopify.
We've been really impressed
with the performance work
that they've been shipping
for all of their merchandise.
One example of
impact at scale is
how they rolled out WebP
support across their platform,
and saw a 60% decrease
in bytes served.
In one extreme case, they
saw savings of over 210 megs
on a single page, which
made me wonder, what
are the z-indexes on that page?
[CHUCKLING]
So we're super excited
to see our tools become
more powerful, integrated,
and open to the ecosystem.
In fact, let me stop
talking for a little bit,
and instead please
join me in welcoming
Elizabeth and Paul to show
some of the new features we've
landed across our
tools, and highlight
how you can use them together
to make web development easier
thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING, APPLAUSE]
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Thank
you Caps Lock Dion.
I am Elizabeth.
PAUL IRISH: I'm Paul.
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
And we are really
excited to work for
Chrome Web Platform team,
and be with you here today.
So we've been working
really hard to make sure
that you have a really
consistent experience
across all of our tools.
And we wanted to take a moment
to walk through from diagnosis
to an actual solution, what
that fix workflow looks
like for performance.
So we also want to
practice what we preach,
so we're going to be
using one of our own sites
to try to optimize it,
web.dev, for this demo.
All right, Paul, you good to go?
PAUL IRISH:
[EXHALING DRAMATICALLY]
Let's do this.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: OK, awesome.
So the first thing
Paul is going to do
is jump into the Audit
panel in DevTools,
where you can run a
Lighthouse report locally
on your own machine.
So he's just going to run the
performance category for now,
right?
PAUL IRISH: Just performance.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: OK, cool.
So it should just
be a few seconds.
And I was told to dance
here, but none of you
want to see me dancing.
This is all pad.
OK, all right, cool.
So the performance score is OK.
But we chose a page that
we know we can improve.
So let's see, there seemed
to be a few images that
are a little bigger.
PAUL IRISH: Yeah, OK.
Yeah, a few images here,
they're just oversized.
Let's--
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Do
you want to tackle them?
PAUL IRISH: Let's just focus
on spa kittens, I guess?
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
Definitely spa kittens.
PAUL IRISH: Yeah, it
looks like it's 79K.
And it could be quite
a lot much smaller.
OK, that's spa kittens.
Good, yeah.
All right, let's
go check it out.
So it's down here.
Good, yes.
Image tag.
Ah, OK, yeah.
1800 pixels wide image,
but shown at just 527 wide.
So, way oversized.
OK, we could fix this.
And so I think probably the
fix that we're going to do,
we'll just use responsive
images, source set
kind of thing.
And I cheated a little bit.
I do know that there's already
a responsive image on this page.
So we're going to
just make use of that.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to take just the file
name of spa kittens.
And then we're going to
go find this other one.
OK, here you can see
like the full source set.
And we're just going
to edit this attribute,
and just replace this.
Command-D, Paste, boom.
OK, yeah, there we go.
All right, now we're going
to take the HTML of this,
and we're going to go
and copy it over into--
use my favorite feature in
DevTools, Local Overrides.
All right, so now we're
going to go down and find
the original spa
kittens image tag.
And we'll just delete that,
and then paste in the new one.
And then hit Control-S.
And then we should refresh.
And let's just verify that that
actually applied to the page.
Yes, OK, good, yeah.
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
So can we actually
rerun Lighthouse to see
if it fixed it though?
PAUL IRISH: Yeah, sure.
Yeah, OK.
So let's take a
look at Lighthouse.
We'll go back up and rerun.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: All
right, come on spa kittens.
PAUL IRISH: Hey Elizabeth, how
do you get a tissue to dance?
But a little boogie in it.
[CHUCKLING]
ELIZABETH SWEENY: The sad part
is that I knew the punchline.
PAUL IRISH: [CHUCKLES] OK.
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
All right, cool.
PAUL IRISH: Ooh, much better.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Amazing.
So, OK.
PAUL IRISH: And
then check it out.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Thank you.
All right.
PAUL IRISH: It's not
even there anymore.
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
It's not there.
So I know you pretty well.
And I'm going to
guess that you already
have a PR ready to go
that'll fix this in source.
Am I right?
PAUL IRISH: Yes.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Fabulous.
PAUL IRISH: I got a PR.
Let's see.
Let's switch over.
Yep, yep, PR for web.dev.
Just start it out.
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
Yeah you're so good.
OK, so we want to make sure that
we validate that the change is
actually good, though, and
convince the entire team
that this is actually going
to be a sustainable fix.
So with that, we
want to take a moment
to introduce Lighthouse CI.
It runs Lighthouse automatically
on every single commit.
And we're super-jazzed about it.
PAUL IRISH: Yeah, yeah.
This is rad stuff.
All right, so--
ELIZABETH SWEENY: And we've
already added Lighthouse CI
to the GitHub repo, right?
PAUL IRISH: Yeah.
So let me show that.
So if we just
scroll down, we can
see we have the integration
right there in the pull
request.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Awesome.
And this allows us to do a few
cool new things, one of which
is actually being able
to see an overview.
So you can see the performance
of all of your pages
over time for all the
report categories.
This is an automated
collection of all
of your Lighthouse report
categories on every commit.
That's including
the state of audits,
as well as the values of
your performance metrics.
So one of the main
things we want to do
is actually compare the quality
of our PR against master to see
if we've done anything
that causes regressions
before the change
actually goes live
and users have to deal with it.
So there has to be a better
way to do it, though--
PAUL IRISH: --than
toggling back and forth.
ELIZABETH SWEENY: Than just
toggling between two reports,
right?
PAUL IRISH: Yeah.
So we've focused a lot on
this kind of experience, what
actually made a change here.
And so let me show you
kind of how that works.
So if we actually just go
back to that pull request,
and we click through
on the status check,
so this is the new diff
view for Lighthouse CI.
Let's bump this up.
So we see the 3-point difference
in the performance score.
And we see all the changes
that happen to all the metrics.
They're all going down,
which is an improvement.
We like that.
And let's go check out
properly-sized images.
Looks like we have
a change there.
Yeah, OK, cool.
So yeah, I made
them all responsive.
And so they're removed
from the report.
The [INAUDIBLE]
savings is all gone.
So we fixed it.
And check this out--
yeah, for all the
images on the page,
we've reduced the total weight
of images by half a meg.
So this is pretty cool.
ELIZABETH SWEENY:
Yeah, that's amazing.
So if you would like to learn
more about Lighthouse CI as
well as other speed
tooling updates,
please join us
later for our talk.
But until then,
thank you very much.
PAUL IRISH: Thanks, guys.
[APPLAUSE]
DION ALMAER: Super
excited about the tool.
The Lighthouse score, not so
excited about, by the way.
So, thanks.
I'm so excited to
learn how we're
working to improve the web
and make you successful,
no matter what framework
you use, what CMS you use.
What I really hope is that
you set bold quality goals,
and use our tools and
services to understand
the experience your
users are getting,
and then create the high-quality
experiences that we all
want to see as a link
on our worldwide web.
Now, finally, I do
have one something
I'm a little bit
embarrassed to admit.
And that's see, you see
these Chrome Dev Summit URLs?
I'm really angry.
They don't actually work.
Like, you put them in the
browser, and they don't work.
But to be clear,
Chrome loves URLs.
I want to make that very clear.
And to tell you
more about Chrome,
please welcome Parisa
from the browser team.
[MUSIC PLAYING, APPLAUSE]
PARISA TABRIZ: Thank
you, Caps Lock Dion.
Cheerio, chap.
He's going to tell me how far
or close Sam to "Downton Abbey"
afterwards.
Hello, everyone.
Hope you're enjoying Dev Summit.
As Anil mentioned, when we think
about the future of the web,
we're considering 4
and 1/2 billion users.
And this isn't just users
who are coming online
for the first time
in emerging markets,
it's also young users who are
primarily using their phones.
Now, in Chrome,
we really, really
believe that every existing
user and future user
deserves an amazing experience.
And so I want to share
just a couple of the ways
that we're trying to
deliver on that experience.
A lot of our focus has been
around three key goals--
how do we make the
web perform better,
web more accessible,
and how do we make the web
more safe and trustworthy.
So let's talk about
performance first.
Now, we believe that the web
is for everyone, no matter what
your device, what
your internet speed,
or what your purchasing power.
And that's why we
invest in performance
with consideration for just
a huge range of devices.
OK, when it comes to RAM, we
have senior memes, all of them.
And we laugh with
you, but we also
work hard to not give
you as much fodder.
And for memory, it's a
really delicate balance.
Because sometimes when
you use more memory,
it actually can lead to a faster
user experience via caching.
And it also makes possible
additional security
mitigations.
But we obviously know,
if you use too much,
it can actually impact
the user experience.
We have lots of people
dedicated to figuring out just
what is the optimal
usage for Chrome
given a user's available
CPU and memory resources.
And we've been investing
more here lately.
One of the things
that we've done
is developed
automated tooling so
that we can find memory
leaks or UI jank in the wild,
and get engineers enough
information so they actually
can debug and fix those issues.
And after a lot of work and
via the help of this tooling,
we've made a couple
of achievements
that we're pretty proud of.
So what we've seen
in the past year
is an 8x reduction in UI
thread jank in the main browser
process.
And we've also seen a 15% CPU
reduction and 50% reduction
in physical memory for
background tabs in the browser.
Now, that's pretty good.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
We're proud of this
work, but we totally
know it's an ongoing effort.
And this is something we're
going to continue to invest in.
So that's the browser.
When it comes to V8,
we've also made a number
of memory reductions here.
For example, we reduced
render in the memory footprint
by about 5%.
And we actually expect
further reduction of about 12%
via V8 pointer compression,
which is literally rolling out
right now.
So more cool improvements.
But people want
to see to believe.
And so you can see
from this video--
within V8, we've massively
reduced parsing time.
And so now Google
Sheets loads way faster.
This is a comparison of Chrome
today versus Chrome a year ago.
And again, if you're into
stats, this is about 33% faster.
So thanks to V8.
And at I/O this year,
we announced a couple
of improvements that
developers just get by default.
And I wanted to just
give an update on those.
So the first one that
we're excited to share
relates to image lazy load.
And this is now
going to be enabled
by default for all
Chrome light mode users.
Now, lazy load is
when the browser
prioritizes loading images or
IFrames in the current view.
And so it'll actually
defer loading elements
outside of the view until
the user scrolls to it.
This means that all
Chrome light mode
users are going to get
even more data savings,
and they're going to
get even faster content
in view experience.
And so that's great for
default users in light mode.
Developers can also
just enable this
by adding one line of text.
And then second
update, and something
that's coming in a couple months
is launching Paint Holding.
Now, Paint Holding
is where the browser
will wait very, very briefly
before starting to paint.
So the page renders
as a whole rather than
jumping different
elements around.
And it just avoids kind of
what is a distracting kind
of white splash.
And so again, just by default,
giving users a better, more
smooth experience.
So performance is one big
area of ongoing investment.
But access to the web isn't
just about performance.
It's also about making
content accessible.
For example, users who
are blind or low vision
are often using a screen
reader or Braille display.
And unfortunately, these
users will typically hear,
"image," "unlabeled graphic,"
or a long, irrelevant filename
read aloud whenever they're on a
page that has unlabeled images.
And obviously this can be a
pretty frustrating experience.
So this is something
that we wanted
to help those users with.
Now, we used Google AI
to automatically generate
descriptions of images.
So now if users turn on
the Get Image Descriptions
from Google feature,
Chrome is going
to automatically
generate descriptions
of unlabeled images.
And so just as an example, if
a user came on this image, then
they might actually
hear, "appears
to be fruits and
vegetables at a market."
So as you all know, it
is still best practice
for developers to actually add
their own Alt text to images.
Because you know the context
of your content best.
But this feature is
really just intended
to help bridge some
of the existing gaps
that we know are present
in the web today.
And our team has set
a goal for ourselves
to just really meet
the highest level
of accessibility standards.
And we've made a lot of
progress on this, and in general
are just thrilled to see
users finding improvements
helpful in Chrome.
Just recently,
Chrome was actually
named one of the most used
browsers among blind users.
And this was according to a
survey by the Web Accessibility
In Mind group, and something
that we're proud of, just
given all the effort into
making Chrome more accessible.
And also have a lot
more work to do here.
But very much driven
by the mission
to make sure that
we're building helpful
features so that,
really, technology
can empower everybody.
Of course, in order to be
truly empowered by the web,
it has to be safe
and trustworthy,
not just for Chrome
users, but for everyone.
And so I want to a little
bit about some of the ways
that we've been
investing in doing that.
Internet-wide safety
absolutely demands
industry-wide collaboration.
And together-- and really, I do
mean from people in the room,
and people in the livestream--
I'm proud to say that we've
made some huge progress on HTTPS
adoption.
Today, 90 of the top 100
sites now default to HTTPS,
and that's up from only
about 25 back in 2016.
From what we see, 90%
of all web traffic
at Google across popular
operating systems,
both desktop and mobile,
is now over HTTPS.
And that's just a
huge accomplishment.
So--
[APPLAUSE]
As a next step,
Chrome is investing
in continuing to improve
the security of HTTPS.
And we're going
to begin blocking
all mixed content or insecure
HTTP content loaded on HTTPS
pages by default. And since
we're asking developers
to do some work as we always do,
we know this takes some time,
and we're going to be rolling
this out over the next four
milestones.
We're also experimenting
with new ways
to make DNS more secure.
So as you know, DNS is
the addressing system
of the internet, and just
a really essential piece
of how the internet works.
Unfortunately, it remains
one of the last non-encrypted
channels.
And this potentially
exposes users
to privacy leaks, or phishing
attacks, or pharming attacks.
And a lot of members
of the web community
have tried to improve
this over time,
but just nothing has really
taken off until more recently.
Now the latest proposal
from the web community
is called DNS over HTTPS.
As a browser, this obviously
plays to our strengths.
But DNS has been around
for 35-plus years.
And so changing it is just
a really complex endeavor.
And it's one that we are
being really deliberately
conservative about.
So we're only going to upgrade
Chrome users to DNS over HTTPS
if we already know that their
DNS providers support it.
And we think that this
is the right approach
to balance user choice and
control while also delivering
significant improvements that
we see for security and privacy.
Now, if there's one topic that
takes over most of the browser
safety and trust
conversationally lately,
it's privacy, and in
particular cookies.
So earlier this
year, at I/O, I've
made some announcements
that we're
committed to making controls for
third-party cookies just more
usable and more visible.
And we've already kicked
off some early experiments.
You can check it
out in Incognito,
which is our mode that we know
a lot of privacy-conscious users
will turn to you.
And in parallel,
we're continuing
to just make progress on plans
to improve the existing cookie
infrastructure.
We recently
announced that Chrome
is going to start enforcing
accurate cookie classification
beginning in February,
and in particular,
looking for developers
to be able to specify
whether their cookies
are to be used
in a first-party or third-party
classification context.
And this is just going to
make cookies more secure,
and also make our tracking
controls more accurate.
Other browsers have
announced that they're
joining us in this effort.
And then one more thing I
want to talk about on privacy,
but we're just continuing
to innovate on our privacy
sandbox.
And what this is is
a secure environment
for personalization,
including ads.
And it also protects
user privacy.
So since the August
announcement,
we've announced two
intents to implement--
Click Conversion Measurement
and Trust Token APIs.
Check them out.
We'd love your feedback.
And you'll hear
a little bit more
about these in the
next talk at 11:00.
Of course you can't have
privacy without security.
And our philosophy
in Chrome is that you
shouldn't have to be a security
expert to stay safe online.
And so as much as
possible, we try
to build security in by
default. So since the beginning,
we've built in
protections to just warn
users of
potentially-dangerous sites
that may try to phish
their credentials
or install malware, and
then also really invest
in regularly updating users
with the latest security
updates or features.
And so I want to talk
about just two things
we're proud of from
this past year.
Passwords-- everyone
knows about passwords.
Compromised passwords
remain one of the biggest
risks to users on the web.
And that's why we continue to
invest in our Password Manager.
Today, not only can Chrome users
safely store their passwords,
but they can also generate
unique, strong passwords
for all sites on either
desktop and mobile.
And what we'll be bringing
to you by the end of the year
is actually a Chrome that
will proactively warn you
if we detect that
any of your passwords
have been compromised.
And this way, as a user,
you can actually just
take additional protections to
protect those online accounts
which may be at risk.
And then finally
another accomplishment
is just bringing Site
Isolation to Android.
So Site Isolation is like
the next major advancement
in browser sandboxing.
And it protects users from
speculative execution attacks.
You may have heard of Spectre,
which got a lot of headlines
two years ago.
And bringing this to
Android was actually
only possible because of a
lot of the memory savings
that we made that I described
earlier in the talk.
And so kudos to the teams
that have made this possible.
Overall, we feel a huge
responsibility in Chrome
to continue to bring helpful
innovation to just make
the web perform better,
make it more accessible,
and stay ahead of
users' expectations
when it comes to
security and privacy.
And I cannot underscore that
this would not be possible
without the support of
the developer community,
and just everybody who's
contributing to the ecosystem.
So truly thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
With that, I'm going
to call Anil back
on stage just for
some closing words.
ANIL SABHARWAL: Reflecting
back on my own story,
if I could take you back
to 1993 for a second,
there is no way
that kid growing up
in Montreal on that
Commodore Amiga 4000 ever
thought that he'd be standing
here with all of you today.
And that is what makes
the web so great.
As an open platform, it
opens up possibilities
for millions of developers
and billions of people
all over the world.
If you see a need in your
community, all you have to do
is build something on
the web immediately,
and you can push it live with no
friction, and no one of having
to approve anything.
It's available for
everyone instantly.
All you need to do
is give them a link.
And that's the power of the web.
And together, we can
continue to move it forward.
In fact, a great
example of this work
that I'd love to
highlight of building
powerful, accessible
web experiences,
is Zlto, a startup that's using
virtual incentives to make
real-world economic impact.
As we close this
morning's keynote,
let's listen to their story.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[END PLAYBACK]
[APPLAUSE]
ANIL SABHARWAL: We're
actually honored
to have Allan and his CTO, Kurt,
in the audience here today.
So thank you, Allan and Kurt.
[APPLAUSE]
So that's it for this
morning's keynote.
So thank you for letting me,
the Chrome team, and Google
continue to be part of this
really amazing community.
Here's to the we in web.
And I really hope you enjoy
the rest of the seminar.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]