BEN MORSS: If you've seen the
talk at Chrome Dev Summit,
you already know
that much of the web
is too slow, too
heavy, and inefficient,
making sites hard to use for
people on slower connections
or lower-powered devices.
Your site may work great
on your $1,000 phone
in your major metropolis.
But someone in a rural
area or another country
may find your site frustrating
or simply unusable.
What if you could
keep your site's look
and feel while making it
accessible to everyone?
What if you could make your site
more elegant, leaner, and more
maintainable with less code?
This is why AMP was
created, to make
it simple for all
developers to create
fast, lean sites for all users.
So what is AMP?
First, fundamentally, AMP
is a web components library.
Working on all
major browsers, it
provides new HTML tags that
do the work you'd normally
do with JavaScript.
AMP is also a set of
guidelines on how to create
fast sites for everyone.
It requires HTML attributes
that enable accessibility.
It stops you from
including too much CSS.
And JavaScript can only be
used in a context where it
can't harm the user experience.
Sites that follow the
rules of AMP get a bonus.
Caches like Google
store AMP pages
so that they can be loaded from
search in less than a second,
even on 3G.
While it's most known
for pure content sites,
AMP also provides tools
to create interactivity.
We'll talk about two
ways to do this--
the old way, which we'll call
AMP Classic, and AMP Script,
which we'll just call,
well, AMP script.
We could also call them
JavaScript Light and JavaScript
Pro.
So first, AMP Classic--
for this, we'll use some
examples from our AMP Camp demo
site and some that aren't.
Let's say that when the
user taps this button,
we want to open a menu.
For this, we use AMP
Events and Actions.
AMP processes browser
events into AMP events
and exposes those to
you, the developer.
For example, when a user clicks
a mouse or taps a touchscreen,
AMP fires an event called Tap.
AMP actions allow you to
change things on your page.
For example, to
show a Dom element,
we'd use an action called Show.
To toggle its visibility, we'd
use an action called Toggle.
And that's how we open the menu.
Notice the form here, on
equals tap sidebar toggle.
Tap is the event.
Sidebar is the ID of the
element we're acting on.
And Toggle is the action.
Next, how about server calls?
When a user visits
our site, we want
to call an API to find out how
many items are in their cart
and then show this
on the screen.
For this, we use two components
that work well together,
AMP Lists and AMP Mustache.
AMP lists sends an XHR
request to an endpoint.
The data returned gets formatted
through a Mustache template.
Here's how this
works on AMP Camp.
On page load, AMP List calls
the end point specified
in the source attribute.
Our API returns JSON that
contains the number of items
in the user's cart.
AMP then plugs that JSON
into this Mustache template.
If there is a count, that
gets displayed at a span.
If the count is zero,
we display nothing--
simple.
Finally, to change what's
on the screen in response
to user actions, AMP lets
you store application data
in HTML state variables and bind
expressions to Dom elements.
Here's a simple example.
We start with the
state variable called
Team that contains an object
with one property, Star,
whose value is
initialized to Yao Ming.
Now, here's a P
tag with something
unusual, an attribute
called Text in Brackets.
These brackets let AMP know
this is a bound attribute.
We've bound this to the
expression Team dot Star
plus Is Tall.
When that expression's
value changes,
so will the content
of the P tag.
Now, remember
actions and events?
Here, we're saying that
when this button is tapped,
go into our team's
state variable
and change the value of Star
to Yao Ming and Mandarin.
And here's the results.
You tap this button and the
text on the screen changes.
Now let's put all this together.
We can use data binding
to change API endpoints.
On our site's
Product Listing page,
our user can filter
and search results.
Each time they make
a selection, we
call our API to retrieve
the appropriate JSON.
When the user makes a new
selection under Sort By,
AMP fires an event
called Change.
Then we store their selection in
the filter property of a state
variable called Products.
Meanwhile, we've found the
source property of this AMP
list to an expression
that calculates
the query string for the API.
So when the user
makes a selection,
the product's object
changes and the expression
is recomputed, which then
triggers a new server call.
And presto, new products appear.
You might be excited to
try out these techniques
or you might just be saying,
why can't I just use JavaScript?
The AMP team loves
JavaScript too.
But part of the
promise of AMP is
that JavaScript isn't allowed
to block the main thread
and slow things
down for the user.
Fortunately, now
there's a solution.
You may have heard talk about
[? Worker Rides ?] JavaScript.
It's the new hotness.
The nice thing is
JavaScript and a Web Worker
runs in a separate thread so it
doesn't block the main thread
or user interactions.
The problem is workers
can't access the Dom.
So how can a worker
control web interactions?
AMP's Script provides
a clever solution.
It maintains a copy of the
Dom and the worker itself.
When something changes
in the real Dom,
AMP Script changes the copy in
its virtual Dom and vice versa.
This makes [? Worker Rides ?]
JavaScript easy.
To preserve AMP's
performance guarantee,
scripts can only run
after a user interaction,
not on page load.
And your code can't exceed 150k.
AMP Script that's
pretty exciting.
But it's so new that at the
time of making this video,
we haven't yet had
time to include it
in our AMP Camp site.
Hopefully by the time
you see this, we will.
I urge you to try
these techniques.
If you don't like
them, by all means
create your interactive
site in another way.
You don't have to use AMP.
But I will say, it's still
hard and rare for non-AMP sites
to be as fast and
lean as AMP sites.
It takes effort and discipline.
And especially on
larger teams, it's
simply hard to avoid
excessive JS and CSS.
AMP can be a product
manager, your scrum
master urging you onward.
So why not give this a try?
Check the links in the
video description for more
information and
for documentation,
as well as for links to the AMP
Camp demo site and the AMP Camp
code on GitHub.
Thanks for watching.
And see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]