MINKO GECHEV: Hello, everyone.
My name is Minko Gechev.
I'm a senior developer
programs engineer
in the Angular team at Google.
In this video, I'm
going to tell you
how to improve the user
experience of your app
by using predictive prefetching.
Imagine that we're
in the subway,
waiting for the next train.
In the meantime, we open
our favorite Wikipedia app
and decide to learn
more about cheese.
Just around the time it gets
tasty, our train arrives.
We get into the car and depart.
While sitting there, we decide
to continue reading more,
but we have a poor signal.
We start angrily
rage-clicking on the links,
but it doesn't help.
It just makes the situation
even more frustrating.
Let us see how we can
use prefetching for fewer
rage-clicking experiences.
First, let us explain
what is prefetching.
Imagine a user is reading the
cheese article from before.
In the background, we
can download and cache
the content associated
with other pages
that there are likely
to be needed next,
so when they perform
a navigation,
they can have an
instant experience.
There are different
prefetching strategies.
For example, we can prefetch
all the assets in the app,
prefetch only the assets
associated with visible links,
initiate prefetching when the
user's cursor is above link,
or apply predictive prefetching.
Predictive prefetching
is a technique
that uses methods from data
analytics and machine learning
to provides a
data-driven approach.
In order to use
predictive prefetching,
we need an app
usage report that we
can feed into a
machine-learning model, which
enhances the app by providing
a predictive experience.
Microsoft's Office 365
uses predictive prefetching
with Angular to improve the
responsiveness of their lazily
loaded components.
YouTube is predictively
prefetching content
for instant user experiences.
But you don't have to
be Microsoft or Google
to take advantage
of this technique.
Guess.js is a library that
adds predictive prefetching
support for apps using
popular frameworks.
And you can take
advantage of it today.
It tracks the possible
navigations from a page
and prefectures only
the JavaScript that
is likely to be needed next.
Now, let me tell you
the story of Naveed,
who introduced predictive
prefetching with Guess.js
to his web app.
Naveed is building a popular
web app with tens of thousands
of users for finding
jobs in Pakistan.
He developed his
web app with Angular
using the Angular
Router and CLI.
Let us compare how three
different prefetching
strategies would perform
on Naveed's website.
If he was prefetching all
the modules in the app,
this will have
consumed 2.56 megabytes
of data for a single user
visiting the home page.
With a more efficient
strategy, if he was only
prefetching the visible
links on the page,
this will have consumed
1.22 megabytes of data.
With Guess.js, Naveed's website
consumes only 0.18 megabytes
of data for prefetching when
the user visits the home page.
This is 7% of the traffic
consumed by the most aggressive
strategy.
With the tens of
thousands of users
visiting Naveed's
websites daily,
he saves gigabytes of traffic.
The prefetching of Guest.js
comes with over 90% accuracy.
Combined with prefetching
on mouse-over,
it can provide
instant experiences
for all the users
of his website,
while saving their data.
Additionally, Guess.js adapts
its prefetching algorithm
to the user's connection speeds.
It performs more
aggressive prefetching
for users on fast network,
and less aggressive
for users on a slower network.
Guess.js prefetches the
individual JavaScript chunks,
depending on their
likelihoods to be used.
It calculates the probabilities
for all the chunks
to be needed at build
time so its payload could
be reduced to the minimum.
And finally, it does not
block the main thread,
since it performs prefetching
only when the browser is idle.
Today you can use Guest.js
with Angular, Next.js, Gatsby,
and Next.js.
The important
takeaways from today
are that predictive prefetching
can speed up page navigation
and improve the user experience.
By doing so, it will
increase user satisfaction
and reduce their data usage.
If you're using Angular
or a popular React or Vue
meta-framework, you can take
advantage of Guess.js today.
You can learn more
about Guess.js
and predictive
prefetching on Web.dev.
Thanks for watching.
[MUSIC PLAYING]