[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: Here's a summary
of how web install is
different from bookmarks.
Web install offers
users access to web
from familiar
discovery and launch
services for their device.
So [INAUDIBLE],, this
could be standalone.
That means it can be
separate from the browser.
It also means that they can be
integrated into the native task
switcher.
This can be a more
familiar way for users
to interact with
apps, or it might
be more suitable to certain
types of tasks than tabs.
Web install integrates
the web apps
with the device services
that expect an installed app.
The important thing to remember
when you're asking a user
to install PWA is that
with an installed app,
you're telling the
user that it is
an experience that is
meant for the device
that the user is using.
And that means that
you need to live up
to those expectations
what you design,
you're going to
have unhappy users.
SPEAKER 2: But of course,
who are these users?
Who is going to benefit
from this extra power?
We're the first ones to admit
that it won't be everybody.
The power of the web has always
been that it is ephemeral.
Users can move seamlessly
between experiences,
and so you shouldn't expect
all of your users to install.
And toward that end, there is
a bit of an install funnel.
This is the same as native
apps or e-commerce conversions.
Most strategies for
optimization apply here as well.
You don't want to push the
user to convert too soon
or they'll leave
your site running.
You should only promote
install to users
who are frequent users,
or who will actually
benefit from your services.
SPEAKER 3: The web is super
powerful in its own right
today.
You can build a hyper
local video chat app
with WebRTC, geolocation
and push messaging.
You can make that app install.
You can add video
effects with Blossom.
And you can even bring
it into new realities
with WebGL and WebVR.
But there's still gaps in
what we can solve with the web
today.
In the worst case, this
means that developers are not
building for the web at all,
or they're relegating it
to a second class experience.
For those that do want
to build for the web
but need the
capabilities of native,
they're forced to bundle
web apps in native wrappers.
This often results in
developers effectively
shipping their own
custom browsers to users,
exploding the size
of their web apps,
and forcing them to take on
the security and maintenance
burden of both
keeping the browser
and their native
wrapper up to date.
Social apps on mobile
devices have been hard,
because they need to be
tightly integrated in order
to be loved by their users.
Quinn thinks for
themself, "our users
want to start a journal entry
from anywhere on their device,
and they want to be able
to share those entries
to other social accounts.
They also want to collaborate
on entries with their friends,
so they need to be able to
invite them to do so easily."
Until recently,
these capabilities
would seem to rule out
building a web app.
They just simply didn't exist.
Both Web Share and the new Web
Share Target V2 and Contacts
APIs, that calculus
has changed, and Quinn
can build a progressive web
app instead of a native app.
Go try it yourself.
On your Android device, go
to fugu-journal.web.app,
add it to your home screen, and
try out everything you've seen,
inviting friends, adding
content, then sharing it out.
While the Contacts API
isn't fully launched yet,
I've enabled an origin
trial on Fugu Journal
so you can see how it works
without a special version
of Chrome, or toggling
any Chrome flags.
And again, you can
try this out yourself.
On your computer, go to
fugu-edit.web.app, install it,
and try to open the files and
folders and save them as you
normally would.
Go to webwewant.fyi
to let us know
what you'd like to see
added to the web platform
to help you bridge
the native app gap.
SPEAKER 4: The first feature
that I want to talk about
is WebAssembly threads.
Threads are key part of
practically all CPUs,
and utilizing them
fully and effectively
has been one of the great
challenges for the web
until now.
SIMD stands for single
instruction multiple data.
And while this may not be a term
that most web developers are
familiar with, it's
an absolutely key part
of modern CPU architectures.
The Google Research team looked
at a bunch of their models
and found that, in general,
SIMD offered a 3x improvement
on overall speed.
And our benchmarking backs up
there's a visually noticeable
difference.
When using both threads
and SIMD together,
common tasks in OpenCV can
be improved by around 15x.
SPEAKER 5: We want
to not only be
able to start an
asynchronous task,
but also wait for
you to finish, read
the results back, and continue
the execution afterwards.
This is where Asyncify comes in.
I won't go too much into
implementation details here,
but what it does is compose
a WebAssembly module
in such a way that you
can suspend the execution,
remember the state,
and later resume
from the exact same point
when an asynchronous task has
finished its execution.
[MUSIC PLAYING]