UNA KRAVETS: Hi,
I'm Una and I'm here
to cover what's new in
material design on the web.
We've got a lot to go
over, so let's get started.
The first update is the Material
Theme Builder tool on Glitch.
The tool itself is a
self-contained application that
showcases each of the
material components with
prompts to update
the base theme shown.
It helps teams to leverage
the three subsystems
of theming within Material--
typography, shape, and color.
The tool uses SAS
variables to show users
how to adjust an
interface style,
and make their own brands shine
by changing just a few lines
of code within a theme file.
For example, color
can be adjusted
via a series of variables,
such as primary, secondary,
background, and surface colors.
These come paired
with on colors,
which represent the
text color on top
of a variable background.
Shape customization can be
made for three component size
classes--
small, medium, and
large components.
Small components include
buttons and input,
medium components include
modals and dialogues,
and large components
include menus and drawers.
There's a great shape
tool on material.io
to help you visualize these
changes on our components
before applying them
to your code base.
And finally, we can
adjust typography
through the generalized
MDC typography variable,
or through SAS maps that
allow you to customize
individual typographic
levels, such as having
a separate weight and font
family for primary headlines
rather than the body copy.
In the end, your theme could
look something like this.
This is just one example that
comes from Google Developer
Days in China.
We've made thousands of
themes around the world
so far, so head over to
Glitch to add your own.
We're also working on
a set of guidelines
for adapting dark themes
using Material components.
For example, in a dark theme,
Google Materials color palette
reduces intensity to
mitigate visual vibration
or strong color contrast
against a darker background.
Instead of solely adding drop
shadows to illustrate elevation
and depth, in a dark theme,
a lighter overlay is applied.
Check out the
material.io guidelines
for more design guidance on
how to transition your designs
into a dark theme, considering
contrast, depth, desaturation,
and limiting colors
for accessibility.
To help with this
transition, MDC Web
has released a set of
typography-themed variables
that respond to background
shades for text styles.
You can now also use
the theme variables
in three different ways.
The most supportive
and robust technique
is with our SAS styling API,
using variables and mix-ins
to override styles.
You can also create CSS
classes with the variable names
to style them by.
And finally, for
modern browsers,
CSS custom properties can be
used for the theme styling.
We're still working on full
support for custom properties
at this time.
We provide so many options
because theming should not
be limiting.
You can extend the theme
builder to make your own theme
as unique as your product.
Leverage our code and build on
top of our Material components
to quickly and easily get
started building product
on the web.
The next new feature in
Material is data tables.
You asked, we listened.
Our designers consider
these three principles
when it comes to data tables.
The first is that data must be
organized in a meaningful way.
Data tables should also be
allowed for user interaction.
And finally, those interactions
should be as logical
as the structure of
the data table itself.
Data tables come with some
basic default functionality,
such as row selection.
But you can also hook them
up to other components,
such as these filter chips.
Check out the links provided
below for a deep dive
into how you can
actually implement
data tables in your web projects
and combine Material components
for orchestrated actions.
We also have a new density
subsystem option in Material.
Material design uses
low-density space by default,
with large tap
targets and margins,
but offers high-density space
when it improves the user
experience.
We brought density
into our system
for the following reasons.
The first is for scanability.
Scanability is improved
for data-heavy applications
with a higher density interface.
The second is that
dense UIs may actually
help users focus by reducing
space between actions.
And finally, more content
is available to the user
on a single screen in more
high-density applications.
Whether or not to
increase your UI's density
can be determined by how users
interact with the component.
Components with
high density enable
users to process and take
action against large amounts
of information in a
more manageable way.
Lists, tables, and long
forums are components that
benefit from increased density.
But density shouldn't be
used for every component.
For example, don't apply
density to components
that involve focused tasks
or alert the user of changes,
such as snack bars or dialogues.
Applying high density to
alerts reduces their ability
to command attention.
A series of new styling
classes on the web
allows for us to access
density in three ways--
the default component
size, a comfortable size,
which provides a higher density
display while respecting
minimum touch target
size, and compact,
which may be used for pages
with a lot of information
but may be inappropriate
for user actions.
Materials.io got
an update as well.
We now provide a
cross platform view
of all of our
component offerings
on a dedicated components page.
This page allows
for quick access
to components and overview of
cross-platform availability.
It should make it easier
to navigate our product
and implement it for your needs.
Check out material.io/components
to browse them all yourself.
And finally, we're kicking
off a new initiative this year
to focus on supporting
Material across web frameworks.
Why?
We know that most of you
are developing web apps
using a framework.
And the open source community
has stepped up immensely,
building components for some of
the most adopted web frameworks
out there.
We want to celebrate this work
and help bring the Material
design vision to life, along
with our open source community.
So many of you have already
built your own wrapper
libraries using MDC Web's
components, foundations,
and adapters.
And we're working more
closely with the rest
of the open source
community as well.
We've updated
material.io to link
to three of the most popular
open source component
libraries.
They've already uncovered
bugs in the Material design
guidelines, and asked
great questions,
helping us to make
Material even better.
And we're helping them to
follow the spec and the Material
guidelines more closely as well.
We look forward to
continuing the conversation
and working to bring
the Material design
vision to every platform and
framework, making it easier
for everyone to use
Material design on the web.
There's so much to
explore and play with,
from theming to
density to data tables
to new website features, and
our open source community.
It's an exciting time to
be building with Material.
So check out material.io
and the links
below where you can find all
the resources that I mentioned
today.
Can't wait to see what
you build with Material.
I'll see you on the web.
[MUSIC PLAYING]