MINKO GECHEV: Hello, everyone.
My name is Minko Gechev.
I'm a senior developer
programs engineer
in the Angular team at Google.
Today, I'm going to show
you a couple of tools
that we have been working on
to help you build fast Angular
applications.
In the presentation
today, we're going
to look into an existing
app and optimize it
by going through three steps.
First, we will introduce
code splitting.
After that, bundle preloading.
And finally, we will deploy
the app to production
with a single command, following
best-serving practices.
First things first, let us
look at our existing app.
As any Angular
application, we can run it
by using the ng serv command.
Now we can open the
app in Chrome DevTools
into the browser.
Let us navigate to all
the pages in the app,
while DevTools tracks
the network activity.
As the next step, we
can open the Network tab
of Chrome DevTools.
Notice that the
only network request
there is triggered by the
image from the first page we
navigate us to.
This means that during
the initial load time,
we are downloading the
JavaScript associated
with all pages, although the
user needs only a subset of it.
This is a good opportunity
to introduce code splitting.
In Angular CLI 8.1, we added
a lazy module generator.
It accepts a module name, a
route name, and a parent module
name.
Let us use it to move the About
page into its own JavaScript
chunk.
All we need to do is run ng
g for generate, m for module,
with the name about, route name
about, and parent module app.
This command generated a
definition of an NgModule,
declaration of a lazy
route, declaration
of a default route in the
lazy module, and a component
that the default
route will render.
Now there is goal to VS code
to remove the eager route
and switch to the newly
generated lazy one.
First, let us remove
the eager route itself.
Next, we can delete
the eager component
import and declaration.
As a next step, let
us move the definition
of the eagerly
rendered component
to the lazily rendered one.
Finally, let us remove
the files we're not
going to use for this
particular example,
as well as the eagerly
rendered about component.
Now, we can preview the
result in the browser.
Notice that the navigation
to the about page
triggered a network
request which
downloaded the about module.
We improved the initial
app load [INAUDIBLE]
by the length scripts which
are not immediately needed
by the user.
This, however, may
introduce latency
when navigating across pages.
A technique that can help us to
fix this is bundle preloading.
As a next step, we can install
the ngx quicklink module
and save it into
our dependencies.
Ngx quicklink is a
preloading strategy
that will detect
when a router link is
visible in the viewport.
It will wait until
the browser is idle
and prefetch it, unless
the user's browser is
in data-saving mode.
To introduce
quicklink to our app,
we first need to import
the quicklink module
and add it to the list of
imports in the app ng module.
After that, we need to
import the quicklink strategy
and add it as the preloading
strategy of the Angular router.
To observe the result,
let's go back to Chrome.
Notice that when
we open the site
navigation, in the
background Angular
downloads the about module.
Finally, let us deploy the
app to production following
best-serving practices.
In the console, we can
type ng add angular/fire.
This command will
install Firebase tools
and perform a couple
of transformations
on top of our project.
If we are authenticated
as to Firebase,
it will also fetch
our project list
and allow us to select
one by using fuzzy search.
With the latest deployment
capabilities in the Angular CLI
8.3, we can add a package
from a cloud provider
and run the command ng deploy to
push our project to the cloud.
Now let us run ng
deploy in the terminal.
It will first build our
app, performing the most
optimal build possible.
After that, upload
the production asset
to Firebase Hosting.
Finally, it will
output a URL that we
can use to directly
preview the deployment.
The cloud platforms with
direct support for Angular CLI
are Google Cloud and
Firebase, Azure, and Zeit.
Community partners also
implemented support
for GitHub Pages, Netify, and
directly publishing libraries
to NPM.
In this video, we looked into
three simple optimization
techniques.
First, we introduced
code-splitting to our app
by using the Angular
CLI schematics.
After that, with
ngx quicklink, we
added efficient
prefetching of chunks,
associated with visible
links in the viewport.
Finally, we deployed the
app to Firebase Hosting,
enabling best-serving
practices such as CDM
and Content Compression.
You can learn more about
all of these techniques
at web.dev/angular.
Thank you for watching.
[MUSIC PLAYING]