ADRIANA JARA: My
name is Adriana Jara.
I'm a Developer
Advocate in Chrome OS.
I will share five tips to
make your PWA stand out
in a good way.
Earlier this year, I was a
developer on a progressive web
app here at Google.
And in the beginning,
our users had
a lot of questions about PWA.
How do you install a website?
What happens if you don't
install it right away?
What happens when
you're offline?
How does it manage
local resources?
These are the lessons I learned
from answering their questions.
Hopefully, they'll help
you build an experience
your users will love.
Here we go.
Number one, dare to be offline.
When a user is
offline, they don't
expect to be able
to get to a website,
let alone enjoy any
of its features.
As a developer, you might even
be convinced that your app just
doesn't make sense offline.
And because a PWA requires
an offline experience,
you can create a
custom page that
asks users to come back later
when there is a connection.
Instead, how about creating
different features?
You can't give users
full functionality,
but some parts could still work.
With the use of device
storage and caching,
for example, users can't
get to the latest posts,
but they could interact with
previously retrieved posts.
They could comment
and add reactions.
You can save those interactions
locally and see them later
when they are back online.
Random searches are impossible.
But if you have
cached recent results,
they answer they are
looking for may be there.
The result?
Happy user.
And you didn't even
need the internet!
By the way, since
you don't know when
a user is going to
be offline or when
the phone is going
to be turned off,
it's a good practice to
save snapshots in workflows
so that the users don't
lose a lot of work
in case of an interruption.
Number two, use
device storage wisely.
On the web, our apps seem
to have unlimited storage.
But in a device, it's
a different story.
There are hard limits.
Keep tabs on how much
space is available.
You don't want your
app to just stop
working in the middle
of recording a video.
You can use Storage Manager
to calculate available space,
and then show the user warnings
so they can take action.
Also, choose wisely which method
is more appropriate to save
the local data.
Some options are cached API--
which, by the way, can
be accessed directly
from the window object.
It doesn't need to go
through a service worker.
IndexedDB.
A good use case
here are operations
that need a transaction or
the native file system API.
It is not fully available yet,
but you can start to experiment
with it.
Check out the link in the
description for more info.
Also, don't keep local
data longer than necessary.
Once you can sync the
data to the cloud,
free up space in the device.
And clear all local data when
appropriate-- for example,
when the user signs out.
Number three, embrace
multi-device journeys.
Users have multiple devices.
They jump from one another
and pick up where they left.
At least, that is
their expectation.
As users, we want to start
a task on our computer
and send it to our phone to
be continued, and vice versa.
It is pretty convenient to
take a picture with our phone.
But also, a big
screen and a keyboard
are nice to edit photos
and type captions.
Another example is
content consumption.
We consume content on our
phone in a different way
than we do on a larger screen.
Users want to be able
to take advantage
of the real estate
that is available
and consume content in the most
efficient and enjoyable way
for them.
Building different
layouts also helps
with making your app more
accessible and inclusive.
Your users know that no matter
what device they're using,
your app will provide the
appropriate experience
for their journey across
different form factors.
Number four, bring
your users with you.
Progressive web apps
are still new for users.
They might not realize
they have landed
on a website with
special capabilities.
Help them along the way.
Prompt your users to install
your app when it is convenient.
For a while, we used the
browser's default prompt.
Unfortunately, it would
interrupt our users
in the middle of our
getting started flow.
The prompt would go
away, and users would
forget to install our app.
Now, you can capture the
before install prompt event
and prompt the users
at a later time.
You can use headers,
banners, menus, and others.
I added a link to an article in
the description that walks you
through different patterns.
You can also help your users
by adding tips in your UI
the first time they
go through a workflow.
You can highlight things like
what data will be available
offline or what
parts of your app
will work in the background.
Finally, don't ask
for permissions
until the user is trying
a specific feature.
Don't ask for camera
access until the user
is going to take a picture.
This makes the user understand
why you need permissions,
and they will be more
willing to grant them.
Number five, beware
of service workers.
Service workers are
powerful and are
central in implementing
several of my tips.
For example, you can
use background sync
to upload large amounts of data.
Even when the app
is closed, they also
make possible to make
good use of notifications
and re-engage your users.
Maybe to remind your
users of unfinished task
or of new content.
However, service
workers can be tricky.
The best approach
is to generate it.
There are tools
like Workbox that
can help you generate a service
worker with the strategies
your app needs.
Finally, keeping your service
worker code to a minimum
will also make your
app easier to test.
This way, you'll
implement behaviors
in helper classes that
can be better unit tested.
Thank you for watching.
I hope you got some new ideas
to make your PWA give users
the best of the web
and native experiences.
I included links
in the description
to help you
implement these tips.
Don't forget to subscribe
and share with your friends.
[MUSIC PLAYING]