SAM THOROGOOD: Hi, I'm Sam from
the Developer Relations Team
here at Google.
And I'm here to tell you that
it's OK to abandon all hope,
to give up, and to go
back on your plans.
Let me set the scene for you.
As you plan your next release
and you look at your code,
it's very easy to
fall into the trap
of improving your code base
rather than moving forward.
You might consider
having faster build
times, more readable code, or
to upgrade to the latest web
framework that
everyone's talking about.
This happened to me back in
November, 2018 in the lead
up to releasing "Santa Tracker,"
which is a holiday themed
experience for all ages.
We were in the
middle of a rewrite,
mainly because our build
times were enormous,
and we wanted to use
Google's new web components
library, LitElement.
But we made a hard decision
to give up on our tech debt
and to ship our old code
base because Santa only
comes once a year.
And by being busy
refactoring a code base,
we just weren't checking off
our task list fast enough.
So let's talk a bit about
what we were dealing with.
"Santa Tracker," at
its core, is a shell,
which hosts lots of
small games or scenes,
like this are fun snowball
throwing game here.
And on December 24, we
unlock the tracker itself,
where you can see
Santa traveling
around the world on his
journey delivering presents
and finding out when
he'll arrive in your town.
Some of these games have
code that is years old.
And, as much as
possible, we want
to avoid throwing these
games out in a rewrite.
So, in 2018, we
decide to migrate
about 50 different games to
work on this new platform.
And, fundamentally,
the rate we were
getting through
our migration tasks
just didn't equal our
December 1 release date.
And this is why we gave up.
So we've now successfully
migrated for 2019 and beyond.
But what did we
learn in the process?
The first learning
is the old idiom of,
don't let perfect
be the enemy of good
as it applies to
developer experience
versus user experience.
I imagined that "Santa
Tracker" would somehow
be infinitely
better for our users
if we had a faster build
time and a more modern stack.
But the reality is that
an upgrade would mostly
help my team and have very
little benefit to our end
users.
Keep in mind, of
course, that sometimes
your technical choices are
changed from underneath you.
And, in our case, we were
using Hastymail inports,
which shipped in Chrome
but never really got
wider adoption.
The truth is though there's
often really fewer reasons
than we think as developers
to change the stack.
Secondly, we learned the
value of allocating time
to prototyping
before you decided
on a new technical stack.
This can save you a lot of
grief and technical debt.
Technical debt is when
you're on a tight deadline
and, instead of properly
solving some problem,
you're patching over it and
leaving it for your future self
to solve.
And, of course, all
software has technical debt.
But it's even worse when
you're blazing new paths,
like we were, into a
totally unknown framework
for a library.
And, for us, we didn't really
allocate time for prototyping.
We were on a tight schedule.
You know, we'd bought
into this vision
of a new, amazing
developer experience.
But, in practice, "Santa
Tracker," like every site,
has edge cases that we
didn't really plan for
and didn't fit into the
mold of this new stack which
we'd chosen, which caused us
to incur this technical debt.
Software always has
innate knowledge.
Our old "Santa
Tracker" code base
had years upon years of
hacks and work arounds.
And, in any rewrite,
it's enticing
to skip these weird code paths.
But, in the end, they
were there for a reason.
By building a working
prototype in a new stack,
you can test these
edge cases to see
if they still matter to you.
Because we skipped this step,
we hit all sorts of challenges
way late into our
development cycle
when it was just too late.
We had to give up
on the refactor.
In hindsight, we
should have built up
all these tricky nuances of
our site in a full prototype
before attempting to replace
the entire tech stack.
What we ended up doing
with what we're using what
we built in 2018 as the
prototype for what you now
seen in 2019 and beyond.
Don't get me wrong.
In 2019, we still
shipped some of the best
parts of the product type.
And that leads me to
the final learning.
Ship early and ship often.
You always want to validate
your technical choices
with real users.
So we'd written a whole new
game, "Elf Maker," entirely
on the new stack.
It wasn't part of the
old codebase whatsoever.
So we felt comfortable
testing it with real users.
And, in fact, if you closely at
how that scene loaded in 2018,
you could see how we introduced
a bit of magic deferring
to an iframe, with a small
shim between the codebases.
We had to come talk to Frank in
build system to make this work.
But, as part of that,
we forced ourselves
to have an end-to-end build
process of the new prototype,
even though we weren't
shipping it wholesale.
And this meant that our rewrite
wasn't just wholly turned
into just a prototype.
And we got a small slice of the
new code in front of real users
to show that it could work.
[BELLS JINGLING]
We're hoping to open source
the new version of "Santa
Tracker" in early 2020.
It's not perfect.
But it is a real
website with a bunch
of build tooling, legacy
card, and necessary technology
choices.
I hope you'll check
it out and get
some insights into how to best
structure your next project.
Remember, don't let perfect
be the enemy of good.
Your users don't care
how the sausage is made.
Ruminate on your
technology choices
by building a prototype.
And, if possible, try to get
the safest parts of your code
in front of real users,
even if your whole refactor
isn't done yet.
Thanks for watching, and
I'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]