PAUL: Goodbye!
JAKE: Bye!
MARIKO: Goodbye!
[APPLAUSE]
[APPLAUSE STOPS]
PAUL: Right, you're up.
Come on.
CDS bingo time.
MARIKO: [SIGHS] OK, OK.
PAUL: That is for you--
JAKE: Oh.
PAUL: --and for you.
MARIKO: Pens, pens.
PAUL: Remote on.
[MUSIC PLAYING ON TV]
MARIKO: That music again.
JAKE: [CHORTLES]
PAUL: Hey, I'll skip
it for you, hang on.
Ehh, there we go.
Good.
You ready?
MARIKO: Yep.
JAKE: Yep.
MARIKO: Let's go.
[PEN HITS PAD OF PAPER]
SPEAKER 1: About
1,000 of us are here
in San Francisco today,
and tens of thousands more
are watching on the Livestream--
JAKE: Got that one.
[TV STATIC]
SPEAKER 2: In Chrome--
SURMA: Should we
watch mine next?
MARIKO: Um, mmmm.
SPEAKER 2: We really,
really believe that every--
JAKE: (HESITANTLY) Later.
Later.
[TV STATIC]
SPEAKER 3: Pixel 4 has a
new, shiny facial recognition
capability.
Starting from Chrome 79--
PAUL: Oh, yep, that's me.
Yep.
SPEAKER 3:
--GooglePlay services.
[TV STATIC]
SURMA: What-- what
is bingo in Japanese?
MARIKO: Bingo.
SURMA: Huh.
JAKE: Huh.
PAUL: Huh.
What is it in German?
SURMA: Bingo.
JAKE: Oh.
MARIKO: Oh.
PAUL: Oh.
[TV STATIC]
SURMA: I think it's
time for my talk.
PAUL: Actually, we could
just watch something else.
[TV STATIC]
SPEAKER 4: Today, 90 of the top
100 sites now default to HTTPS,
and that's--
MARIKO: Yes.
Yes.
Got it.
[TV STATIC]
SPEAKER 4: --one of our own
sites to try to optimize--
SURMA: Dude.
Dude, dude.
Right now, there.
SPEAKER 4: --for this demo.
All right, Paul,
you're good to go.
JAKE: Ooh, live demo.
Live demo.
PAUL: Ooh.
MARIKO: Ooh.
PAUL: Let's do this.
SPEAKER 4: OK, awesome.
JAKE: Is it gonna work?
SPEAKER 4: So the first
thing Paul is going to do
is jump into the Audits--
JAKE: It works!
MARIKO: Yes!
JAKE: [SIGH OF RELIEF]
[TV STATIC]
NATHAN SCHLOSS: So one thing
Facebook recently announced
is a redesign of the website.
SURMA: Wait, I thought
this was Chrome Dev Summit?
JAKE: They actually
contribute to Chrome.
MARIKO: Hmm.
[TV STATIC]
SPEAKER 5: 780 digits, that's
more than a Google of digits.
That's a lot of digits.
MARIKO: Ooh!
Ooh, ooh!
Big number!
SURMA: Ooh!
MARIKO: Big number!
PAUL: Yay.
JAKE: Yes.
[TV STATIC]
SURMA: All right, time
to watch my talk now.
MARIKO: Um, sorry,
I got a thing to--
JAKE: Yeah.
MARIKO: --to do.
JAKE: I got a thing to do.
PAUL: Yeah, no.
JAKE: Enjoy, though.
Enjoy.
MARIKO: Yeah, bye!
SURMA: All right, suit yourself.
[TV STATIC]
(ON VIDEO) It's a
minesweeper clone as a PWA.
So it has all the PWA goodies
like offline and nice graphics.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
And it was projected at
around 400 million feature
codes were--
[SHARP INHALE] Yes!
(ON VIDEO) --in 2019 alone.
So we explore-- [APPLAUSE]
Full house.
(ON VIDEO) --especially
if we wanted
to include that audience
in our target audience
so that they can play on
these devices as well.