[MUSIC PLAYING]
EMILY STARK: Today, my
colleague Michael Kleber and I
are going to be telling you
about what Chrome is doing
to help people make safe
decisions about what data they
share with websites.
If you're a web user in
2019, and I think most of you
probably are, you've probably
had some pretty mystifying
experiences.
You've probably
had an experience
where you're reading a news
article on your work desktop
computer, when you stumble
upon an ad for the exact pair
of shoes that you searched for
on your personal phone a week
ago.
No matter how many times you've
seen ad experiences like this,
it still probably
throws you for a loop.
How did this one
website on one device
know your search history
on another device
at a completely different time?
And what else might
it know about you?
Or maybe you got an email,
another mystifying experience,
from your bank,
telling you to log
in to verify a fraudulent charge
or to unfreeze your account.
And the email looks legit,
the link looks legit,
but how do you know?
How are you really
supposed to tell?
And maybe even more importantly,
how is a non-technical user
supposed to tell?
The fact is, it's not
always easy to tell
where you are on the
web or what websites
are observing about you.
Chrome's goal is to help people
with both of these problems.
We want to help users
make safe decisions
while staying in control
of their personal data.
And we want to do this while
preserving a thriving web
ecosystem where content
creators can make money
through ads without
invading users' privacy.
We'll start by talking
about what Chrome
is doing to help people
understand where they are
on the web, what's the
identity of the website
that they're visiting,
and particularly,
is the site being misleading
about its identity?
As developers, this
may be a problem
that your users struggle
with, or maybe even
something that you sometimes
struggle with, yourself.
Because even as
expert users, even
for myself, as a person who
works on a browser security
team, it's not
always obvious when
a site is being misleading
about its identity.
In theory, the URL
bar that's shown
at the top of a web browser
is your unambiguous clue
to website identity.
If the URL bar says Google.com,
you're at the real Google.
And if it says
Evil.com, you're not,
no matter how much the web
content area looks like Google.
But in practice,
it's not always so
easy to tell site
identity from a domain,
as you can see here
with these examples.
Some of these URLs might be
hard for even expert users
to notice and distinguish
from Google.com,
much less non-technical users.
And this isn't speculation.
There's lots of research,
lab studies, surveys, field
experiments showing that
many users don't notice
or understand URLs when they
need to in order to make
effective security decisions.
In a study that we did with
over 1,000 participants,
we showed users a browser
window where the website looked
like a Google login
page, but the address bar
said tinyurl.com.
When asked to identify
this website, over 85%
of participants said
the website was Google,
even though the address bar
clearly said tinyurl.com.
This presents a
really hard problem.
Lots of people use URLs for
lots of really useful things,
but there are also lots
of ways that URLs can be
used to trick or harm people.
So what can we do about it?
We're approaching this
problem from a few angles.
First, we're actively combating
sophisticated spoofing
techniques that
abuse URLs to create
unusually deceptive attacks.
Second, we're
drawing-- we're trying
to draw people's attention to
the information in URLs that's
most relevant for making
security decisions.
And finally, we're
building specialized tools
to support expert use cases
so that we can help make URLs
better security tools
without interfering
with expert workflows.
We've found that sites
can be particularly
misleading about
their identity when
they abuse Internationalized
Domain Names, or IDNs.
These spoofing sites
use non-Ascii characters
in the domain to look remarkably
similar to a legitimate domain.
Suppose you were looking at
Example.com, as written here.
You could do a very careful,
character-by-character
comparison, and
you would probably
conclude very confidently that
you're at the real Example.com.
There is no way this is a spoof.
But it turns out, there's
a Cyrillic character that
looks identical to
a Latin letter A,
so this isn't the
real Example.com.
It's a completely
different domain,
even though it looks the same.
The question that
browsers are faced with
is when is it safe to
display non-Ascii characters
in a domain, and when
does it create a spoofing
opportunity like this?
You can see that with a
naive IDN display policy,
or even with a
sophisticated one,
there are many
interesting avenues
for spoofing that can open up.
To combat this kind of
spoofing, in Chrome 75
we introduced a
new warning which
we call the Lookalike Warning.
This morning detects
spoofy IDNs and shows
this page to direct the
user to the legitimate site
when we think they
might be under attack.
Here's how this
works under the hood.
When Chrome encounters an IDN,
Internationalized Domain Name,
in a navigation, it
converts it to a skeleton
using an algorithm that converts
a representation of the domain,
collapsing similar looking
characters into one.
We then compare that skeleton
against the skeletons of very
popular sites and also sites
that the user has visited
and engaged with in the past.
If there's a match among
one of those sites,
we show this morning to direct
the user to the legitimate site
that we think is the site
they actually want to go to.
But of course, it's not
only IDNs that are confusing
and that present
spoofing opportunities.
Paths, fragments, and
other components of the URL
can distract from the
domain name, which
is the crucial
indicator of identity
that users need to scrutinize
to make security decisions.
You may have noticed
some changes recently
to how Chrome's Omnibox
looks to help draw users'
attention to the domain name.
First, we did some user research
on the extended validation
indicator in Chrome.
Extended validation is a special
type of HTTPS certificate
which you can buy to tie your
domain name to a legal entity.
And when you do this,
your legal entity name
shows up in browser address
bars, as you can see here.
The idea is that this
type of certificate
relieves people,
relieves end users,
from having to understand
site identity from URLs,
because they should
be able to discern it
from the EV indicator instead.
From our user
research, though, we
found that EV
certificates don't really
help people understand
site identity today.
For EV to be
effective, people need
to notice when it's
missing, because that
indicates a possible attack.
But we found that they didn't.
There have also been
some recent proof
of concept attacks
showing that EV can even
be abused to show actively
misleading site identity
information in the address bar.
So in Chrome 77, we
moved the EV indicator
into page info, which
is this UI surface
that you see when you click
on the lock icon in Chrome.
If you have an EV
certificate for your website
and you're wondering where
the EV indicator went,
this is where.
This is in line with our
general philosophy on Chrome
that users should be able to
assume security by default
and will warn when
something is wrong,
rather than, we don't want to be
presenting positive indicators
and relying on users
noticing their absence,
because we've found that
just doesn't work as well.
We also recently
launched a change
to simplify how URLs themselves
are displayed in the Omnibox.
This scheme, HTTPS or HTTP, and
the very common subdomain www,
don't add much information
for many users.
The scheme is most
useful for telling
whether the connection
is secure or not,
but we already represent
that visually with a lock
icon or a not secure a badge.
Besides, we want it to
be so that you don't have
to specifically check when a
connection is HTTPS by looking
for this scheme, because Chrome
will warn you when it isn't.
And for the vast
majority of sites,
the presence or absence
of the www subdomain
doesn't make a difference.
It's just visual noise
for a lot of users
who have a hard time
finding the security
relevant part of the URL.
We now hide these URL
components in what
we call the steady state of
the box to make the UI simpler
and to focus the user's
attention on the security
relevant part of the URL,
which is the domain name.
You could imagine in the
future other possible UI
changes that might
draw attention
to the domain name even more.
Should we hide the
path of a URL until you
click to edit in the box?
Should we make the
domain name stand out
more by making it
bolder or bigger?
Should we animate in
the path, after the user
has had a chance to inspect
the domain on its own?
There are lots of
different possibilities,
but so far we don't have
strong evidence about which one
is the best direction,
if any, so this is still
an open problem.
In line with this
philosophy, we plan
to eventually remove
even the lock icon
that browsers typically
show on HTTPS connections.
We plan to present secure
HTTPS connections as neutral,
as the default,
and warn only when
the connection lacks security.
As you can see here, positive
indicators like the lock icon
can be confusing to users
and send the wrong message.
We want to make it so
that if you see nothing,
you can assume it's
security HTTPS,
because Chrome will
warn you if it's not.
However, we don't
have a firm timeline
for this change for
removing the lock icon,
because we need some more time
for research and preparation
still.
Now, not everybody wants
their URL display simplified.
In fact, many of
you in the audience
might be power users who
understand URLs perfectly well
and are pretty good at
telling when a site is being
misleading about its identity.
We want to build tools just
for power users like you who
understand the underlying
identity system of the web
well.
Our first foray into this
space is a Chrome extension
called Suspicious
Site Reporter, and it
does a couple of things that
might be of interest to people
like you, who want to see the
full details about the web
pages they're visiting.
So first of all, when you
install this extension,
you'll always see the full,
unedited URL in the Omnibox.
It let you bypass
any simplifications
that we make to the
box in default Chrome
with the aim of helping
less technical users.
Secondly, we think that
experts play an important role
in protecting the
masses on the web.
The extension gives
you an easy way
to report malicious sites
to Google's Safe Browsing
service, which scans the
web for malicious activity.
For example, if we go back to
that suspicious bank website
that I mentioned at the
beginning of the talk,
suppose that you,
as an expert user,
received this link from an
email and noticed that it
looks like a phishing site.
Maybe it doesn't look like
your bank's normal domain,
or that your real
bank wouldn't ask
you to do something like provide
your password over the phone.
So in these circumstances, if
you open up the Suspicious Site
Reporter extension, you'll
see some more information
about that site,
highlighting maybe
that it's not a top site
that users visit often.
Maybe it's a site you've
never visited before yourself,
and maybe pointing out some
behaviors that suspicious sites
typically exhibit.
From there, if you decide the
site is, indeed, suspicious,
it's one click to report
that the URL to Safe Browsing
for scanning.
And if Safe Browsing finds that
the site is indeed malicious,
seeing evidence that it
violates our policies
on phishing or
malware distribution
or social engineering,
it will block the site
for all users of Chrome.
So as technical experts,
you have an ability
to stop malicious sites that
non-technical people might not
have, and you can
use that ability
to protect all users of the web.
You can install the
extension from this URL,
or if you want to get
even further involved,
the code is on GitHub, and
we'd welcome your issues
that you want to file
or any code that you
want to contribute.
Building usable security tools
is a really hard problem,
but Chrome is
committing to helping--
is committed to helping
people understand
where they are on the web.
We're doing this by
combating spoofing,
drawing people's attention to
what they need to understand
to make security
decisions, and harnessing
the power of experts like you.
But web users today aren't just
concerned about first party
website identity.
They're also concerned
with third parties
and how their data flows
among those third parties.
I'll now handed
over to my colleague
Michael to talk about limiting
what data is being observed
about you on the web while
enabling a thriving web
ecosystem.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
MICHAEL KLEBER: Thanks.
Hi.
I'm Michael Kleber, and
I'm a software engineer
working on privacy and
tracking prevention in Chrome.
So let's talk about
third parties on the web.
As Emily says, when you're
visiting a site on the web,
the browser can do a lot to help
you know what site you're on.
But most sites
aren't constructed
in-house from the ground up.
Just like most homeowners
get a professional
to do their electrical
work, lots of websites
have third party experts
to do their analytics
or their video serving or other
specialized functions for them.
Third parties are great, and
the fact that this is possible
is pretty amazing.
Composability is one of
the web's superpowers.
One huge role third
parties play today is ads.
Sure, Google and Facebook
put ads on their own sites,
but that's not what
I'm talking about.
Most ads on the web
come from third parties.
When you visit a news
site, it probably has
ads that were placed there--
could be by Google or Facebook,
or could be by 100
other companies
in the ad-placing business.
And that's great, too.
Sites across the web, full of
important and useful content
that people get to see for
free, support themselves
with tens of billions
of dollars a year
from ads placed
by third parties.
But there's a problem
with the system today,
and I'm sure you
know what it is.
Privacy.
If you're browsing
the web, then even
if you know where you are,
what site you're visiting,
you probably don't know
all the third parties
that are involved.
And it's unreasonable
to expect you to.
What's more, if you're
a developer building
your own site, you might not
know all the third parties
who could be pulled
in when it runs.
This is like knowing
your whole supply chain.
Transitive
dependencies are hard.
And even if you
know who they are,
you still might not know
everything that they're doing.
And the answer is
it shouldn't matter.
People should be able to
browse the web without worrying
that someone is collecting
a dossier on them
for what they're
doing, and developers
should be able to build
sites without worrying
that their infrastructure
is compromising their users'
interests.
So how can we get there?
How can we let third parties
do the hugely important things
that they do today,
including letting
ads pay for content, without
allowing specific people to be
tracked across the web?
We have a 2-step plan to
get to a flourishing web
without tracking.
First, we want to give
third parties new tools
to accomplish their goals.
That's probably not what you
expected me to say, right?
But bear with me a minute.
Third parties may want
to answer some very
natural and
nonpersonal questions,
things like how many
different people saw my ad?
Or how often do the people
who click on these ads
actually buy something?
Or is there someone who
can vouch for you being
a trustworthy human web user?
Answering all these
questions today
relies on a really powerful
capability, global cross site
identity.
And this is what
can also be used
to knit your browsing behavior
together into a user profile.
We would be much
better off if it
were possible to answer
these questions with more
right-sized APIs.
We need a web that
is powerful enough
to support those vital third
party use cases without relying
on a too-large tracking
mechanism that gives you
a way more information
than what you really need.
It turns out that support
for some of these use cases
isn't easy.
We don't want the browser to
share your activity with anyone
else, not even with a trusted
counting service or a spam
detection provider,
and that means
we need to do things the hard
way with powerful machinery
doing privacy preserving
operations behind the scenes.
Privacy preserving measurement
and fraud prevention,
well, we've published
proposals backed
by cutting edge crypto and
secure multi-party computation
research.
Check out the private join and
compute blog posts and video
for some related prior work.
Even harder are the
ways that the browser
can support those ad
companies who want to show you
ads that you're most
likely to be interested in.
We have ideas here,
too, built on top
of on-device and
federated computation
and guarded by differential
privacy protections.
Check out Google's
Federated Learning website
for some more details.
I know it's odd to think about
something specifically meant
to help ads being built
into web browsers,
but the browser
is the place where
we can offer privacy guarantees,
and these capabilities turn out
to be really important
for the web to flourish.
How important?
Well, our friends in Google Ads
ran some experiments on life
without personalization or
these sorts of new capabilities,
and the results are
pretty devastating.
Websites got 52% less
ads revenue on average,
and news publishers
got 62% less.
I'm sure you all can imagine
what losing half of their money
would do to the
websites you love.
And that's why Chrome
believes that this work is
worthwhile and necessary
to the health of the web.
And look, I know some of you
are looking at this slide,
and saying, oh, this
is just about Chrome
helping Google protect
its bottom line.
So let me be clear here.
Google makes most of its
money from search ads,
and people only
come to Google.com
to search for stuff because all
the richness of the web exists.
Helping the open web thrive
is the mission for Chrome
and is vital to
Google, and I think
it's why we're all here today.
So part one of my
plan was new APIs,
and these APIs are built to
support their use cases even
in a world where there's no
way to link up your activity
across different sites.
So once we've invented new
ways for the web to flourish,
ways that don't
rely on tracking,
what does that unlock?
How do we move to a world
where people who use the web
are going to be safe and feel
confident in their browsing?
Recognizing users across
sites has historically
been based on third
party cookies,
but as browsers have restricted
access to those cookies,
we've seen them replaced
with other mechanisms,
covert browser storage, device
fingerprinting, asking for user
provided information
like email addresses.
Those covert tracking
techniques are a real problem.
They lack transparency
into who's using them
and for what purpose, and often,
there is no way to reset them.
We've started landing
changes in Chrome
to block some of these
ways of tracking.
To be honest, there
are a lot of ways
that you might try
to track users,
and so fixing them is going
to be a long road, not
a quick fix.
And we'll be carefully
watching the impact on good use
cases along the way.
Something like shared caches
can be a tracking vector,
for example, but they also
help pages load faster.
Speaking of good
use cases, remember
what I said about
us being much better
off if it were possible
to answer questions
with more right-sized APIs?
This applies to the covert
tracking problem, also.
Check out this code.
What's going on here?
Looks like someone is writing
a string of characters
to a Canvas element and then
reading the pixels back, maybe
to fingerprint you based on your
graphics stack, for example?
No, it turns out
this is WordPress.
The rights to
Canvas are read back
to check whether this string
of emoji here with 0 width
joins in between them, renders
as three separate characters,
like this, or as this one
character added in Emoji 12.
If the web platform
forces you to use
high entropy
fingerprinting surfaces
to perform mundane tasks like
checking for Emoji support,
that's a problem
that we need to fix.
And then we want Chrome
to notice it and stop it
when a website is
abusing a bunch
of unrelated, high entropy
content APIs as a way
to fingerprint you.
Our privacy budget
explainer describes
the multi-step process
that we're working on.
As for third party
cookies themselves,
let me start with
some upcoming changes
that we announced
earlier this year.
Starting in Chrome M80,
that's three months from now,
if you set a cookie
the way you've
probably been doing it
since the dawn of the web,
that cookie will be available
only in a first party context.
If you want that cookie
when you're a third party,
you need to do something new.
For details, see the Chromium
blog posts linked here,
or see the console warnings that
are live in Chrome right now.
But the quick summary is this.
If you want a cookie available
when you're a third party,
you will need to explicitly
set it with the attributes
SameSite=None and secure.
And yes, that secure thing
does mean that HTTPS is a must.
There will be no
third party cookies
on insecure HTTP requests.
This is part of an IETF draft.
We expect both
Firefox and Microsoft
Edge to shift this change in
sometime next year as well.
This is the new world.
OK, so what about third party
cookies over HTTPS, then?
I'm sure some of you are
hoping that I will tell you
the future, that
I am going to gaze
into my cookie
dough-flavored crystal ball
and tell you whether cookies
are going to stick around
in their current form or
go away entirely or live on
with some restrictions
that prevent
their use in
cross-site tracking.
And I wish I had
an answer for you.
People's expectations
are changing,
and all of us in the
browser community
are watching those
changes happen.
And it's difficult to predict,
especially about the future.
Google is a company, and
Chrome, as a browser,
cannot unilaterally chart
the future of the cookie.
We can make the current
web architecture better
by introducing more privacy-safe
ways to do important things,
and we can build for
every eventuality.
So what I can say
is that Chrome wants
to build a web that
thrives, even if third party
cookies go away entirely.
And this is where
we need your help.
Help us imagine a world
without third party cookies
or other tracking vectors.
What other use cases are crying
out for a specialized browser
support before we
can land there?
What new primitive capabilities
does the web platform
require to get as much
utility as possible
without allowing user tracking?
The Chromium privacy sandbox
page links to the explainers
that we've published so far.
Tomorrow morning there's
a talk by Chris and Yoav
about the Blink process,
what an explainer is,
and the conversations
that we have
in public where we figure out
what to ship to solve problems
and what problems need
solving in the first place.
Please join us.
There are hard trade offs and
difficult design problems here.
Let's solve them together.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]