[MUSIC PLAYING]
YOAV WEISS: Hey.
Welcome.
I'm Yoav Weiss.
I work on Chrome, co-chairing
the Web Platform Incubation
Community Group at the
W3C and a Blink API owner,
among other roles.
CHRIS WILSON: And
I'm Chris Wilson.
I'm also a co-chair of the Web
Incubation Community Group,
and I'm a web developer
advocate at Google.
We're here to discuss how the
web platform continues to grow.
But more particularly,
to explain
how Chromium
manages new features
added to the web
platform and how
Google contributes to open
standards and works together
with the community.
Now, before we get going, we
wanted to define a few terms.
Because although you may have
heard these all the time,
there are some
subtle distinctions,
and they kind of get lost.
Now, Chrome, I would
hope everyone knows,
is Google's browser.
This wraps in a bunch of Google
services and user experience
features.
But Chrome is built on
top of Chromium, which
is an open source project.
And that core open
source project
also gets used by a
number of other browsers--
Edge, Samsung, Internet
Browser, many others.
Blink is the web platform
engine inside that.
Sometimes we'll say
Blink when really we
mean Chromium, and vice versa.
Sorry.
We've tried to script
this really well,
but I'm not positive
we'll do it right.
And Blink is built
around the implementation
of a number of features--
open standards based
web platform core
features that we've all
known to come and love
and HTML, CSS, JavaScript,
a bunch of other APIs.
Most of those are defined
in open collaborative forums
like the W3C, the
IETF, the WHATWG.
The last bit is one that
Yoav and I already mentioned,
which is the Web Platform
Incubation Community Group.
We usually call this the WICG.
We co-chair this, along with
Marcos Caceres from Mozilla
and Travis Leithead
from Microsoft.
And this is the
place where we start
the journey of a lot of
these collaborative efforts.
Now, we should be clear
that open source is not
the same as open standards.
That's the core of what we want
to discuss today, really-- how
these processes of
managing an open source
project like Chromium
interacts together
with the processes of
managing an open standards
platform like the web.
YOAV WEISS: So, yeah,
we're here at 10:00 AM
to talk about
processes, and I want
to apologize about that,
because no one really
likes bureaucracy.
Everyone have horror
stories of processes
that went horribly
wrong or make no sense.
And bureaucrat is
rarely a compliment.
But at the same time,
bureaucracy can be important.
Coordinating humans is hard.
Chromium is a huge open source
project that's seeing 90,000
commits a year from over 2,000
different contributors working
for 55 different
companies, potentially
with multiple organizations
inside of each company.
And each one of those parties
have slightly different
interests.
It's also important to
recognize that a lot
of those contributions are
coming from Google employees,
but non-Google contributors are
almost 20% of that pie chart.
And as someone who was a
Chromium contributor many years
before becoming a
Google employee,
that's something that's
near and dear to my heart.
So in order to make sure
that all those contributions
from different parties all make
sense, we need an open process.
We needed to make sure
that the project is
making progress
towards its goals
and remains true to its mission.
CHRIS WILSON: And
it's important to note
that open standards
organizations also
have their own processes.
Now, I'm going to
focus mostly on the W3C
during the course of this talk.
I'm on their advisory board, so
I have the most insight there.
But the diversity across other
open standards organizations
is actually fairly similar.
The W3C has over 400
different member companies,
participating in more than
40 active working groups
and interest groups,
and 300 community
groups that kind of explore
different topics in a less
organized way.
The main document that
governs the W3C's process
is more than 50 pages long.
So there are lots of
different people, lots
of different needs involved.
And in this context,
Chromium's engagement
is really just one
piece that needs to fit
into that standards process.
In fact, although
Google may dominate
the participation in
Chromium, we're not at all
the majority in standards.
Yoav just showed you this
pie chart of participants
in Chromium on the left.
The graph on the
right is the number
of individual participants
in the W3C by company.
Now, although Google is
still that largest slice
single company--
we do believe in and we
participate really heavily
in open standards efforts--
we're only about an eighth
of the overall participation.
In fact, if you add up all of
the Chromium browsers together,
like Microsoft's participation
and Samsung's participation
and Chrome, you'll find this
is still less than a quarter
of the whole
participation at the W3C.
The web is much broader
than just Chromium.
Now, Chrome is, however, fully
committed to the broader web.
In fact, the first
half of our mission
is explicitly to make the
web the premier platform
for its experiencing
the world's information.
The second half
of our mission is
to deliver the
best implementation
of that platform.
Now, it's natural to
ask, why do we really
care so much about the web?
We do work on at least one
other premier native platform.
And of course, our
revenue doesn't come
directly from the web itself.
We don't sell Chrome.
But the answer is one we've
talked about many, many times,
starting with the very
first Chrome Dev Summit.
Those of you who
participated in that
might recognize this slide
and the SLICE acronym.
We believe a Secure, Linkable,
Indexable, Composable,
Ephemeral platform is critical.
Above all, the fact that
this platform is open
makes it more powerful
than any single vendor.
Yes, even Google.
So these attributes
make a shared openly
defined platform, this critical
value for users and developers.
And although these core
critical attributes don't really
change over time,
like we're pretty much
using the same slide
from seven years ago--
well, six years ago--
we want the web to always be
open, secure, and ephemeral.
It's important to recognize
that the web needs
to evolve as computing evolves.
A viable platform cannot
afford to stand still.
Computing and how
we users experience
it continues to march
forward, and so does
our expectations of computing.
When I first started working on
the web platform 26 years ago,
it was a radically
different world,
when graphical UIs were still
a relatively new concept.
The smartphone that's
in my pocket right
now, the platform for most
of my web consumption,
that's more powerful than
the Cray supercomputers
that I worked with at that time.
Now, even in more recent times,
it took years for the web
to pivot, even as
a content platform,
from desktop to mobile.
The web was slow to
move from this kind
of hard-coded, pixel-perfect
desktop experience
to a mobile first
development model.
YOAV WEISS: And if we
want the web to remain
relevant for years
to come, there's
a lot of work to be done.
so?
We need the platform to
evolve, but what's the rush?
Admittedly, we are shipping
a lot of new features.
Can we just slow down?
Well, there are
multiple areas where
we think the web needs
to urgently improve.
Developer experience is one,
because we see developers
working around the web
platform's basic model of page
navigations to create
different models that fit them
and their users better.
We see them-- well, you--
using complex tools in order
to solve common problems.
And we feel like we
need to do better.
We need to provide better
building blocks that
will enable developers
to easily create
the experiences they need.
And the three talks coming
right after this one
will outline exactly what
we're doing on that front.
We also see users
spending more and more
of their time in native apps and
less of their time on the web.
We need the web to match
those users' expectations
of mobile experiences.
Highly related to that,
there's the performance front,
where we have data that
shows that most users still
have subpar experiences on the
web, which we know is causing
them frustration, at best.
And we need a faster web if we
want our users to stick around.
There are also new
user interaction models
that are arriving--
most notably, VR and AR-- that
the web needs to be ready for.
And finally, computing
has moved to mobile.
The web needs to
be as present there
as it is on desktop, because
this is where the users are.
So as the project is focused
on improving the web platform,
we have two major ways, two
major tools, to do that--
adding new features that will
help developers and users
and removing user-hostile
features from the platform.
Both of these have obvious
benefits, but also slightly
less obvious risks.
Removing features can
harm web compatibility
and break some
content that relies
on those harmful features.
But we feel strongly that the
platform cannot live forever
with the burden
of past mistakes.
And given our market
share, we feel
like it's our responsibility to
take on that compatibility risk
and enable other
browsers to follow.
And adding new features,
especially when
we are the first to ship
them, carries another risk--
interoperability risk.
Different stakeholders
in the platform
have different views on
the urgency of improving it
and different levels
of investment in it
and, therefore, can
focus on different things
that matter to them.
Maybe some use case that
we think is critical
is something that they are not
willing to invest resources
in or think that the
user and developer
benefits don't outweigh the
extra complexity and cost.
And if other browsers never
adopt the features we ship,
they will never
be interoperable.
And developers won't be able
to use them across the web
as part of a platform,
which is not our goal.
At the same time, if every
browser waited for others
to ship first, that would result
in deadlock and stagnation.
And sometimes in order
to convince other vendors
that a use case is
indeed important,
we need data that can only be
gathered by real-life usage.
Therefore, we unfortunately
often find ourselves
in a position where we are
the first browser engine
to ship new features.
In order to reduce
the risk there,
we make sure there is a
clear path for other vendors
to follow by investing heavily
in testing infrastructure,
requiring comprehensive
test suites,
as well as detailed
specifications
for the features we ship.
So that even if we
can't get those features
to be interoperable
out the gate,
we get to eventual
interoperability.
And in order to properly
manage that risk versus benefit
calculus, we have
the Blink process.
CHRIS WILSON: So if
you've interacted at all
with the Chromium
open source project,
you've probably seen people
talking about intents.
Intents to implement,
intents to ship.
These intents are part of
the Blink process, where
a set of trusted
Chromium engineers
called the API
owners, such as Yoav,
make sure that the
trade-off is being
taken into account by
the engineers working
on different features.
Mozilla has a very
similar process.
Part of our process grew from
the WebKit process, as well.
But as part of these
processes, engineers
need to show that there's
industry agreement or backing,
that the feature they're trying
to ship is an important one,
and also that the feature's
design was properly reviewed.
That Blink process is not a
replacement for the standards
process, but a separate one.
And it's not determining
what gets standardized,
but what code can land in
Chromium turned on by default.
Now, those standards
processes, on the other hand,
are a lot broader, and they
can be a lot slower, too.
As I pointed out
before, Chromium
is just one engine and one slice
of the participation driving
standards.
Now, we do try
very hard to build
that collaboration
between different teams
from different organizations and
across the wider web standards
community by consistently
participating
in those open forums--
the W3C, the WHATWG, the IETF,
TC39, and ECMA, and the like--
and bringing our
needs to those groups
to incubate them in public.
And this process
of incubation first
is one that we actually
started championing in Chromium
a few years ago as a way
to explore new additions
to the web platform
with low overhead,
without committing
first, without saying,
hey, we're going to ship
this feature at some point
in the very near future.
Because some ideas fail.
In fact, some ideas should fail.
But you don't really
know that upfront.
We didn't want to get those
ideas baked into a standard
before we realized, hey, maybe
this wasn't such a great idea.
Incubation in the
WICG, for example,
is a great way to work
together in public
and collect intellectual
property commitments
so eventual standards
will be free to implement,
but with low overhead.
In short, the idea
was to get to 80%
of the exploration with
a much lower overhead,
but responsibly, as well.
Now, this leads to a
couple of key points.
First, incubations
can actively fail.
They can go into a deep freeze.
They can wait for more
data, some other change.
Or in some cases, they may ship
in one browser or another prior
to transitioning to an
official recognized standard.
Now, in that latter case, this
is not the end of the story.
This isn't the endpoint.
Not everyone agrees on which
incubations are ready to ship.
Everybody has
different priorities.
But when Chromium
ships incubation
status specifications because
we believe they're needed,
but we don't have agreement
from other vendors or developers
to turn them into
standards yet, we're
taking on a deeper
responsibility.
We have to continue to
maintain that feature.
We have to continue to push
for cross-vendor collaboration
and standardization.
And if those features do get
picked up by others later,
we need to work together
to possibly change
what we already
shipped to make them
truly cross-industry standards.
Incubations are not standards--
yet, at least.
Incubations only
turn into standards
when a sufficiently
cross-industry set
of participants
in open standards
agree that they should
become interoperable.
Until multiple vendors want
to ship those implementations,
there's only so much one
vendor can really do.
Now, we do control
our ship cycles.
We choose what features
Chromium is going to ship
and what features
Chromium believes
are critical to
provide to developers.
But what becomes a standard
is an open community decision.
The broader community of
developers and vendors
need to want this
feature to happen.
So as incubations mature
and there's open agreement
that there should be an
interoperable standard,
it's time to create
a working group
with multiple
cross-industry stakeholders,
or be adopted by
a working group,
and set timelines
for deliverables.
Formalize the use cases.
Finalize the design.
Make sure you have wide
review of that design.
If you haven't already
completed addressing
accessibility and privacy
and internationalization
and other wide
review issues, now
is the time to
finish all of that.
You need to finalize
a test suite.
Make sure that we're fully
making sure that this
is going to be interoperable.
And then, of course,
finalize the standard,
actually get it out in public.
Now, this is a
super long process.
Also, this can be different
across different organizations,
like the W3C versus
the WHATWG, and I
don't want to spend all
our time in that detail.
But with this in
mind as the end goal,
we wanted to dive
into the journey
of a feature in Chromium
from idea to shipping.
And that really
is where we start.
The first question is,
well, what do we work on?
And I know it's really
tempting to think that Google
has some super detailed
internal feature
plan of exactly what the
priority is of all features
for the next 5 or 10 years
is for the web, sorted
in priority order, exact
ship dates, everything.
Of course, we do try to plan.
That is not really
the way that it works.
In reality, we listen
to a lot of inputs.
We have to know what
areas need attention.
And we work very
closely together
with individual web
developer partners
out there to get insight into
how their work is progressing.
You know, ask them where the
rough edges of the web are.
We also recommend
that web developers
use a tool initiated by our
colleagues at Microsoft,
the Web We Want
initiative, which
is a great place to
share ideas that you
may have as developers.
So browser and
platform engine people,
we participate in triaging
these suggestions.
We look at them.
We see what people think is
important to add to the web
platform and try to
take it from there.
And both of us, as well as
our co-chairs and many others
in the web platform
standard space,
we participate in discussions
in the WICG discourse
tool, which you can find
from our site at wicg.io.
This is where a lot of
new incubations pop up.
And then, finally,
we participate
in a number of other channels.
We listen to the results
of the MDN survey.
We pay a lot of attention
to the framework ecosystem.
Shubhie and Houssein will
detail that later this morning.
And of course, a lot of other
channels and conversations.
Now, once we've identified
a problem space that we want
to address, we-- well, engineers
on the Chromium project--
start a process of exploring
that feature space.
And step one in that
process is to spend time
researching the problem.
Now, we're not always perfect
at separating this stage out,
but we try very hard to
focus first on the problem.
Not a proposed solution, but
researching the use cases,
figuring out the problem space
the developer needs first,
rather than inventing
a solution first.
The goal of this stage is to
publish, publicly publish,
an explainer with those
use cases detailed.
There might be a
suggested solution,
but it's critically
important for us
not to focus on that
first, not to fall in love
with our first good idea.
To put it another way,
if the explainer contains
a design for a
really great hammer,
every use case is going
to look like a nail.
You might need an electric
screwdriver instead.
And you won't know
that unless you
research what kind of
fasteners are the use cases.
So an explainer is a short--
hopefully no more
than a page or two--
explanation of the problem
space at this point.
It grows later.
This is the point
where the explainer
should go to a public forum.
So frequently, in
Chromium, these
get published to the WICG
discourse to attract attention.
This results in a file
like this, by the way.
This is one of the very first
really well-known explainers,
the service worker explainer.
And we strongly
encourage developers
to participate at this stage,
both by sharing what you need
to spark these ideas and
these use cases, filing needs
in the Web We Want
tool or whatever.
But also, participating
in the early discussion
of those features, like
watch the ideas that
get shared in the WICG
discourse, comment on them,
give us your feedback on them.
We're building this platform
for you, not for ourselves.
And in terms of maturity,
though, it's really important
to understand at
this stage, this
is not a done, baked feature.
This is like a newborn kitten.
It's hard to tell
exactly what it's
going to look like
as it matures,
and it needs a lot of
care and attention.
YOAV WEISS: The next step, once
we have a clear understanding
of what we're trying
to solve and why,
is to figure out what a solution
may look like, try it out, see
how it can be improved,
and basically rinse
and repeat that process
until we're fairly
confident we got it right.
At this point, the
Chromium engineers
working on this
problem would want
to notify others on
the projects that they
plan to start lending code
related to the problem
behind a flag turned
off by default.
This is what they intent
to prototype email is for.
Intent emails, in general,
are sent over to the Blink Dev
mailing list and serve
as a notification
to the broader
community of work that's
happening in certain areas.
That step was previously
called Intent to Implement,
but that resulted
in some confusion,
because it wasn't really
clear that this only
means lending code behind a
flag and not some stronger
commitment.
As a result, Mozilla
renamed their similar step
in their process to
Intent to Prototype,
and we very recently, just
last week, aligned with them.
Got to love conference-driven
development, huh, Chris?
The purpose of this
step is to make
sure code owners won't be
surprised when they see code
starting to land in this area.
But starting to work
on a certain prototype
doesn't require
project-wide approvals.
This is also a good
checkpoint to make sure
that the feature is on the
right track for getting
a wide review and a tag
review for the explainer
in the initial design
and making sure
that we get feedback and
opinions from other browser
vendors.
And if that hasn't happened
yet, that checkpoint
gives us a lot of
time to still do
that and correct that course.
How can developers get involved?
Browser engineers at this
stage are craving for feedback.
The [? last ?] steps
deliverable was an explainer
outlining the use cases.
One form of feedback could
be to point out related use
cases that are not addressed.
Or otherwise, in case
there is a proposed design,
pointing out ways in which
the design can be improved.
And alternatively, a
statement of support
and real-life examples
related to the use cases
can be extremely helpful.
And if this is a subject
you're familiar with
and want to get
more involved, you
can just hop over
to the GitHub repo
and participate in
that early design work.
And by the time intent
to prototype is sent,
there is probably some
rough design in mind,
but it's still not too
late to change course.
At that point, feedback on
the API shape, its ergonomics,
or its ability to solve your
problem is very much welcome.
And at that stage, some
code might be landing,
and the API opens its eyes
and starts wobbling around.
But it's still extremely
early, so no telling
how it will end up.
And also, I'm now
legally obliged
to say that these
are my kittens,
and the credit for the
photos go to my kids,
which this is all they do.
CHRIS WILSON: So the next major
step in a feature's journey
is to evolve that design
by experimenting in code,
working together
with the community,
just plain iterating
on development.
And at this point,
engineers are going
to be landing code in
Chromium under flags
and asking developers to
try out those designs,
even though the features
are switched off
by default for users.
This is also the stage where
open collaboration with others
in the standards space
becomes even more
important to make this a
multi-stakeholder project.
So how do developers get
involved at this point?
Well, this stage is really
about developer involvement.
This is where we're
asking developers
to try out the designs,
to check out a feature,
switching on flags
and testing them out
with the understanding, of
course, that they may not ship.
They certainly may not ship in
that particular form at all.
But we also have
another tool that
comes into play at this point
that we wanted to mention.
And in Chrome, we have this
tool called Origin Trials.
Now, this is not a mandatory
step for feature development.
It's a useful one,
a lot of time,
because it's a way to get
even broader developer testing
on a particular feature.
A Chromium engineer communicates
this intent to experiment,
and then any developer
out there can register
for a key for their domain.
And that will turn on the
feature for their users,
even if the users
don't enable the flag
or have no idea what
this flag is about.
This Origin Trial gets some
specific features to prevent it
from getting too popular
or burning it into the web
platform accidentally.
This is a way to
broadly test features
with a wide variety of users,
not just those, like most of us
here, who might be convinced
to turn on some magic flags.
But at this point, the feature's
kind of like a teenager.
And as a parent of a
teenager or myself,
and as a former
teenager, it's maturing.
It's pretty stable.
It's self-supporting,
for the most part.
And you can see a
lot of the shape
that it's starting to take
as it becomes a real grownup.
YOAV WEISS: And finally,
when we're confident enough
that an API is in a good shape
and would solve real developer
and user problems, that's when
it's time to try and ship it.
That's the point in the process
that's a bit more strict.
Chromium developers that want
to ship a feature by default
need to prove that it's
mature enough to do that
without excessive risk.
We talked earlier about the
risk and benefit assessment
that API owners need to do
in order to ship features.
This is the point where
that assessment happens.
And shipping new features
requires three API owners
to sign off on it
or LGTM it, which
stands for Looks Good To Me.
It's important to note that the
fact that an intent email was
sent to Blink Dev doesn't--
so it means that the
team behind the feature
thinks that it's ready.
But it doesn't yet mean
that it will ship soon.
There are many cases where
the feature team is slightly
optimistic, and the
API owners conclude
that there's more
work to be done
before the feature can ship.
That's fine and a natural
part of the process.
There are also cases which are
a bit more rare of features that
don't ship at all due to
fundamental disagreements,
which mean that the risk
inherent in the feature
outweighs the benefits of--
outweighs its benefits.
And while the exciting
parts of the process
revolve around
shipping new things,
removing old and busted
parts of the platform
is equally important for
security performance, as well
as interoperability.
If we refuse to
remove features, that
means that adding
any new feature
would make it part of
the platform forever.
And willingness to
take some compact risk
and remove features
helps us to ship faster
and can also help other
browser vendors, who can then
follow in their footsteps
with reduced compatibility
risk for their users.
Feature removal is equally
part of the process
subject to an intent to remove.
That requires approval
from three API owners,
just like shipping
a new feature.
That approval typically
requires a high bar-- or rather,
low usage of the feature--
in order to make sure that the
removal won't break the web
and won't cause too
much compatibility pain.
And because we're
all humans, we also
need to account for cases
where we got it wrong.
Again, one of the
principles that
enable us to take that
interoperability risk
of shipping first
is our willingness
to change course
and remove features
if we realize we
need to modify them
or even unship them entirely.
There are cases where
after we shipped,
substantial feedback from
other vendors and developers
convinced us that we need
to change the API shape.
And our willingness to
make those breaking changes
enables us to listen and
act on that feedback.
Prominent examples include
the web components V0,
which shipped and is now
in the process of being
removed in favor of web
components V1 as well as video.
CHRIS WILSON: WebVR, which we
didn't actually entirely ship
but had to take feedback on.
Audio AutoPlay, where we
radically changed the way
that we detected
AutoPlay scenarios.
YOAV WEISS: Yup.
And so even when an
API is about to ship,
there's still a lot of room
for developer involvement
and feedback.
Feedback on the intent thread
can provide a lot of insights
and can influence the
API owner's decision.
Similarly to the previous
step, playing around
with the implemented
API by turning on flags
before it's shipped
and reporting issue,
or even after it's
shipped, can be extremely
helpful for newly shipped APIs.
And finally, actually using
the APIs you find useful
is an extremely
strong signal for us
to ensure us that we
made the right decision.
And at this point, the feature
is fully mature, on its own,
theoretically in the wild.
But in practice, just
sits on the couch all day.
This is where the metaphor
kind of breaks down.
So, to recap, the
typical journey of an API
goes from researching
the problem space,
publishing an explainer
with use cases,
designing a solution in the
open with interested parties,
experimenting with
that solution,
and eventually
shipping it or not.
And note that at
any stage, we can
decide that we need to go
back and address some issues.
For example, an origin
trial can reveal
that there are some
problems in the design
or the understanding
of the problem space
and cause us to go back to
one or two steps before that.
And on top of that, there
are also always exceptions
to that general flow.
So just last week, we had
an intent to experiment
for an origin trial that was
required in order to gather
data to understand
a certain use case
and know whether
it will or will not
provide performance benefits.
So an origin trial is part
of step zero, if you will.
CHRIS WILSON: So what we
would like you to take away
from this talk is,
first, there is
a difference between Chromium
process and standards process.
They work together,
but they're not
replacements for each other.
Our intent process is
intended to make it possible
for us to move the
web platform forward,
even if we have to
go out on a limb
sometimes, but also work
together with the standards
process.
This is all done in
public on purpose,
and we'd really love to
get developer involvement
at every stage of this.
Adopt an API space.
Propose needs in Web We Want.
Look at proposals on
the WICG discourse.
File issues in individual
feature featuring incubations.
Watch the intents on Blink Dev.
Give us feedback
on all those things
you care about, because that's
what we're really looking for.
And with that,
we'd like to close.
Thank you so much
for your attention.
YOAV WEISS: Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]