SOC SIENG: There are
many ways to add support
for payments on your website.
But which one is right for
you and your customers?
My name is Soc.
And I am a developer
advocate with Google Pay.
Today, I want to
provide some guidance
on how you, as developers, can
enhance the online checkout
experience for your customers.
Specifically, I'll
walk you through how
to make payments
simple and more secure
with autofill and Google Pay.
In many cases, people
make online purchases
with a credit or debit card.
Providing this
information is often
accompanied with requests
for other details,
like a user's shipping
or billing address.
Autofill simplifies this
experience for users
by making their
payment details readily
available during
the checkout flow.
Autofill does most of
the work for the user.
And no additional effort is
required by website operators
to take advantage of it.
Autofill works by providing
a list of suggested payment
and contact details
that have been
saved to the user's browser.
If the user is
signed into Chrome,
Chrome autofill extends
this by asking the user
to save these details
to their Google account.
This action makes the user's
payment and contact details
available across any of
the Chrome-enabled devices.
Checkout forms can
vary significantly
from one website to another.
To account for this,
Chrome autofill
uses heuristics to identify
payment and contact detail
fields.
To improve the
effectiveness of autofill
and to ensure that
your users have
a great autofill experience,
make sure your form fields are
tagged with their
respective attributes
for credit card fields
and address fields.
Links to autofill resources
can be found in the video's
description below.
With Google Pay, you can
make checkout even easier
for customers by eliminating
payment and shipping
forms altogether.
Google Pay provides users with
a simple and secure method
for entering their
payment and shipping
information on websites.
Plus, it works across
all modern browsers.
Hundreds of millions
of Google users
already have their payment
details saved to Google Pay.
That means purchases
are just a click away.
They don't even
need to enter a CVC.
In addition to accepting credit
card and debit card payments,
Google Pay offers additional
payment methods like PayPal.
Once configured, using
PayPal as a payment method
with Google Pay
no longer requires
the user to re-enter
their PayPal
password when making a payment.
The security and privacy of user
data is paramount to Google.
And this is no
different when it comes
to payment data in Google Pay.
Payment credentials
are encrypted
for secure payment processing.
Integrating the Google Pay
button into your website
is easy, and testing it out
requires very little effort.
First, include the Google
Pay JavaScript file,
check if the user is ready to
pay, add the Google Pay button,
request payment data, and
finally, extract the payment
token for processing.
A detailed step-by-step guide is
available as a code lab linked
in the description below.
To speed up and simplify
the purchasing experience
for your customers, add
the Google Pay button
to checkout floor, shopping
cart, and product pages.
Google Pay is always
making improvements
for both our
merchants and users.
So keep an eye out for new
features, like promo codes
and offers.
We've also been experimenting
with enhancements
to the Google Pay button.
And early results have
shown increased usage rates
amongst users.
If you're interested in early
access to these new features,
please let us know by following
the link in the description
below.
What about the
Payment Request API?
The Payment Request
API is a W3C standard
that helps users share
their payment and contact
details with websites
using web or native payment
apps, like Google Pay.
If you are a payment
app provider,
we encourage you to explore the
Payment Request APIs as a way
to offer your users an enhanced
experience on Chrome browsers.
Payment app creators can
use the web payment standard
to deliver a better
user experience.
The Google Pay
JavaScript Library
leverages the
Payment Request API
to provide a native experience
on Chrome for Android
with a native experience rolling
out soon on Chrome for desktop.
At the moment, the
Payment Request API
is not consistently
supported across all browsers
and requires developers to
include browser specific logic.
Therefore, to accept
Google Pay, we
recommend that developers
integrate with the Google Pay
JavaScript Library directly.
Google Pay can simplify
your customer's purchasing
experience by eliminating the
need to interact with a payment
form completely.
In addition, it provides
a simple browser agnostic
API for developers, a
simple and secure payment
experience for users on
both mobile and desktop,
support for additional forms
of payment, and, in the future,
access to features like
promo code and offers.
When used together,
autofill and Google Pay
can help make payments
simple and secure.
Thanks for watching
and see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]