[MUSIC PLAYING]
PHIL WALTON: Hey, everyone.
My name is Philip Walton.
I'm an engineer on the Chrome
team working on web performance
and Service Worker tooling.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: And I'm Ewa.
I'm also an engineer
on the Chrome team.
Today we're going to talk about
Service Worker from the speed
and resilience perspective.
We'll look into how our
decisions regarding Service
Worker implementation
can influence,
both positively and negatively,
our site's performance.
And we hope that by
the end of this talk,
you'll have a really
good understanding
of all the trade-offs involved
in using this more and more
mainstream technology.
PHIL WALTON: So Ewa,
I noticed you said
Service Worker was mainstream.
What makes you say that?
EWA GASPEROWICZ:
Well, Service Worker
is now supported in all
modern browsers, which
means you can move
from treating this
as a pure progressive
enhancement
and treat it as a core part
of your site's architecture.
Service Worker can do many
things, but in this talk
we'll focus especially on
its caching capabilities.
Often when we think about
Service Worker and caching,
we usually associate it with
providing offline support.
After all, one of the main
achievements of Service Worker
was that we finally could get
rid of the offline downosaur
and send him to the
well-deserved retirement.
But apart from
that, Service Worker
can also be a great
tool for improving
the performance of
your online site,
especially for your
returning users.
When used right, it can give
you a serious boost in terms
of speed on the repeated visit.
PHIL WALTON: That's right.
And on the other hand,
when used incorrectly
or without proper
analysis, it can actually
hamper a site's
performance, or even
derail the whole
experience altogether.
So as developers,
it's critical that we
understand how
Service Worker affects
the performance of our site.
As with any technology, there
are both costs and benefits.
And we want to
maximize the benefits
while minimizing the costs.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: Well,
using Service Worker
brings a lot of benefits
in terms of performance.
In many cases it allows you to
overcome the network latency
entirely.
For example, if you
cache your entire app,
you don't need to go
to the network anymore.
Also, if you have
some cached content,
you can show it
immediately, even
if a bit stale, and look for
the updates in the background
at the same time.
It can also make your average
requests smaller on average.
For example, in
the app show model
where you're fetching just
partial part of your page
rather than the
full HTML each time.
Finally, there are some
more subtle benefits.
For example, we know
that JavaScripts
need to be parsed, compiled, and
executed before it can be used.
This can take time.
So engines like V8
use some heuristics
to see if they can
actually store the bytecode
from these phases to be
used on repeated visits
to avoid this cost.
Now in Service Worker, the
chances of a repeated visit
are pretty high.
So it can opt into
that optimization
automatically for you.
This means that it stores
the script as bytecode
by default, making the
repeated visits faster.
All these are really
good performance reasons
to implement Service
Worker on your page.
But it's not for free.
Phil, what are the
costs of running
Service Worker on your page?
PHIL WALTON: Yeah, so the
first and arguably most often
overlooked cost
of Service Worker
is that it can take time for
the Service Worker process
to start up if it's
not already running.
And this can happen
if a user hasn't
visited your site in a while.
Let me show you what I mean.
Consider a basic
network first strategy
in which the service worker
just forwards the request
from the web app
onto the network
and doesn't touch
the cache at all.
Since this web app is
running a service worker,
every request then has to go
through that service worker,
and if the service worker
process isn't currently
running, the web app has to wait
for the browser to spin it up
before it can make any request.
So let's take a look
at the total time
it takes to make a request
in various scenarios.
In the case where the web app
isn't using Service Worker,
the total time is just the
total of network latency.
In the case where the web
app is using Service Worker
and that service worker
is already running,
there is a little
bit of extra cost
because it has to go
through the service worker--
the request has to go
but that cost isn't
usually too high.
However, in the case where the
service worker is not running
and needs to boot
up, that startup time
can really delay the response.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: So
in cases like this
where the service
worker is actually not
running on the page,
how long does it usually
take to boot up?
PHIL WALTON: So that's
a good question.
And the honest answer is it
depends on the user's device,
but fortunately there
is an easy way you
can measure this cost yourself.
So this code here uses
the performance timeline
to get performance data
for a particular URL.
If the request for the URL went
through the service worker,
then the worker start property
on the performance entry
will mark the moment
right before the service
worker was run.
And the request
start property will
mark the moment the
service worker received
the fetch event.
So the difference between
these two timestamps
is the total time it took
for the worker to start up.
And if the service worker
process was already running,
this time will be usually
zero or close to zero.
And so I actually measure
service worker start up
time on my website,
philipwalton.com, and here's
what I found when
looking at my own data.
When users visits my site for
the first time-- or, sorry,
for the first time after
installing the service worker--
it's already running only
about 25% of the time.
That means 75% of the time the
service worker is not running
and needs to take
some time to start up.
For those cases, I found
that on desktop it's
usually between 20 and 100
milliseconds to start up,
but on mobile it can be more
like 100 to 500 milliseconds,
and at the 95th
percentile, sometimes it's
more than a second.
So let me reiterate, these
are stats from my website.
The numbers you see
might be different,
but this should give
you a general idea
of what's possible.
Another cost of using Service
Worker is that the cache reads
aren't always instant.
And this affects
any caching strategy
where the service worker
has to wait for the cache
to either miss or error before
it can go to the network.
We saw before that a
network first strategy
can be slow when you're not
using Service Worker at all.
But what about strategies
that use cache, or start
with the cache, anyway?
A cache first strategy
will initially
look for a response in the
cache, and if one is found
it'll be used.
But if it's not found or
there's a timeout or error,
like I mentioned, it will
fall back to the network.
So here's how the performance
of cache first strategies
break down in
different scenarios.
The most common
case is going to be
the one at the top,
which is very fast when
there's a cache hit.
But this is not the
only possibility.
There could also
be a cache miss,
there could be a slow cache,
you could have a timeout--
remember, there's
also the possibility
of the service
worker isn't running
and so then that could
delay it as well.
All of these bad cases could
happen at the same time.
So while it's definitely
possible to have a cache
first strategy that's faster
than not using a service
worker, look at how
many of these examples
end up being slower.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: So Phil.
I'm wondering how likely is it
that the slow cases actually
occur.
Is it measurable somehow?
PHIL WALTON: Yeah.
So this is also measurable.
It's a little bit trickier than
the last example I was showing.
So this, the same way, uses
the performance timeline,
and you can look at the
entries transfer size property.
If the transfer
size is zero, that
means the request either
came from the cache
or came from the service worker.
For requests that you know are
being handled by the service
worker because you set
up a route for that URL,
you can look at the time
between the response start
property and the
request start property
and see the total strategy time.
Of course, that doesn't tell
you if it was just handled
by the cache, if it was handled
by cache and the network.
If you need more granular
timing data into that stuff,
then you have to add
these performance
marks in your service
worker itself.
You can use something
like performance.now.
and then post message this
data back to the window.
It's a bit clunky at the
moment, to be honest,
but we have a new API proposal
for fetch event work timing
that should make this
easier in the future.
And it is a proposal right now.
So if you want to offer
feedback on the design,
go to this short link
here on the slide,
and we love your feedback,
and you can chime in.
So the last call that
we want to point out
is that requests made from
within the service worker
can sometimes compete
with higher priority
requests on the window.
And the cause of this is usually
overaggressive pre-caching
or pre-caching before
the window has finished
loading all of its resources.
So for example, if you're
pre-caching literally
every single asset
on your website,
you could potentially
get to a situation
where those pre-cache
requests get
queued ahead of more important
requests that the user needs.
So while APIs like
priority hints
can solve this issue somewhat,
the recommended approach right
now is just to wait to
register your service worker
until after the load event.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: OK.
Thanks, Phil, for the thorough
walkthrough through the costs.
So once we know all this and
we know how to measure it,
how does this translate into
the design of Service Worker?
Well, usually there are three
sources the service worker gets
content from, either from
network, either from the cache,
or it can also
generate it on the fly,
for example, by using
some templating logic.
When designing Service
Worker, your role
is to find a combination
of these three sources
that is the most
efficient for the use
cases on your web pages.
This is the serving
strategy of Service Worker.
Of course, in order to use
anything from the cache,
we need to populate it first
with the resources first.
And this is the caching
strategy of Service Worker.
Taking all these aspects into
account can be quite daunting,
but fortunately there are
tools that make it easier.
For example, Workbox
is a set of libraries
that make it easy
to cache assets
and take advantage of Service
Worker features and related
APIs.
In this talk we'll focus on
the general design principles
that you can implement
yourself in Service Worker.
But we will also call out
some of the Workbox features
that can help you out in
some common scenarios.
PHIL WALTON: OK, so
let's start with looking
at the serving strategies for
Service Worker implementations.
And given what we said about
the costs that can be associated
with using Service Worker,
you're probably wondering,
is it possible to avoid these
costs entirely and make sure
that my site actually loads
faster than it would have
without the service worker?
So the first and arguably
most important step
in building a fast site
with A Service worker
is an understanding
of which requests
are most important to optimize.
So broadly speaking,
there are two types
of requests, navigation
requests and resource requests.
Navigation requests are
for your full HTML pages
and resource requests
are for the assets
like JavaScript, CSS, and
images that those pages then
reference.
So in my experience with
talking to other developers
about Service Worker
implementations,
I found that most
people are generally
pretty good at responding
to resource requests
from the cache,
but unfortunately I
don't see a lot of people
responding to navigation
requests from the cache.
And that's really too bad,
because navigation requests
are typically where the biggest
performance gains can be made.
So here's why.
The key difference
between resource requests
and navigation requests is that
navigation requests are likely
already being cached
by the browser.
In addition, you
can already use APIs
like link rel preload
to warm the HTTP
cache for future requests.
So if all your service
worker is doing
is pre-caching static
resources, you're
essentially just recreating
what the browser is already
doing for you.
Navigation requests,
on the other hand,
are completely different.
In general it's not recommended
to put caching headers on pages
that you navigate to because,
obviously the content might
change but the URL doesn't,
and so that can get you
into trouble.
Which means that
navigation requests
don't benefit from the
HTTP cache in the same way
that resource requests do.
They also don't work with
APIs like link rel preload.
And to top all that off,
navigation requests are
typically the ones that
will encounter a service
worker that's not running,
whereas resource requests,
by the time the service worker
starts up the navigation
requests, it's already running
and so those work just fine.
So don't get me wrong.
I'm not suggesting that you
ignore resource requests
and don't cache them.
You should cache them, because
that can give you more control
and you can get the
bytecode optimization
that Ewa mentioned.
But what I am suggesting is
that if you want your site
to be as fast as
possible you have
to respond to navigation
requests from the cache
as well.
So here are three
practical and concrete ways
you can speed up
navigation requests
and avoid most of the
Service Worker costs
that I mentioned earlier.
First, as I just said,
respond to navigation requests
from the cache.
Even if you eventually
need to go to the network,
you should respond
with something
right away so the
user understands
that it's happening, that
the request is working.
A simple way to do
this with Workbox
is to use either a cache first
strategy or a stale while
revalidate strategy.
Personally, I like
stale while revalidate
because it gives
you an opportunity
to check for updates
in the background,
and then you can notify the
user if there's new content.
In terms of performance,
as you can see,
responding from the
cache is generally faster
when not using a service worker.
And that's even true in
cases where the service
worker's asleep and needs
to start up, or in cases
where the cache is slow.
The only situation it's worse
is when there's a cache miss
and you have to go to
the network anyway.
But that's to be expected.
So I know what many of you
here are probably thinking.
There's absolutely no way that
I can respond to all navigation
requests with cache content.
I need my content
to be up to date.
I need it to be fresh.
And this is true.
Many apps just simply cannot
provide value with stale
content.
They have to have fresh content.
But just because you
need to fetch something
from the network
doesn't mean that you
need to fetch the entire
HTML page from the network.
So my second tip is that when
the network content is truly
required, fetch just the minimum
amount of content you need,
and then combine that
content with other parts
of the page, which should
already be in the cache.
And even better is
if you can combine
that content in the form of a
streaming response to the user.
So let me show you an example
of what I mean by that.
A lot of HTML pages
have a structure
that looks something like this.
You have kind of a head section,
a header, navigation, sidebar,
footer, and lot of these
sections of the page
repeat on every single
page throughout your site.
The only thing that changes is
often a single content area,
like you can see here.
So in these types of
situations, clearly
it's more efficient
to just fetch
the stuff that's changed rather
than fetching all of that stuff
every time.
If you've ever built a
single page application
you're probably kind of
familiar with this concept,
though the streaming
part might be new to you.
So here's a visualization
of the performance breakdown
between traditional
network responses
and a streaming response
that combines network
content with cache content.
So in the example on top,
since the network request
is for the full HTML page, you
can see it takes a long time,
and in the example
on the bottom,
the network request is for
a smaller part of the HTML,
and so there's less
data to be transferred.
So it will typically
take less time.
In addition, the cached content
can be fetched in parallel
with the network
content so it doesn't
add to the total time it
takes to make the request.
And lastly-- and this is the
best part about streaming--
since it is a
stream, we don't have
to wait until all the
content is available to start
sending something to the user.
As soon as we have
the cached content
from the start of the
page, the header section,
we can send it to
the user right away.
And then we can just
add to the stream
once we get more network
content in later.
So the overall experience is a
much faster time to first byte
and then a faster
time overall as well
If you've never used
streams before, you
might be a little bit
scared of the idea.
You might think
it's complicated.
But actually, with
Workbox it's really easy.
So what you do is you just
register a route like you would
do with any Workbox
strategy, and then
you invoke the strategy function
from the Workbox streams
package.
The strategy function takes
an array of other Workbox
strategies and each
of these is expected
to resolve to a response that
you then stitch together,
and Workbox stitches it together
in the form of a stream.
In this case, I'm
using cache first
for the header part
and footer part,
and I'm using network
first for the content
so I can make sure
that it's fresh.
And that's really it.
Workbox takes care of
merging this concept together
in a stream, and if the
browser doesn't support
streams it automatically falls
back to a single text response.
And because the
strategy requests
less content from the
network and because it
can read from the
cache in parallel,
it's typically
quite a bit faster
than the no service worker case.
Of course, the actual
speed differences
will depend on the size
of the content area
relative to the
entire HTML page.
And that will vary
from site to site.
But in general, streaming cache
content with network content
is one of the fastest ways to
respond to navigation requests.
I say one of the fastest
ways because there actually
is one more optimization that
we can get this even faster.
So the last technique
for speeding up
navigations that I
want to talk about
is a new API called
Navigation Preload, which
allows you to make the
navigation request in parallel
with the service
worker starting up,
essentially eliminating that
Service Worker boot up cost
that I mentioned before.
So by now you've probably
seen this chart many times.
You understand that the
Service Worker boot up time can
extend the navigation request.
So with Navigation
Preload, what you do is
you just do these
requests in parallel.
And the way that this
works is the browser that
sets this Service Worker
navigation preload header
on the preload request, and
then that allows your server
to respond to this request as
it would have had the request
come directly from the
service worker itself.
So for example, if you're using
the streaming partials strategy
that I just discussed,
you could respond
to the navigation
preload request the same
as you would have if it had
come from the service worker.
To use Navigation Preload,
it's relatively easy.
All you have to
do is enable it--
you probably want to
feature detect first,
but then you enable it at any
point in the lifecycle, really,
but it's often best to do
it in the activate event.
And then once you've
enabled it, fetch events
for navigation requests
will have access
to a preload response
property which you can then
use however you want.
And looking at the
performance of this technique,
you'll see how navigation
requests with Navigation
Preload are even faster than the
already fast streaming example.
And one last thing I want to
say about Navigation Preload
is that you really
only want to use it
in cases where you know you're
going to have to make a network
request on navigations.
If you can use just the cache
first strategy to respond
to navigations, then
that ends up being faster
and then you waste
the network request.
So in general,
only use it if you
know that you have to use
content from the network.
So to summarize everything I've
said so far, even though there
are definitely some costs
associated with using Service
Worker, with the proper
serving strategy you can easily
overcome these costs
and you can end up
with a even faster loading
site than what you could have
done without Service Worker.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: OK.
Now let's talk a bit about the
caching part of the Service
Worker.
When we think about
cache management,
we usually want to
achieve the following.
We want to start the right
resources at the right time
while controlling the overall
size of our application.
We definitely want to
prevent quota overflow,
because as developers, we do
have quite a bit of storage
space on users' device,
but it's not unlimited,
so we need to stick to that.
And we also want
our resources to be
as fresh as possible,
which means we
need to have efficient updates.
Now when it comes
to right resources,
it's good to understand
what you actually
want to put in the cache
in the first place.
Resources are a little
bit like food, you know.
There are the critical
ones, really important ones
like some HTML core
scripts or basic styles.
This should really get
the highest priority
in terms of cache.
Then there are non-critical
ones, for example,
images that are not
visible straight away,
or some big media files or
some additional widgets.
We cache them on the
best effort basis.
And finally,
there's trash, which
means stuff that should not
be there in the first place.
This is the bloat, the
unnecessary parts of your page,
like unoptimized images, dead
code, unused script, and so on.
Why do we have
trash in our pages?
Well, because we're
humans and sometimes
our projects are
simply not perfect.
This moment, when
you're considering
how to shape your caching
strategy for Service Worker,
is a great time to
stop for a while,
make an audit of
your page, and get
rid of all that unnecessary
part before they end up
clogging your user's device.
So reviewing your
app and understanding
which resources are critical
and which are not so critical
will really help you later
in designing and updating
your cache in an
efficient manner.
Now what about timing?
Usually we cache assets either
in the install event of Service
Worker--
that's usually pre-caching--
or later during the runtime
of our application.
Let's compare these two.
So pre-caching is very
similar to installing
a ready-made package
with your app.
It's great for caching
the critical content,
since we know it's most probably
going to be needed anyways.
It's relatively easy to
implement and to manage
and to update, because you can
just replace the whole package
with the new
version when needed,
and also because the
size of such package
is known beforehand.
On the other hand,
when using pre-caching,
you need to make a lot
of arbitrary decisions
about what your user is going
to need even before they start
interacting with the page, which
might lead to the situation
where you cache many more
resources than necessary.
Also, as we mentioned before,
it can cause network congestion
and compete with the
other network requests
from the window.
Runtime caching,
on the other hand,
is really great for
non-critical assets
because you can draw conclusions
from your user's behavior.
For example cache only
images they already
accessed, or cache
different parts of your app
depending on the
user's entry point.
On the other hand, the
problem with runtime
is that you need to be
really careful about updates
because assets might
end up in cache
at different moments in time.
For example, if resources
depend on each other,
like you have a script
that depends on the markup
and you end up caching
incompatible versions of them,
you run into trouble.
So you need to be very
careful about versioning.
Also, important thing
is that in this case,
the cache will grow over time.
The size is not
known beforehand.
So as the user
interacts with the app,
the size will be different.
Here's an example.
This is a very simple
e-commerce app I built recently.
If I cache pages in
this app at runtime
and the homepage
is fully cached,
it takes about 150 kilobytes
with all the images.
But later when the user
navigates to a new category,
like accessories page, it
gets added to the cache,
and the overall size
grows to 300 kilobytes.
And so on and so on.
As the user interacts with my
app, the overall size grows.
If the app is
really big it might
be really hard to predict
ahead of time how much space it
will take on users' device.
This is why it's so important
to control the size of your app
through the runtime.
Phil, can we do it
programmatically somehow?
PHIL WALTON: You can.
If you ever need to check your
app's current storage usage,
you can use the Storage
Manager API which
has an estimate method that
returns, both the total quota
as well as the current
amount that's being used.
EWA GASPEROWICZ:
Well, it's really
cool that we can
estimate that, because it
allows us to proactively
control the app size
and prevent quota overflow.
Quota is limited and depends
both on users' device
and also on the amount of
currently available space
on the device.
So you can't just throw
assets into the cache
and assume it will
never fill up.
You always need to have
a plan on how to remove
old or unnecessary assets.
After all, you don't
want a situation
where you can't update
some critical script
because your cache is
full of cat videos.
Here are some
things that can help
you to stay below the quota.
As we mentioned
before, you can store
partials of your pages
instead of full HTML
to avoid duplication
and save some space.
You can also separate your
critical and non-critical
assets into different
caches with different names,
so that you can evict the
non-critical ones when needed
without touching the rest.
Finally, you can also
cache some resources
only if there is plenty of
space, like conditionally.
Or you can put size or maximum
number of entries constraints
on your cache.
I think this is something
Workbox can help us with.
PHIL WALTON: Yeah.
With Workbox you can
easily manage the rules
for how and when cache entries
should expire with the Cache
Expiration plugin.
And you can use it with any
of the Workbox strategies.
So you configure both a max
number of entries per cache
or a max age for each entry.
You can also
configure the plugin
to automatically purge
all entries if there
is any kind of quota
error or anything
like that, which is
usually a good thing
to do when you have a
non-critical asset cache.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: OK, now a few
words about updating the cache.
The simplest solution is what
I call the nuke approach, which
means you clear all your caches
and start fresh every time
your service worker updates.
It's very easy to
implement, but it's not
very efficient nor kind
to your user's data plans.
So you should be more granular
about what you update and when.
And if you want to
be more granular,
you need to properly
tag your assets
so that you know which ones
are compatible with each other.
You can use the
content-based hashes
in the file name of
the given resource,
or provide revision
data on each asset
so that you can manage it
in Service Worker later on.
This process can be very
error-prone when done manually,
so fortunately we have tools
to help with that as well.
PHIL WALTON: Yeah, with the
Workbox pre-caching package,
you don't have to
manually manage the update
process yourself at all.
It has an asset manifest
that maps file URLs
to their revision
hashes, and that
allows it to remove
old assets and fetch
new ones without having to touch
any of the unchanged assets.
It makes the upgrade
process really efficient.
Workbox also has both Gulp and
Webpack plugins, as well as
a CLI, so you can
easily generate
this asset manifest yourself.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: As you can see,
Workbox makes a lot of things
easier for us as
developers so that we
can focus on what matters
most, and that's the user.
And users can really vary.
They can be of
different background,
they can use our app
at home or on the go,
they can use more or
less advanced devices
or have different access
to data and connectivity.
There are some things
we can do to accommodate
those differences.
First of all, when
working on performance,
never assume the
environment you work in
is representative of
your whole user base.
For example, you should
always throttle your network
to 3G speed when testing to
get a more realistic feel
for your performance.
Secondly, keep in mind
those underpowered devices
with little storage and really
control the size of your app.
Remember that the
overall size of your app
might grow over time if
you use runtime caching,
and plan accordingly.
Also, sometimes
there are actually
explicit hints from
the user that you can
use in your decision making.
For example, you can refrain
from speculatively pre-caching
future resources if the Data
Saver mode is turned on.
When user enables this
feature in Chrome,
the save data header is
being sent with each request.
So you can detect
it and, for example,
refrain from
aggressive pre-caching
a lot of future assets.
Similarly, you can use the
Network Information API
effective type method to
differentiate your strategy
based on the current network
condition of the user.
Finally, you can also
consider scenarios
where you give the user the full
control over the experience.
For example, you provide
save for later button, where
a user can explicitly opt in and
decide to get something stored
for future use.
Putting the user
first can really
benefit the quality of
your app, especially
in the long term
development horizon.
PHIL WALTON: So
to wrap up, I know
we've presented a
lot of content today,
and we don't expect you
to remember everything.
If you want to learn more about
Service Worker best practices,
we've launched a new
section on web.dev
with content dedicated to
building fast and resilient web
applications with
Service Worker.
So definitely check that out.
Also, we've just released
a V4 beta of Workbox
with lots of cool new
features, and we'd
love your feedback on GitHub
before the public release.
And finally, just
a few key points
we want to leave you with.
First, definitely have a plan.
You can't just assume that
adding Service Worker to a site
will magically make it faster,
because without an optimization
plan it probably won't.
Second, don't just
reinvent the HTTP cache
inside of your service
worker, and don't just
cache static resources.
If that's all you're
doing, you're not actually
optimizing your site
for Service Worker
and you might even
be making it slower.
Third, remember that
navigation requests are
the most important
requests to optimize,
and you should always try to
respond to them from the cache.
Fourth, measure the
real user performance
of your implementations and make
future performance decisions
based on data.
Don't just guess.
Fifth, control the
size of your app
and how much you store
on the user's device.
And last but definitely not
least, respect the user,
respect their data, and
respect their preferences.
Thank you.
If you have any questions,
feel free to find either of us
afterwards, or hit us up on
Twitter and ask questions.
That's it, yeah.
EWA GASPEROWICZ: Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]