[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: And as we
evolve our metrics story,
we want to fill in as many
gaps of our measurement of user
experience as we can.
There are a few major shifts
here that I'd like to call out.
The first one is
the reduced emphasis
on first meaningful
paint and first CPU idle.
We're excited to have
metrics available that better
capture when a page feels
usable, which leads me
to the second major call-out,
which is the new metrics you
see added.
So largest contentful
paint, total blocking time,
and cumulative layout shift
are all out and available.
These new metrics
help to fill some
of the gaps in our
measurement story.
For instance, when
time to interactive
does a good job of identifying
when the main thread calms down
later in load,
total blocking time
aims to quantify how
strained the main thread is
throughout the load.
SPEAKER 2: Pretty much
all the lab metrics
are available in Lighthouse.
First input delay only really
makes sense in the field.
So then, when it comes
to field metrics,
you can see most of them are
available in Chrome UX Support.
Other than you can
collect yourself
with the Performance Observer.
And you can check out, actually,
the documentation for all this
in web.dev/metrics.
SPEAKER 1: Thank
goodness, gone are
the days where you're having to
toggle and compare between two
Lighthouse reports side-by-side
trying to find the differences,
and you're actually able
to see the diff view.
Now, you can see the changes
between the two reports
in a single view.
So we are launching the 0.3
alpha of Lighthouse CI today,
and you can check it out
in the repo and set it up.
Please let us know
what you think of it.
It is early stages, and we
definitely want your feedback.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 3: A user's hardware
and their network type
can massively impact the
experience that they're
going to have with your site.
Now, there are three
or four key signals
we'll be looking at for
adaptive loading today.
First of all, we've got
network for fine-tuning things
like data transfer to
use less bandwidth.
We've got memory for
reducing the amount of memory
consumption on
low-end devices, CPU,
for limiting costly
Javascript execution,
and reducing
CPU-intensive logic.
To make all of this
easier, today, we're
releasing a new experimental
set of React hooks
for adaptive loading that
you can go and check out.
Adaptive module serving is
something I'm excited about.
And this is this idea
of shipping a light,
interactive core experience
to all of your users
and progressively adding
high-end features on top--
so if a user's device
characteristics and network
can handle it.
Now, it's this
device awareness that
takes progressive
enhancement to the next step.
SPEAKER 4: Well, we have
navigator.hardwareConcurrency,
which tells us generally
how many CPU cores.
And many browsers also give
us navigator.deviceMemory,
which tells us how much RAM.
So maybe, on desktop, there's a
way we can use these two fields
and figure out some
generalized buckets that we
can apply consistently
across different devices
and different metrics.
Once we have this core--
this core metrics-- and we're
able to break it up and have
a consistent way and
understanding of what
different types of hardware,
we can actually consider
this in our core frameworks.
SPEAKER 5: We're in close
contact with the Angular team
and really excited for their
achievements on both UX and DX.
In particular, they shared
differential loading,
which reduces polyfill
in modern browsers,
and they have
automatic deployments
to different platforms, to
name a couple of things.
Also, Dion mentioned
in the keynote
that we have funded
a number of projects
with the Framework Fund.
We'll have funding
again next year.
So if you are playing a role
in the framework ecosystem,
providing something of value,
please apply for funding.
At Google I/O, I mentioned
that we kicked off
an effort in the space directly
collaborating with NextJS.
In particular, we are starting
with performance improvements
first, both because this is
an important problem needing
attention, but also, it wasn't
overlapping with other efforts.
SPEAKER 6: Sum Up,
another major NextJS site
that we tested our
chunking strategy on,
saw a reduction of their largest
JavaScript bundle by 64%.
And again, the amazing
thing about these changes
is that it involved no actual
change to the user's code
whatsoever.
This is all by
just turning a flag
on that changed the chunking
strategy to use our newer,
granular approach.
Today, we're excited to
introduce a new Babel
preset that optimizes
specifically for this case.
It's called Babel
Preset Modules,
and it's available
on npm right now.
But running the same code
through preset-modules
produces this.
It's a lot smaller.
Here's the thing-- both outputs
run in all browsers that
support script-type modules.
SPEAKER 7: So these sort of
things that we're currently
working on to help you with
building more scalable web
applications.
So one of them is translations.
Then there's unit testing.
So unit testing,
integration testing,
is a really broad topic.
Also, there's image handling.
So images that make up a
large percentage of what
you show on the website, right?
But we don't provide an
opinionated way to load images,
currently.
So that means that it's
really easy to include
images that are too large.
There is analytics.
And analytics is something
that you all probably use
in a website, at
least, because you
want to know what your
users are doing on a page.
However, to correctly
implement and relay
analytics in single-page
applications is really hard.
There's error reporting.
You probably all have
written bugs before,
and it's really hard to catch
bugs in production in websites
because it runs on a browser
that is not your own browser,
and because of that, you can't
see what users are doing.
So error reporting is very
important in that way.
So relaying errors
that happen it's
going to be easier
very soon, too.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 8: Let's walk through,
step-by-step, what Portals
could do.
Let's say you have a page,
say foo.html, all blue.
Super nice with this
foo blue background,
and having foo.html
in the center.
And you also have
another page, bar.html,
which is pretty
similar to foo.html,
but having a different
color and a different URL.
We'll use these two pages to
see what Portals could do.
You would first want to check if
your browser supports Portals.
As you all know,
progressive enhancement
is very important,
because we don't
want to break any experience
in non-supportied browsers.
You could check
if the HTML Portal
element is in the global
window object to achieve this.
Next, let's create
a Portal element
by document.createElement,
setting the source attribute
as bar.html, and adding
some styles of our own,
and lastly, adding the
element to the document.
And boom, you'll see bar.html
embedded in the page.
So as you can see,
Portals really
makes the loading
experience disappear.
You don't need to
wait for the page
to render anymore
because it's already
rendered inside the portal.
Like I mentioned, Portals has
nothing to do with animation,
but you can always
animate the Portal
to make the transition smooth.
It could be using keyframes
or JavaScript to move around
the element, but in
this case, let's say
we animated the element
with CSS transitions.
SPEAKER 9: All right to close,
we've talked about four APIs
today.
The first one, Portal,
which is designed
to enable instant and
seamless navigation.
Periodic Backgroud
Sync, this is designed
to get content ahead
of time on the device
so that you don't have to
worry about connection.
Content Indexing-- this
one is about surfacing
the content that's
available on the device,
and it's going to be available
in Origin trials soon.
And last but not least,
Web Bundles-- so this
is a convenient format to enable
discovery and distribution.
[MUSIC PLAYING]