[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: I think that's on.
Google have asked me if I'll do
a behind-the-scenes of Chrome
Dev Summit.
And they've sent me this bag.
I guess it's some
kind of camera.
Oh yes.
Let's go to Chrome Dev Summit.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 2: Hello, I'm Timothy
Jordan for The Developer Show
here at the Chrome Dev
Summit at the Yerba Buena
Center of the Arts.
SPEAKER 1: Timothy Jordan.
SPEAKER 2: Hey, Paul.
SPEAKER 1: Hey.
SPEAKER 2: How are you doing?
SPEAKER 1: I'm good.
I'm doing a behind-the-scenes
video for Chrome.
SPEAKER 2: I'm doing a top five
recap video for the Chrome Dev
Summit.
Notice the camera.
SPEAKER 1: Awkward.
I'm running late.
I'm supposed to be on stage.
Do you know where the
stage actually is here?
SPEAKER 2: No, Paul, I do not.
SPEAKER 1: Go in.
[CHEERING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]