[MUSIC PLAYING]
JASON CHASE: Good
morning, everyone.
So I lead a Chrome
team whose mission
is to help developers better
understand and control
the web platform.
So we've been working
on feature policy
and reporting API,
which we think
can really make your lives
easier as web developers.
Maybe it won't save you
from speeding tickets,
like Nicole said, but
we'll see what we can do.
So we know there's many
benefits to being on the web.
But as a development platform,
it's far from perfect.
On the Chrome team,
we regularly provide
web consults to help people
address issues with their site.
Now, these consults bring
together developer relations,
engineering, and other
folks to help people
deep dive into questions
or issues with their site.
Now, the goal is to provide
actual recommendations
to improve things.
Now, as a result, we've
identified common mistakes that
happen over and over again.
And-- spoiler
alert-- performance
is a common theme here.
And the two big
performance problems we see
are too much script and
too many image bytes
being sent over the network.
So you know there's a
right way to do things.
But it's an adventure
to find that sometimes.
And even if you find the
right way, there's bumps.
Or you might slip off the path.
So as we've seen in
other talks, there's
a long list of things to
keep track of and get right.
Now, this is hard enough if
you're an expert developer.
But imagine you have a dev
team with junior developers
and you need to keep
everyone on the same page.
So we need help.
What if we could make
web development easier
with guardrails?
So if you imagine
guardrails along a path--
if you hit a rail, you know
you're doing something wrong.
And the rails stop you
from leaving the path.
Now, this isn't
necessarily a new idea.
But looking at repeated
mistakes in our web consults,
we're thinking about
different ways to apply this.
Concretely, how could we help
you put guardrails in place
for development?
So AMP gives us examples--
an example of guardrails
and web development.
AMP gives guarantees you're
not going to veer off course
by making it nearly
impossible to do things wrong.
Now, AMP started by providing
building blocks, tightly
constrained, to ensure
great performance in UX.
So this is an
[INAUDIBLE] approach
to carve off good parts
of the web platform.
Now, not everyone can
or wants to use AMP.
So learning from AMP, we thought
about a more configurable
approach.
And that's Feature Policy.
So we're really
excited about it.
We think it's going
to be a great tool
to help guide you
towards the well-lit path
to web development.
Now, with Feature Policy
you opt into a set
of policies for the browser to
enforce throughout your site.
These policies restrict which
features the site can access--
or modify the browser's default
behavior for certain features.
So let's talk through some of
the common problems we've seen.
So images often have
extra quality or metadata
that take up space
but isn't required.
Now, as we've seen
in other talks,
again, there's many
tools to optimize images.
But you have to
remember to use them.
Or you have to integrate them
into your build pipeline.
Now ideally, your
page should never
serve images that are larger
than the version that's
rendered on-screen.
Anything larger just
results in wasted bytes
and slows down page load time.
So a common example might be
sending a desktop-size hero
image to a mobile device.
We've designed policies
to catch common mistakes
of un-optimized or
oversized images.
So we researched
the impact that we
think these policies
can have on 10,000
of the most popular sites.
Our analysis shows
that 10% of sites
can save over 500
kilobytes on average.
Now, that can reduce load time
by up to 10 seconds on a 3G
network.
So let's take a quick look.
So this shows the policies
being applied to a site.
Now on the left, policy
for un-optimized images
is turned off.
And you can see, the
images load at normal.
On the right, we've
turned on the policy.
And it's blocked
one of the images.
So we compute a compression
ratio of bytes to pixels.
And if that ratio
is greater than 0.5,
it will block the image and
will show a placeholder.
So the idea is to point
out the images that
need to be corrected.
So this site might
look familiar.
At Google, we're big
believers in dog-fooding.
So we went and applied all the
policies we could to the site.
Lo and behold, we found
out we made a few mistakes.
So we applied a
bunch of policies.
But it was actually the
oversized images policy
that caught that we were sending
some images that were too big.
So oops!
It just shows that
even the experts,
like our developer relations
team, can make mistakes.
So we really need
better tooling to help
catch these kind of things.
So another common problem is
images without explicit sizes.
Now, as we see on the left, this
can cause your user experience
to jump around as
the browser loads
the new images and
resizes the page.
Now, on the right, we've
applied a policy to catch this.
So the browser can set these
images to a fixed size.
And it'll keep your
user experience stable.
So how does this all work?
Policies, like I said
before, are a contract
between developer and browser.
We use them to
inform the browser
about our intent for our site.
It's a set of rules for how
each page should behave.
Now, the browser
helps keep us honest
when our page tries
to veer off the path,
by validating that it's behaving
according to its stated rules.
So if a page or embedded
third-party content
attempts to violate
any of the rules,
the browser will identify
or block the behavior.
And in some cases, it
may override the behavior
to write a better
user experience.
All right, let's take a look
at how you configure policies.
Now, each policy refers
to a single feature.
And then it defines a
list of origins that
are allowed to use the feature.
Now, with each
page response, you
can add this Feature
Policy HTTP header.
So in this example
here, this will
catch all oversized images.
And this is the one that saved
our bacon on the CDS site.
Now here, the
"none" keyword means
that no origin is allowed
to use the feature
of oversized images, disabling
it entirely for your site.
Now, looking at
that example, you
might wonder why we would say,
oversized images are a feature.
Now, we have
policies for helping
you enforce best practices,
to ensure good performance
and user experience.
And the way these
often work is, we'll
define a known bad
practice as a feature.
And then you use the
policy to prevent it.
Now, we do this for
web-compatible reasons.
We don't want to go ahead
and break the internet
by all the sudden turning off
oversized images for everyone.
So we'll allow that
behavior by default.
And then you opt
in to turn it off.
Now, this header
applies a policy
that catches any images
that are not optimized.
Now here, we're making
an explicit exception
for our photo CDN.
Now in this case, it might be
because our users expect really
high-detailed glossy pictures.
And those don't compress well.
Now, in this case, there's
only one origin listed.
And all origins
will not be allowed.
So here's an example that
puts them all together.
So first, we have a policy
that ensures every image has
explicit dimensions.
So we saw this earlier,
preventing your user experience
from jumping around.
Now second, we have a
policy to selectively enable
the geolocation feature.
So now, we're applying
this to our own origin
and to our trusted
maps provider.
The "self" keyword
here means the origin
of the top-level page.
So by combining this
with explicit origins,
you have full control over who
is allowed to use a feature.
And then finally, we're allowing
any origin to use autoplay.
And here, you see an
asterisks keyword.
That means essentially everyone.
So by default, Chrome
will only allow autoplay
on same-origin iframes.
With this policy, we can
allow cross-origin iframes
to play as well.
So in that last
example, we saw features
in the more traditional sense--
well-known APIs that
are exposed to the web,
like geolocation, camera,
full-screen, autoplay.
So before, we saw policies
about enforcing best practices.
So now, we have policies that
give you granular control
over the features you use.
So we've probably all
seen this example.
You go to a site.
And before you interact
with the site at all,
you get a pop-up to use
location or microphone
or something like that.
So with Feature
Policy, you can lock
this down to either prevent
the use of the feature at all
or really just dole it out to
specific origins you trust.
So we've talked through some
examples of an HTTP header.
You can also use
an Allow attribute
to control Feature
Policy on iframes.
So now, why might
you want to do this?
Well, as we talked about,
you can be really selective.
So maybe you have one frame
on your site that shows a map.
You could use the
Allow attribute
to grant the geolocation
usage to that frame
and on no other frames.
Now, in the example we see
here, this Allow attribute
is changing the default
for the AutoPlay feature.
Well, you'll notice,
if you go to generate
and embed on YouTube,
they're already
using this in production today.
So we've seen a
lot of flexibility
in how you can configure
Feature Policy.
So we built in some rules
to make sure they're
being applied correctly.
So Malte in the keynote
talked rather enthusiastically
about not using sync-xhr HR.
And yes, we do have
a policy for that.
And AMP is using
that in production.
So the way the rules apply is,
first, policies are inherited.
So scripts will
inherit the policy
of their containing frame.
So this means that, for
your top-level scripts,
they'll inherit the policies
of the main document.
So this means you can apply
the policies at the top.
And they cascade down to
all nested sub-frames.
So in AMP's case, they
can set the policy
to disable sync-xhr
and know that it
will be applied
to all sub-frames,
regardless of how far
they might be nested.
And this applies to
the iframe attribute--
Allow attribute as well.
So if you have an
Allow attribute
and you have a header, the
stricter of the two policies
wins.
Now, on the other hand, we
have this one-way toggle.
So disabling a feature
turns it off permanently.
So that means,
again, in AMP's case,
they've turned off the feature
with the sync-xhr policy.
And that means no frame,
nested or otherwise,
can turn it back on.
Now, for policy
supporting best practices,
it might not be
feasible for the browser
to actually block the bad
practice before it appears.
It can only detect the
problem, in some cases,
and then break your page in
an obvious way or notify you.
The goal, in that
case, is really
to let you know there's
a problem to fix.
Now, we saw this in the
policy for un-optimized images
and oversized images.
Now, in other cases,
the browser can actually
block the bad practice, so your
site continues to behave well.
The policy front-sized
media works this way.
So it will apply
fixed-size to images
to prevent the user experience
from jumping around.
So we have dev
tools in Lighthouse
to give you great insight into
the behavior of your site.
So where does Feature Policy fit
into your development workflow?
Feature Policy lets you set
the policies up-front and then
catch problems early
during development,
before anyone writes
a lot of code.
Now, you can build
policies that defaults
for new sites or new pages.
And this way, you can enforce
standards across your dev team.
Policies are served with each
page and validated at runtime.
So you can choose to turn
them on for some users and not
others.
You can also turn them on
for some pages in your site
and not others, as
you incrementally
improve your site, for example.
So at a minimum we recommend
enabling the policies
on your staging server.
This can let you catch
problems that you
didn't see during development.
For example, you might have
your images come from a content
management system.
And they're not available as
you're developing the site.
So this can catch
problems with that.
In addition to
staging, you can also
apply policies in production.
You can have your dev
team, your managers--
all the way up to your CEO--
use your site with policies
enabled, so that you can
find real issues in the wild.
For regular production
users, you likely
won't enable the
policies if violations
will break the user experience.
So for example, with
the image policies,
loading un-optimized
images more slowly
is probably a better
experience than having
them missing altogether.
You still want to know
about all these violations,
so you can correct them.
So we've designed
report-only mode
to give you the
best of both worlds.
So you can configure policies
similar to the examples
we saw before.
But you mark them
as report-only.
So you see here,
internal users--
they have the policies enabled.
We'll break things.
We'll see problems with images
that need to get corrected.
For production users, we have
them in report-only mode.
So the production users
get the normal experience.
But then you can get reports
about what's gone wrong.
So speaking of reporting,
Feature Policy violations
are really just the start.
There's lots of other
info from the wild
that'll be really valuable--
for example, browser
interventions.
Sometimes, a browser
needs to intervene
to improve the experience
for the end-user.
So an example of
such a intervention
is blocking document.write,
unlike 2G connections.
So there, we've discovered
that doing a document.write
on a really slow
connection can really
impair the user experience.
So to protect that,
we've just blocked it.
But that happens in the wild.
You don't know about it.
You really want to
find out about it,
so you can correct it.
Now, what else?
So just taking a
look at this, there's
lots of things going on
in the wild on your site
that you'd really
love to know about.
Not a problem-- some of these
are just console messages,
which you can't collect.
Now, there's other things
that have a bespoke API,
like window.onerror.
So you have to remember
to go hook up something
there to get some errors.
And then there's things like
crashes and network errors
that just aren't possible
to capture from script.
So a solution here
is reporting API.
This gives you one place
to collect all sorts
of information from the wild.
It's a one-stop shop.
It exposes information that
wasn't available before.
We've talked about
network errors, crashes--
now, that's coming soon--
Feature Policy violations.
Deprecations, interventions,
and network errors--
you can get those today
with reporting API.
There's two ways
to use reporting.
We have the reporting
observer, which
lets you collect reports
client-side, with a JS API.
Now, you can filter
by report type.
Here, we've said, we just
care about deprecations
and Feature Policy violations.
And then you can use a callback
to funnel these reports
to your own analytics
provider or however you'd
like to capture them.
Now, because it's client-side,
the available types
are limited.
But the key feature here
is it buffers results.
So you can set up your reporting
observer later and still get
reports that happened
earlier in page load.
So every report has
some common fields.
So we can see here the type
of the report and the URL,
where the report happened.
And then, for each report
type, there's a specific body.
Now, for Feature
Policy violations,
we see it's telling you the
feature that you were using.
And it tells you where in your
code the violation occurred.
Now, the second way
to use reporting
is with the
report-to-response header.
So this lets you configure
out-of-band delivery reports.
The browser will queue
up reports and send them
to the location
of your choosing,
separate from the
execution of your page.
And so here, you can get
all of the report types
that we saw earlier.
So you'll see a
couple fields here.
So first, there's Group.
And that just lets you name this
particular set of end points.
And then you can refer
to that group name
in other parts of
your configuration.
Now, max_age says how long this
configuration is valid for.
After that, we'll throw
away this configuration.
So this lets you know
change endpoints over time
and gradually
switch to new ones.
And finally, endpoints
is an array of URLs.
So you can configure
multiple URLs for fallback.
So if the browser can't
reach one endpoint,
it'll try another.
And so talking about one
place to configure reporting--
CSP, Content
Security Policy, now
integrates with
the reporting API.
So whereas before, you'd
specify a report URI
and you'd give it
an URL to where
you wanted your reports to go--
now, you can use the
report-to directive.
And you just point it at one of
the endpoints you'd previously
configured.
So if we go back to
the preview example,
you'd send a report-to header.
And you'd define a group
called CSP endpoint.
You can have all the URLs
you need there, the age.
And then you just
refer back to it here.
So where can you use this stuff?
So both the Feature Policy
framework and the reporting API
are shipped in Chrome.
Firefox is implementing
Feature Policy.
And Safari has support for
the iframe Allow attribute.
Now, what's really
great is you can
benefit from using
these policies now,
even though there isn't broad
support across browsers.
If you do some of your
local testing in Chrome
with flags enabled, you can
apply all these policies
and catch problems before
they reach other environments.
So I've talked a lot
about a few policies,
walked through the
examples, explaining
why you might want to use them.
But that's really
just the start.
So here's a list of all the
ones we have available today.
Most of the ones around
granular control-- like,
turning on and off
features, like, geolocation,
microphone-- those
kind of things--
those are already shipped.
So you can use those now.
And we saw that with the
YouTube example and with AMP.
And a lot of the best
practice policies-- those
are behind a flag.
And we're also working
on a bunch more.
Now, seeing that long
list, you go, man,
how am I going to
set up policies?
How am I going to
try them all out?
Well, we have a handy
dev tools extension.
So this lets you really easily
toggle a policy on and off
and see the effect
on your page, so you
don't have to configure
the set-up headers
or modify your code
to allow attributes.
You can just try it
and see what'll happen.
So here, we've seen an
example of using the extension
to turn off the
geolocation feature.
Now, this extension
uses a JavaScript API.
So the advantage there
is, you can feature
detect which policies
are even supported.
And you can go one step further.
And you can query to
see which policies
are enabled or disabled.
So this can allow you
to code defensively.
So for example, if you have
content that's embedded,
you can respond differently
if you know the features that
are available to you.
So we really love to hear
if these policies are
useful for you.
The ones we're really interested
in are somewhere around some
of the images,
and even sync-xhr.
So we've made it easy for you
to, hopefully, copy and paste
and get a header
sent real quick.
Now, if you have
ideas for new policies
or if you have feedback
on the existing ones,
we'd love to hear from
you on our GitHub repo.
And finally, you can head
over to FeaturePolicy.rocks.
And you'll get more information
about Feature Policy,
about code samples,
and live demos.
Thanks a lot.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]