[MUSIC PLAYING]
SURMA: Hello, everybody.
Yes, it's me again.
Prepare for more bugs.
I'm kind of excited to be here
because we finally reached
a point where, with Houdini,
I can talk about actual APIs.
Because they're starting
to land, and that's
kind of really exciting.
But as with any talk, I have
to start with what Houdini is.
Because on my Twitter, I often
see there's still confusion.
Because it turns out there's
a software called Houdini.
There is apparently a magician
that was called Houdini.
So I want to clear up what
Houdini really is about.
So every browser has more
or less four major stages
in the rendering pipeline.
It starts with styles, where the
browser collects all the style
sheets that are in the
document and then figures
out which element is affected
by which of these styles.
And now that we know
the width, the height,
and if it's Flexbox or Grid,
which style is on which
element, we can do layout.
We can basically calculate
how big an element is
and align them on the page
and get boxes on the page.
They are still empty
and transparent
because in the next stage
we can take that layout page
and paint it, just draw it.
And we can draw it
all on the page.
Sometimes elements get on
their own piece of paper,
which is called a layer.
And once we are done
painting, respecting
things like background color and
the text color and the border
color, we can give all of
that, all this pieces of paper
to the compositor and put
them together in the page
that you will see
on your screen.
And if something was
on its own layer,
we can move the pieces
of paper around.
And that's how
animations are made.
It's obviously
kind of a shortcut
but you can see where
I'm coming from.
So bringing it back
to the question,
what really is Houdini?
Well, Houdini is a standards
effort in the CSS working
group in the W3C to expose
hooks into these major stages
of the layout phase to
the developer, to you.
So you have more control
not only over the visuals
but to write better
polyfills and have
more control over how your
page just appears to the user.
It is hard because
these four stages
are different in every browser.
Sometimes they're even
parallel or not even
that clearly separated.
But we're working
with all the browsers
to make sure everybody
can implement these APIs.
Houdini can be super
intimidating at first.
Because under the
Houdini umbrella,
there's a lot of APIs.
And you don't really immediately
know what to do with what.
But they actually kind
of form a hierarchy.
So you have four high-level
APIs, four major APIs
that basically represent
those four major stages
of the rendering pipeline.
And then you have a couple
of lower-level APIs that
build the underpinning,
the basis for Houdini
and that make these
higher-level APIs
possible in the first place.
And specifically, worklets
are really interesting.
Worklets are kind of
the Swiss Army knife
within Houdini for performance.
And so I want to make
sure I take a second
to explain these because
we're going to use them
for the rest of the talk.
And more importantly, I want to
distinguish them from workers.
Because lots of people
confuse these two,
and I can't blame them because
they sound very similar.
And in fact, they actually
have a lot of overlap.
But there is a couple of
very important differences
that I want explain to you.
And for that, we have to
talk about the event loop.
This is an event loop.
And if you don't know
much about the event loop,
that's absolutely fine.
Everything that
you need to know,
I will explain to you today.
But if you want to
know more, I really
recommend watching Jake's talk
about the event loop, which
you can probably find on
YouTube if you just type
in his name and event loop.
And actually, I'm using a lot
of his visuals in this talk.
So this is an event loop.
It's a loop, and it
processes events.
And it's called an event loop.
Whenever an event happens,
the JavaScript engine
checks if there's a handler for
this event in your code base
and then takes the code for
that handler and queues it up.
And every turn, the event
loop takes something out
of the queue and runs it.
And then, in the next turn,
it takes the next thing out
of the queue and runs it.
And that's obviously
super simplified,
and there's much more
nuance to this entire thing.
But that's kind of how
an event loop works.
And in this world, a worker
would look like this.
It's a completely
separate event loop.
It's an isolated scope.
It has its own handlers,
its own events.
And they have nothing
to do with each other.
They might be able to put a
task into the other loop's
queue with postMessage,
but that's pretty much it.
And there is considerable cost
to spinning up and maintaining
an event loop, and
that's why you can't just
spin up 1,000 workers
and call it a day.
Because that's
actually quite costly.
Worklets are different.
They're also isolated JavaScript
code with their own scope.
But worklets don't
have an event loop.
Instead, they kind of attach to
already existing event loops.
And that makes them a lot
cheaper to create and maintain.
You can even attach
multiple worklets
to an already
existing event loop.
And because most worklets are
specified to be stateless,
we can even migrate them in
the middle of their lifetime.
So if it makes more
sense for your code
to run in sync with
another event loop,
we can just [POP] take it off
and take it to the next event
loop where it makes more sense.
So this will come in
really handy later on,
but that's basically the big
difference between those two.
And now that we have
worklets in our back pocket,
we can finally talk about
the very first Houdini API,
which is for the paint worklet.
So as I said--
I'm not going to go through
these in order, by the way,
more like in order
of [? availability ?]
if that makes sense.
But for the paint
worklets, the API
is called the CSS Paint API.
And as I said, all elements have
to be painted sooner or later
to be able to appear onscreen.
And so far, you have
been able to use
CSS to customize how
your elements appear
onscreen but only with
those ways that CSS exposes.
So for example, if you
want to do rounded corners,
you can reduce border radius.
And you get this, and
it's kind of great.
But it also turns
out that there's
different ways to
make a box seem
like it has rounded corners.
And if you want to use
any of these other ways,
you're kind of screwed nowadays.
Because what do you do?
So for example, there is a
so-called squircle, which
mathematically
speaking, is closer
to a circle than a square.
And it doesn't change
curvature abruptly at all.
So it has a kind of
different aesthetic look,
which could be kind of nice.
So if you wanted to have
this thing on the web today,
what do you do?
You can maybe do an
SVG background image,
which is not really a border.
You could maybe use a
canvas or a 9-slice image--
I don't know.
But with Houdini,
you can actually
teach CSS how to draw
the exact look that you
want to have on your page.
So how does this work?
Step one with all
worklets is that you
have to load a JavaScript
file into the worklet
that the browser gives to you.
So in this case, we
have the CSS namespace,
and all the worklets that
Houdini brings to the browser
are going to be in this CSS
namespace sooner or later.
So in this case, it's
called Paint Worklet.
And every worklet
has an addModule call
with which you can
load a JavaScript
file into that worklet.
Let's take a look
inside this file.
In that file, we
want to teach CSS
how to paint something
new with JavaScript.
But first, it needs a name.
So there is a registerPaint
function, and it takes a class.
And now, we want to
basically associate
a name with that class.
And every paint class--
in this case, I'm
using my-paint--
we need to define a paint call.
And this paint call
gets a context,
which is almost identical
to the canvas contact
that you're hopefully
familiar with;
a geometry object, which tells
you how much width and height
the element has that
you're supposed to paint;
and a properties
object, which allows
you to read the
styles of the object
that you are painting-- so like,
background color, text color,
font size.
All these things are in
there for you to read.
And now, what I'm
doing here is basically
I'm setting my fill
style to hotpink.
And just draw the
biggest possible circle
in the middle of the element--
not very useful, but in the
way useful for me to show you
what is actually going on.
So now that we have defined
how to draw this appearance,
how do we tell the
browser to actually use
this new appearance?
So we do that in CSS.
So in this case, I'm
just adding a new style.
And you can use paint
worklets everywhere
that CSS expects an image.
So in this case, I'm setting the
background image not to a URL
but to a paint and
use the name that I
used in registerPaint in here.
So here, I use paint(my-paint).
And this is actually--
if it works?
No?
This is not good.
Told you, prepare for more bugs.
No, the entire laptop froze.
[LAUGHTER]
No!
OK, maybe it's
coming back to life.
I'm going to try something.
[LAUGHTER]
I achieved something today.
All right, as I was
saying, we load the file.
We had that.
We had this one.
We draw a circle in
the middle, and I
want to do the big reveal
where we use the paint
function for the
background image
instead of just a
normal SVG image.
I'm going to press the button.
[APPLAUSE]
We have a pink circle.
I'm so happy.
By the way, everyone,
thank you so much
for the kind messages on
Twitter and your support here
in the room.
It could have been
so much worse.
Thank you very much.
All right, what I'm
doing here is, as I said,
I set the background
image on a text area.
So this is a text area where
I'm animating width and height.
Don't do this at home, kids.
Never animate width and height.
But you can see the circle
is pink and in the middle.
So you might be asking, what
is the advantage of using
Houdini's Paint API--
what this talk is about--
over using a normal canvas?
So there's a couple of
things I want to talk about.
The first one is
auto-repaint, meaning
that the browser can
figure out when it actually
needs to run your code to do
these painting operations.
I'm going to talk a bit
about this more a little bit
later in the talk.
It is auto-sized.
If you've ever worked
with the HTML canvas,
you know that the number
of pixels on an HTML canvas
is completely independent
from the number of pixels
a canvas has on
the screen, which
is super painful to work with.
And in this case, you
don't have to worry
about it because
it is automatically
set to the correct size.
It is off main thread,
meaning the code
that you write to do the
paint operation doesn't
run on the main thread.
And that's a lie.
Currently in Chrome, we do
run it on the main thread.
But as I said, the
worklets can be migrated.
So the second we have the
infrastructure in place
to run this kind of
code somewhere else,
it will just happen.
And that means you don't use
any of your main thread budget
making sure your page
is buttery smooth.
No DOM overhead-- and this one
is actually very underrated.
Often, I see effects
on the web that
use a couple of DOM elements
or any kind of assembly
of different styles to achieve
a certain visual effect.
With this, you're just
using a virtual canvas,
so not even one DOM element
to achieve this effect.
And that can really add
up on low-end phones.
So for example,
this is one of the--
no.
[LAUGHTER]
No!
Wait.
For me, this just means I'm
going to skip that slide.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go out of fullscreen,
and moving this to
a different slide,
going back into fullscreen.
And we're going
to go to this one.
All right.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
Wow.
All right, my point that I
was trying to make was that we
found that on low-end devices,
implementing these kind
of effects--
like this wonderful effect
that [? Una ?] implemented--
is actually more efficient
in the paint worklet
than using a million
DOM elements.
So that's why this is actually
a performance [? formative ?]
to make your app
run buttery smooth
even on the low-end devices.
So this is another effect
that [? Una ?] wrote
that I think is really nice.
And this is kind
of a nice example
to show how the browser can
decide when to paint and when
not to paint.
So in the paint class, you
can declare your dependencies.
You can say these are the CSS
properties that I rely on.
And so the browser
knows only when
any of these properties change
will the code have to run.
Otherwise, it won't.
And so, in this case, you have
a couple of custom properties
saying, I want to have this
number of stars and this hue
and this different
sizes kind of thing.
And then in CSS, I just do a
keyframe animation on the hue,
and you end up with this effect.
And it's actually efficient in
the sense it doesn't run just
[INAUDIBLE] every frame
but only repaints when
the animation actually tells
you that it's necessary.
This is another
effect, a simple clock,
that many people might write
with SVG or with a canvas.
Some people would, again,
probably bend over backwards
and try to make this happen with
a DOM and just a couple of DOM
elements.
But if you look closely, you
can see that the hand actually
has a trail, and that
suddenly makes it a lot harder
to do with SVG or with the DOM.
And maybe canvas would
be more appropriate.
The nice thing here is that you
can have this module, a clock
CSS Houdini module,
and configure it
with just a couple
of custom properties.
So you can animate the
background color or the color
of the hands, the
thickness of the hands,
the thickness of the circle
at the end, or the length.
You can show or not show the
individual stops on the clock.
You could do all of
these things at once,
but it gets really
stressful to look at.
So I wouldn't do that.
But it's just a clock.
And once again, this trail
is just a CSS transition.
So the browser knows, while
the transition is going on,
I need to repaint
this every frame.
But the second the trail is
done, it stops repainting.
It's a really easy
performance win.
So far, we've been using CSS
Paint for background images.
And we have gotten
pretty far I think,
if you still remember what I was
talking about a couple of hours
ago it feels like.
But you can use it anywhere
where CSS expects an image.
So for example, you
could also use it
for a mask image
or a border image.
So in the land of
border image, you
could make this kind of organic
look, where the border looks
kind of hand-drawn.
And if you want
that kind of look,
CSS Paint makes it really
easy to achieve that effect.
This is probably
a very important
progressive enhancement.
You can detect support for
Paint Worklet in both JavaScript
and CSS.
One note about the at
syntax for @supports,
it detects support
for Paint Worklet,
not for one specific
Paint Worklet.
So even if the name-- like
in this case, something--
doesn't actually exist
as a Paint Worklet,
it will still get evaluated,
which is kind of handy.
For this talk, I
want to introduce
the 3PigStability
index, which is supposed
to be a little notion
of how stable an API is,
based on the story
of the three pigs
and the wolf who tries
to blow their house down.
So in this case, in
the CSS Paint API,
the spec is a [INAUDIBLE]
recommendation,
which is basically
W3C-speak for, it's stable.
It's shipped to
stable in Chrome.
Safari announced that they have
it in development right now.
And with that, I will
call it brick stability.
That at the bottom,
by the way, is
supposed to be a brick emoji.
But the brick emoji
just got standardized
in June of this year, so none
of the fonts have it yet.
But luckily, it still kind
of looks like a brick.
If you want to know
more about this API,
I'm going to shamelessly
self-plug the article that I
wrote, which you can find here.
If you have any questions,
hit me up any time.
And with that out
the way, we finally
have talked about the
first Houdini API.
I'm going to go
onto the next one
and see if the browser
will handle this.
I just realized I--
should I risk hiding
the URL above?
I will do it, good.
The next one-- compositing.
As I said, the
compositor main job
is to do animations with
the papers that move around.
So as such, the animation is
called the Animation Worklet
API.
So let's talk about that a bit.
If you currently think
about animations on the web,
you have three choices.
It's more like 2
and 1/2 choices.
You have CSS
transitions, which allow
you to transition a CSS
property from the current value
to a new value.
You have CSS
keyframe animations,
which are a declarative timeline
API, which is more powerful
and can do some kind of looping.
And you have Web
Animations API, which
is the imperative
version that allows
you to do nested timelines
and all sorts of things.
But the problem is that
it's really badly supported.
It's behind a flag in Safari.
Chrome has an implantation but
it's missing a lot of features.
Edge doesn't have it at all.
So it really isn't
usually a good choice.
But even if it was,
there are often
scenarios where what Web
Animations API offers
is not enough.
And this is where Animation
Worklet API would come in.
So what you see here is a normal
Web Animations API animation.
Usually Web Animations API is
thought about in the .animate
call.
This is the same thing, just
a little bit more elaborate.
It's also part of the API.
And a worklet animation is
actually very, very similar.
So for example, I would
just use a worklet animation
instead of an animation.
And because we are associating
this animation with a worklet,
we need to, once again,
provide a worklet name.
Other than that,
it stays the same.
So we have the keyframe effect
that we target an element with,
and we have two
keyframes that we
want to use within two seconds.
Then now we have an animation
worklet on this CSS namespace
and can call addModule.
And now, within our animation
file, we can use JavaScripts.
We have an animate
callback where
we get the current time and
the effect of the animation.
And now it's our job to set
the local time of the effect
depending on the current time.
If we do it like this, where
we don't think about it,
it's literally a pass through.
And it will behave just like
a normal web animation API.
But this is JavaScript,
so you can basically
implement arbitrarily
complex time mappings.
Now, what does
this actually mean?
I'm not going to go into
all the details of this API
but just going to give
you a little taste of it.
So if you want to
know more, I'm going
to shamelessly self-plug
another article I
wrote, which you can find here.
And again, read it,
and give me feedback.
I would very much welcome that.
But what do you use
Animation Worklet for?
So for example, I think a
year ago or two years ago,
Safari proposed the
spring timing function.
And it's implemented in Safari.
I don't think any other browser
has implemented it so far.
But what do you do if
you want to use it?
Or what do you do if you have
any other timing function that
doesn't exist and
you want to use it?
This is where Animation
Worklet would come in handy.
So in this case, we
can, for example,
write a bounce animator.
Because if you think about
it, if you animate an element
from A to B, you can either
just move it from A to B,
but you could also move it from
A to B and a little bit back
and a little less
back, and it will
look kind of like a bounce.
And that's exactly
what we're going to do.
So we have a constructor
where we take some options.
In this case,
there's going to be
an option, for example, for
bounciness, which makes sense.
How bouncy is it
supposed to look?
And in the animate
call, we are going
to use this bounce function.
Depending on the bounciness
and the current time,
we're going to determine where
in between these two keyframes
we want to end up.
So the bounce function I use,
I implemented with some really
dodgy and handwavy physics.
But in the end, you
can just think about it
like implementing this kind of
graph between two keyframes.
So if we do that,
and we run that,
you can see that it's
now actually a bounce.
And keep in mind that this is
literally just two keyframes,
and we're just bending
time, so to speak.
And this animation,
because it's a worklet,
runs off the main thread.
It actually runs on
the compositor thread.
Meaning that even if the
main thread is super busy,
it will make sure that
this animation runs exactly
at the device's frame rate,
frame perfect, and make sure
that your animations look
really, really smooth.
So so far, we have done this.
We have done animation.
But if you look at
this, I explicitly
wrote out document
timeline even though it's
an optional argument.
The point is that with
Animation Worklet,
you could get time from
somewhere else, not just
actual time.
You could, for example,
think of something
like a scroll timeline.
Or you could even
conceive of something
like an input timeline.
We are talking about
input timeline,
but I have nothing to show here.
But I can show you
scroll timeline.
So here, you see a
Pac-Man that I've linked
to a scroller at the bottom.
So what you see, I can
basically scroll the scroller
at the bottom, and the animation
will jump to the position
where I am within the scroller.
And so it kind of gives this--
this gives you an
animation scrubber.
And this is kind of fun
but not that useful.
But you can conceive of
more useful uses [INAUDIBLE]
scroll-linked
effects, where I have
three independent animation.
The follow button, my
name, and my avatar
are all scroll-linked
effects that
can assume their position
within the animation
depending on how far I scroll.
The parallax effect would be
another very popular choice
to use with this.
And it's much easier to
implement than it currently
is on the web.
Now, in combination with CSS
Scroll Snap Points that we just
implemented in Chrome, you can
now have a lot of synergy here,
where you have really
smooth transitions
between different
sections of your app.
And you see I have
an indicator on top,
and the images kind
of zoom into view.
And now, for me, the
really interesting thing
is that Animation Worklet is the
same thing as the Paint Worklet
was for rounded corners.
If you don't like how
Scroll Snap Points work,
Animation Worklet
is low-level enough
to allow you to implement
your own version.
So it really
future-proofs the web
for whatever people will
come up with in the future.
Let's talk about the
3PigStability index
for this API, which--
we have gone through many,
many iterations on Animation
Worklet, but always in
collaboration with Apple,
with Microsoft,
and with Mozilla.
And we are now at a point we
feel fairly confident that all
the browsers are at least
on-board on a conceptual level
with what we come up with.
So all in all, I would
give this a wood stability.
As I said, we feel pretty
confident about it.
But now it's really time for us
to see what you feel about it.
So it is in Canary.
You can play with it now.
And we are going to an
origin trial in Chrome 71.
So if you want to test
out in production--
and we would love it if you do--
please sign up here.
As I said, the article should
give you all the insight
that you need to get started.
And if not, please contact me.
I'm very eager to
help out so that we
can get some real data on the
benefits of Animation Worklet.
I have-- I don't know how much
time I have left at this point.
I'm just going to go for it.
Because I can talk a little
bit about Layout API.
So the Layout API,
I'm going to start
with the 3PigStability index
because it's complete straw.
We literally refactored this API
two weeks ago at [? TPACK. ?]
So there is a half-finished
implementation in Canary,
and you should play with it.
But don't expect the code
to still run next week.
But there is so much
potential in this [INAUDIBLE]..
I really want to give you
a little insight into this.
So with the custom layout
API or the Layout Worklet,
you can basically define
your own display values.
So I'm just going to have a main
element and a couple of divs
in there, and that's it.
Everything-- all the other magic
will happen in the worklet.
So now we have a layout
worklet on the CSS namespace.
I'm going to add the module.
And in there, we have
a layout callback.
I'm not going to explain all
the parameters because A,
I don't understand them all.
And B, layout is pretty complex.
But I'm going to
keep this one simple
so we can get a feel for it.
So what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to loop over
all the children,
all my child nodes
that are on my custom
layout element.
I'm going to lay them out in
empty space, basically asking,
how big would you be if
you had no constraints?
And then I'm just going to
give them a random offset,
basically giving them
a random position
within the rectangle
that I occupy.
And then I return this
list to the browser saying,
I did my layout.
Now, please go
forth and paint me.
And that's exactly what
the browser will do.
So if you look at this, you
can see a couple of rectangles.
And every couple seconds,
I add or remove a rectangle
to force a relayout.
And they get a truly
random position,
which is also truly useless.
But you can see that
this is actual the layout
phase of the browser.
This runs during
the layout phase
of the browser,
something that was
completely closed-off
to developers so far.
And to give a little bit
more of a useful example,
I also implemented
a masonry layout.
So here, I'm just
loading random images
from Unsplash with
different aspect ratios.
And the masonry
algorithm, if you will,
takes care of assembling
these in three columns.
And the number of
columns is, once again,
just a custom properties,
which I can increase.
And it will kind of
scale up and give you
this really nice masonry look,
which so far, you would always
have to do with position
absolute magic and main thread
JavaScript.
And this is just
actual layout, which
I think is really exciting.
If you're into the code--
because I don't have an
article for Layout Worklet yet,
mostly because by the time I
would be done with an article,
it would be out of date again--
please go to this
repository that I maintain,
where I have samples for all the
worklets I talked about today.
And you can fork them and
play around with them.
Or I would be so happy if
you contributed to them.
I kind of want to build a
collection of off the shelf
Houdini elements
with popular effects,
which I think would
be really useful.
If you want to keep up with
the development of Houdini,
I made
ishoudinireadyyet.com, where
you can see all the
browsers, which Houdini
APIs they support,
which ones are
in development, which
ones they at least want
to implement in time.
There is links to the articles,
to demos, to the specs.
Hopefully, I can make
this the one-stop shop
that you need to
keep up with Houdini.
And I can't believe that I
made it to my last slide.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]