[MUSIC PLAYING]
SHUBHIE PANICKER: My
name is Shubhie Panicker.
I'm a software engineer working
on the web platform in Chrome.
JASON MILLER: And
I'm Jason Miller.
I'm a [INAUDIBLE] for Chrome.
SHUBHIE PANICKER:
Our talk today is
about a key strategy for
runtime performance of web apps,
and that is scheduling of
JavaScript on the main thread,
as well as approaches for moving
script off the main thread.
Jason and I have both
been deep in this space
exploring gaps in APIs for
what we are calling achieving
get responsiveness guarantees.
We're excited about
the opportunity
here, both with
existing primitives
as well as the new APIs
we will show in our talk.
JASON MILLER: Right,
so to get started,
let's illustrate this
problem space using a demo.
So this is a simple application
that searches through photos
as you type.
And you can see here
with this JavaScript
controlled red
spinner animation,
it's doing a fair
amount of blocking work
on the main thread.
And while this is happening,
the app can't respond to input.
So typing gets queued.
Looking closer, what we see
if we pulled up the profiler
is something like this--
a sequence of long tasks
that block the main thread
and cause that input queuing.
We can see this on a
simplified view here.
So if we receive
input and we start
doing some processing in
response to that input--
say, searching photos
rendering some list items--
we're skipping frames already.
But in addition to that, if
we receive additional input
while that task is running,
it will get queued,
and it only is able to execute
once that has completed.
So this is data
captured from real users
on real websites in the wild.
And it shows a breakdown of
where Chrome was spending
its time while handling input.
So there's a lot of
interesting data here,
but we don't really have
time to get into it.
The main thing to look
at is the amount of time
that we're spending in
this V8.execute task.
That is Chrome
running JavaScript
during touch handling.
And it's clearly the
biggest contributor
to touch input latency, both on
average and also in the worst
case.
SHUBHIE PANICKER: So a
problem with our search as you
type example app is
that there's just
a lot of different types
of work happening here.
And all of these
different work have what
we are calling rate deadlines.
So for example, the user is
typing in that search box.
Their input has
to be responsive.
There's ongoing
animations on the page.
They have to render
consistently and smoothly.
And then there's
the heavy lifting
of fetching search results,
post-processing, preparing,
rendering these
search results in time
so that it's relevant to
the user's typed in query.
The difficulty is that
it's hard for apps
to balance these
competing needs to reason
about all these different
deadlines and keeping
everything meeting
these timelines.
JASON MILLER: Right,
so we have a bunch
of different types of work.
And each of those types of
work has a different deadline.
And what we need to be
able to work through this
is priorities.
SHUBHIE PANICKER:
So there's a couple
high level approaches
to try and achieve
responsiveness guarantees.
The first approach can
just be doing less work.
And there are ways of doing this
such as in an infinite feed,
you might only render
what's visible.
We just saw a strategy with
the virtual-scroller talk
right now.
Now this is not always possible.
Modern apps often just
have a ton of work to do.
So a second strategy
here is chunking up work
and prioritizing
these chunks of work.
In practice, though, this
is also very difficult.
It can be impractical to achieve
this manually on your own
as an app developer.
And we think there's a real
opportunity here for frameworks
to step in and help their users.
Frameworks are in
a great position
to ensure chunking and
prioritizing of work.
So stepping back a
bit, what we need here
is some way to provide our
chunks of work, our tasks,
to a system that can hold
them, say, in a task queue,
and then the system
can make good decisions
about when to take tasks
out of the task queue
and execute them at an
appropriate time based
on everything that's going on.
And this is the
definition of a scheduler.
JASON MILLER: So Google Maps
is a really great example
of an application that
uses a scheduler to keep
its interactions smooth.
This app has to manage multiple
different types of interactions
and events.
And these can all
happen concurrently.
They do this by
scheduling all work
and giving a much higher
priority to input response
tasks.
We can see that here.
So let's say I'm
panning the map.
And as I'm panning,
additional tiles
are coming into the viewport
and need to be loaded.
However, if I stop
panning and I pull up
the drawer at the
bottom, all of a sudden,
that is far and away the most
high priority task to execute.
So those map tiles being loaded
need to be de-prioritized.
SHUBHIE PANICKER: So a key
aspect of a good scheduler
is its ability to execute
work at the best time.
And this is an
appropriate time based
on everything that's going
on, various factors like,
what's the type of the task,
what's important to the user
right now, what's the overall
state of the application,
what's the internal state
of the browser, et cetera.
So to understand this
notion of best time,
we have to step down a level and
look at the browser's rendering
pipeline.
The browser is periodically
bumping frames, typically
every 16 milliseconds for a 60
frames per second display rate.
And each frame has a set of
things that happen in sequence.
For instance, we have request
animation frames followed
by style, layout, and paint.
In Chrome, input handlers
are aligned right
before request animation
frame callbacks.
So the point here is that
there is limited time
to do the urgent work that needs
to happen in the current frame.
And then the app has
to immediately start
thinking about preparing
for that next frame.
And the third type of
work here is idle work,
which might be left over
in the current frame
or there might be
plenty of idle time
if no frames are being rendered.
So this is the
terminology we are using
for these three types of work.
We have user-blocking tasks
for the current frame.
This is typically
to provide the user
an immediate acknowledgment
of what they are doing.
So in our example app, this
might be keeping that typing
interactive in the search box,
keeping those animations going
on the page.
Overall, keeping the
page responsive overall--
buttons should be toggleable.
Default work is this
next category of work.
This is typically user visible.
And this is preparing for the
next frame or a future frame.
And in our example,
this would be
the work of the post-processing,
preparing the search results,
rendering them in time.
And finally, the third
category, idle work.
This is typically work
that is not user visible.
This can be at the
end of the frame
or if no frames are
being rendered-- things
like analytics, backups,
syncs, or indexing.
So on the right here,
we've listed some existing
primitives, existing ways
how a developer might
be able to submit work
to the browser to target
these priority levels.
So for user-blocking,
input handler, and request
animation frames
are great for this.
It's also worth noting
that micro tasks are suited
for user-blocking urgent work.
They do not yield
to the event loop.
And we've seen some bad
cases where developers
are accidentally doing
non-urgent or large amounts
of work without realizing
it's blocking rendering.
The second thing,
default. We have
things like setTimeout
zero, postMessage.
These are really hacks
and work arounds.
There isn't a real
primitive here.
And we are working
to fill this gap.
And finally, for idle,
requestIdleCallback
is a great API.
So JavaScript schedulers
can be built today
using these primitives.
Now while it's possible
to build a scheduling
system in JavaScript,
they suffer from gaps
primarily because they don't
have enough control on signals
to properly control scheduling.
So we'll go through
some examples.
So for example, we've
seen JavaScript schedulers
are trying to estimate
the frame deadline.
So they're doing a whole
bunch of bookkeeping,
trying to guess at it.
But they're doing it poorly
because it's just not
possible to do this well without
knowing browser internals.
So we are considering
exposing an API for that.
isInputPending is a really
useful signal for schedulers,
and we are actively
exploring an API.
Then there's other
coordination work.
So for example, handling
fetch response priorities
is pretty relevant.
If you're doing urgent
work for the current frame,
you don't want your low
priority fetch responses
to come in and interrupt that.
In practice, though,
there's a lot of other work
that's happening in the browser.
The browser might
initiate various callbacks
such as ready state
change for XHR
or a postMessage might
come in from a worker.
There's internal work
like [INAUDIBLE]..
And it's just not possible
to codify priorities
for all of this and
[INAUDIBLE] signals.
So this got us thinking, how
about moving the scheduler one
level down and integrating it
directly with the browser's
event loop where we already
have most of these signals
and a lot of great information?
And this would solve
an additional problem.
That is this
coordination problem
between multiple
parties in the app.
If you have third party content,
or embedded libraries or legacy
code, or even other frameworks,
they can all co-exist and use
the same day scheduling system
with consistent priorities.
So this is a very early sketch
of what an API might look like.
The key thing here is a set
of global task use targeting
each priority level.
And so this is really
simple and straightforward
compared to using a
myriad different APIs.
The second thing
is we think it will
be useful to have a notion
of user-defined task
queues, a virtual task queues.
And this would give
developers more control
over managing a group of tasks
and doing bulk operations
like updating priority,
canceling all the tasks,
or flushing the task used
if the app is going away.
JASON MILLER: Right, so
here we can see a simplified
version of that map
scheduler that we looked
at using this task queue API.
So first, we hook into the
user blocking and default task
queues just to give ourselves a
high and a low priority queue.
And then we start listening
for pointermoves events.
And each time we receive
one of these events,
we enqueue a pan
task with coordinates
at that pointermove.
The pan task translates
the map tiles, obviously.
And then it might, let's say,
enqueue a low priority task
to detect any tiles that
have moved into the viewport
and potentially
load those tiles.
The thing to note here is if we
receive a new pointermove event
before we've invoked this
loadMoreTiles task, that
would be given a higher priority
than loading more tiles.
And that's exactly what we want.
We give higher priority
to input-driven tasks.
And let's say the
team behind Maps
needed to track analytics
or do something in response
to pan gestures, they'll be
a good case for something
like an idle priority task.
SHUBHIE PANICKER: So here you
can see most of the frames
are in green and getting
rendered in time.
And this is what a well
scheduled system looks like.
The work is chunked up.
There is high priority
work happening
at the beginning of every
frame, followed by style,
layout, paint in
purple and green,
just immediately followed by
default priority work in yellow
to prepare for the next frame,
as well as idle priority work
being properly interleaved.
And this time is
adequately utilized.
Next.
So all the APIs
proposals we showed today
are super early stage.
We actually don't know what the
end game here is going to be.
This is a really great time
to give us feedback and help
us chart the course here.
For web developers,
we really think
that there is an opportunity
here with improved scheduling,
even if they're just properly
using existing primitives.
For framework authors,
we want to urge
you to consider a
scheduling system
and collaborate with us now to
develop the right set of APIs
in this space.
React's work on concurrent
and time slicing
has proven that
frameworks can really
play a good role in
terms of helping apps
improve responsiveness of apps.
And we're already
working with React
and actively looking
to form partnerships
with other frameworks and apps.
This is a link to
our GitHub repo.
Filing issues on the
repo is a great way
to get that feedback
dialogue going.
JASON MILLER: Right.
So what about work that
can't be chunked, though?
What if we have a bunch of
JavaScript we need to execute,
and it's really difficult or
even potentially impossible
to break that work up?
Here's an example that
illustrates what I mean.
Let's say we have
a text editor that
does something like
live JavaScript bundling
as you type.
If I load in a decent
amount of code here,
things start to be
a little bit slow.
So every time the
bundling process
kicks in response to my input,
it blocks the main thread.
And this causes the
cursor to freeze
and it queues up my text input
until bundling is completed.
And this really disrupts
the typing experience.
You can see that in the CPU
profile here on the right.
So it would be really
difficult to break
that work up into 50
millisecond chunks,
and that's for two reasons.
First, I didn't write
any of the Bundler code,
so modifying that would be a lot
of work, particularly for me.
Plus there is a whole bunch
of different libraries
that are being used to actually
make these things happen,
those dependencies.
And downloading, parsing, and
evaluating those dependencies
on the main thread blocks.
So using background threads lets
us offload that work and get it
off the main thread so the
main thread can sort of just
keep handling input.
There's a few use cases that
lend themselves extremely
well to this approach.
If you're building a computer
aided design tool, a game,
or doing encoding,
these are great places
to just start with threads.
Same thing for AI,
machine learning, crypto.
If these are the types
of things you're doing,
you should start here.
In the browser, our primitive
for threading is the worker.
So if you haven't
used Workers, you
haven't used them in a while,
they're basically threads.
They have a simple
messaging interface,
so you can send a
message to the worker,
and you can receive
a message back.
They have no DOM access
whatsoever and a very limited
global scope, kind of just
fetch and module stuff.
And they shipped
around 10 years ago,
and they're available
essentially everywhere.
So the API for workers
looks like this.
You will instantiate
the worker constructor
and pass up the
name of a script.
And then we can
listen for messages
coming back out of that worker.
And we can send messages
down to the worker.
So here, we're sending it
a message that's an object.
And this describes that we
would like to, say, invoke
a computeHash function.
And we're going to pass
it the contents of a file,
expressed here as
an array buffer.
The second argument to
postMessage is interesting.
This tells the browser
to, rather than
structured cloning the array
buffer, it will transfer it in.
Finally once computeHash
has completed,
it will say, postMessage
back to our thread
and will be dropped into the
message handler on line 3.
SHUBHIE PANICKER:
So under the covers,
this postMessage of the data
is incurring a serialization
on the main thread.
And it's getting
queued up, hopping over
to a worker thread,
followed by deserialization.
And end-to-end, this
is called a thread hop.
And this thread hop has
a cost, and primarily
from the data being
subject to what
is called structured
cloning, which
is a copying behavior while
recursing the JavaScript
object.
The size of the data is relevant
to the cost of the thread hop.
So one downside of
the postMessage API
is that it doesn't have
a notion of statefulness
between the request
and the response.
So if you make a whole
bunch of requests,
you'll get a whole
bunch of responses back.
And it's hard to correlate
those responses to requests.
JASON MILLER: Right.
So we've seen how to
communicate with a worker using
postMessage.
There's actually a number
of ways you can do this.
A second way would be
to use MessageChannel.
MessageChannel is something
you can instantiate,
and you get back two ports.
You can pass your other port to
some other contexts like a tab
or a frame or a worker, and you
can message between the two.
They have the same
interface, as we just saw.
Another one would
be BroadcastChannel.
This is like a
MessageChannel that's
shared to all
contexts associated
with an origin, so all
tabs, frames, workers,
service worker.
And all you do is you
instantiate a BroadcastChannel
with a channel keyword.
And you message without
having to pass ports around.
Soon we're actually going
to have a fourth way
to communicate.
And this is
transferable streams.
It lends itself really well
to things like audio and video
where the format you would want
to use to express these things
is streaming.
The thing with all of these APIs
is that they're message-based.
And based on some of the common
usage patterns that we've seen
and what we've heard
from developers,
we think there might be a case
here for a higher level API.
So we've seen solutions to this
in userland through libraries
like comlink, greenlet,
workerize, via.js.
These all help coordinate
messaging across boundaries
by abstracting that
postMessage using something
called proxying.
SHUBHIE PANICKER: So
messaging certainly
improves over a postMessage.
I'm sorry.
Proxying improves
over postMessage,
but it comes with a
number of downsides.
Every method call
to a proxied object
incurs the cost of a thread hop,
and this can come as a surprise
to developers.
Platform gaps can cause
memory leaks in these APIs.
These APIs don't really have a
notion of a backing threadpool
or a concept of managing
threads and resizing the pool.
Embedded libraries are not
able to share the same thread
or threadpool.
And for complex APIs, it can
be impractical to recreate
this API surface cross thread.
So this raises the
question, is there
an opportunity here for better
integration with the browser?
Is there an opportunity to
provide a more compelling API?
JASON MILLER: Right.
We think there might be a use
case here for something that
looks something like this.
So here, we're passing
the name of a function
in some other context
and some arguments
to a theoretical
postTask method.
This postTask method
would return a promise
that eventually resolves to the
return value of that function
somewhere else.
This abstract code helps us move
from a message passing model
to a more task-oriented model.
SHUBHIE PANICKER: So in
looking at the requirements
for a better API, we
considered other platforms.
We looked at iOS
and Android, which
have plenty of precedent for
usage of background threads.
In particular, iOS has an API
called Grand Central Dispatch,
which is a very stable
well-proven API that's
loved by iOS developers.
Android, amongst other
things, has something called
AsyncTask, which is a
very minimal, clean API.
We talked to framework
developers and experts
in usage of these APIs
who were deeply familiar
with the pitfalls,
and we learned things.
Some key things we learned in
terms of the basic requirements
we want for our model is,
number one, good ergonomics,
a way for developers
to offload work
by just thinking in
terms of submitting
task versus coordinating
over threads.
Secondly, a native
threadpool that's
shareable with embedded
libraries and other parties
in the app.
And finally, a system-controlled
thread management,
where the system can be in
control of making decisions
on resizing the threadpool or
decisions on where to run which
tasks.
So we set off on a
path towards building
a basic task queue-based API
inspired by Grand Central
Dispatch.
And a naive API
might look like this.
Let's say you have three
tasks, A, B, and C.
And let's say each one
depends on the results
of the previous task, and
we can submit these tasks
from the main thread
over to worker threads.
And then we'll start
getting responses back.
So here for three tasks, we paid
the cost of six thread hops.
There's a few downsides
here and gotchas.
So for one, these
thread hops can be
expensive on lower-end devices.
And depending on
the data size, it
can be up to 15 milliseconds,
and this can add up.
This means that
if these hops are
in the path of user
interaction, this
can add up to multiple
frames worth of latency now.
On Android, we've actually
seen this in practice
in the real world in
their usage of AsyncTask.
So one conclusion
here is this notion
of default posting back results
to the main thread is not
a good idea.
Besides the latency issue,
it can cause congestion
from queue buildups.
And then you might remember
from our earlier main thread
scheduling talk, we're
doing all this work
to carefully chunk up our work
and execute our high priority
and our default priority work.
And all these postMessages
coming in at random times
messes with main
thread scheduling.
A second thing to note here
is that default posting,
even to the current
thread, can be pretty bad.
And we saw this in Grand Central
Dispatch with their dispatch
at current queue API.
JASON MILLER: So this
brings us to a new proposal
we have that incorporates
some of our learnings
from other platforms.
It lets developers avoid sending
data back to the main thread.
It lets you chain tasks
together without data transfer,
and pay the return
cost only once.
It also minimizes
thread hops using
a built-in sticky threadpool.
What we want is the experience
that you see up here
on the right.
So let's dive into that.
If we revisit the Code Editor
that we showed earlier,
the one that bundles
JavaScript as you
type, if we do this
using Task Worklet,
we can leverage some
of these features
to improve performance
fairly considerably.
Because Task Worklet
avoids transferring
data between threads, the
bundling and minifying tasks
in this demo can
actually all reuse
the same AST that is generated
from that initial parse task.
In the end, only the
resulting minified code,
which is a relatively
small string,
actually gets sent back
to the main thread.
So the implementation
looks something like this.
First, we create
a Worklet module,
and that registers
named task processors.
These are just classes
with a process method.
Then over on the
main thread, we can
coordinate that data
flow using this postTask.
So we're going to
parse the code and then
pass that resulting AST through
the bundle and minify tasks.
And the important
thing to note here
is that none of these variables
are actually holding values.
These are just pointers to data
that exists in the threadpool.
Data transfer back
to the main thread
only happens when
we await the result
property of that last task.
So doing this in a typical
workers implementation
would normally take
six hops, as we saw.
We executed three tasks.
We need to pass a message down
and backup for each of them.
In Task Worklet, this
is only two thread
hops because we can
transfer data between tasks.
Task Worklet is also
backed by a threadpool.
So let's say we start
off with a task that
produces a large set of images.
When we post a task with some
of those images as its argument,
it will attempt to
run in the thread
where that data is
already available.
So data is never transferred
between threads in this case,
and at least a few
are thread hops.
To take advantage
of pooling, though,
if there's no optimal
thread available,
we will resort to transferring
data between threads
in order to get parallelization.
And then finally,
let's say the result
that we're looking
for here is actually
just a comparison of
the number of cats
versus the number of
dog photos, since that's
what's important in the end.
In this case, the
only thing we ever
transfer back to the main
thread is a single integer.
And as you can imagine,
that's extremely cheap.
So we've been thinking
a lot about what
the future of web development
off the main thread
might look like today we have
libraries like Comlink that
use reflection to
kind of emulate
the interface of some
code running in a worker
so that it could be called from
the main thread seamlessly.
In the future, we think we might
move towards a Task Worklet
model where developers approach
multi-threaded web programming
in sort of a different way.
You have a threadpool that's
managed automatically, named
tasks, and this
concept of a task graph
that optimizes
execution and data flow.
So this is a really
early proposal.
We are looking for
feedback, and we are looking
for real-world use cases.
There is an implementation
available in Chromium
behind the Experimental
Web Platform Features flag.
And also we have Polyfill
and some source code
and demos available
at this GitHub repo.
There will be a link at the end
of the presentation as well.
SHUBHIE PANICKER:
So there's been
a lot of interest in this idea
of multi-threaded JavaScript
over the last couple years.
There have been several
independent explorations
by various frameworks and apps.
So we dug into this
in the last few months
to understand how far can we
get with just using the worker
API as a way to
achieve threadedness.
And to set some context
here, a new worker
doesn't just spin
up a raw OS thread.
It actually creates its
own JavaScript environment
on top of this.
And part of that is what's
called a V8 isolate, which
has a non-trivial
weight in addition
to the weight of the OS thread.
A key implication here
is that the worker,
by creating its own
JavaScript environment,
is not able to share data or
code with the main thread.
And this is fundamentally
different from background
threads on other platforms
and other languages.
So this has implications
in terms of using Workers
in a mainstream way.
And by that I mean when the
worker is in the path of user
interaction.
In particular, we looked at
two app development models
using worker.
The first one is doing state
management in a worker,
and this is where you can do
the heavy lifting, business
logic-y stuff in a worker.
And the second model
goes even further
and does the bulk of
rendering in the worker.
Now while worker doesn't
have access to the DOM,
there are libraries
like WorkerDOM.
So you can do virtual
DOM updates in the worker
and then ferry the [? diffs ?]
back to the main thread.
So real apps have been
built using these models.
However, there are some
significant challenges
that we want to
highlight here if you're
planning to go down this route.
The first thing is that it's
hard to have synchronous access
to a worker, but real apps
need synchronous access
to their app state.
So what this means
is sometimes you
want to look up your app
state on the main thread,
and sometimes you might update
that app state on a worker.
And this means you now have
to maintain and replicate
this app state in both
places and synchronize it
continuously.
And this has a cost in
terms of thread hops.
The second thing here is
that the worker has to be
bootstrapped with all the
script and modules that it needs
because, like we said, it
cannot share code with the main
thread.
And this has implications
for startup delay.
So we run benchmarks to dig
into this base cost of a worker.
And these are some numbers
from a medium Android device.
Startup takes upwards
of 10 millisecond.
And this is, again,
a Chrome on Android.
A thread hop varies anywhere
from one to 15 milliseconds,
depending on the device and
the size and type of the data.
Look out for a
blog post that will
be accompanying this talk
in the next week or two.
And we will have some detailed
links to our benchmarks
and data there.
We also set up more
realistic benchmarks.
We built apps that
were representing
the app development models
we mentioned, that is,
the state management in a worker
and rendering in a worker.
And we did a ton of runs
on real mobile devices,
both with and without worker.
And we looked at a
variety of metrics,
everything from loading
metrics, memory metrics,
to rendering metrics, such as
frame rate and input latency.
And we approximated input
latency using cycle time.
So again, the blog post will
have more details on this.
But I do want to highlight
one bit of interesting data.
So this is basically
showing runs
with an app that
is representative
of rendering in a worker.
The red are runs with worker,
and blue runs without worker.
So what we are seeing
here is that on worker, we
are seeing a higher and
more improved frame rate.
But on the flip
side, we are also
seeing a higher input latency.
So there is a
fundamental trade-off
here between improved
smoothness versus user latency.
Workers are able to free up the
main thread by offloading work.
And so they can free
up that main thread
to focus on rendering, and
less grip means fewer long task
hiccups on the main thread.
Again, on the flip
side, input latency
suffers from thread hops.
And the worker environment
is a limited environment
and doesn't have APIs.
And it's not just the DOM.
There are many other APIs as
that are still not available,
like media, audio, et cetera.
JASON MILLER: Yeah.
So the key thing to
take away from this
is, workers might be able to
make your rendering smoother,
but they might do it at the
expense of a bit of input
delay.
There's cases, though, where
this is completely worth it.
So AMPscript is a great example.
AMPscript renders
using workers in order
to sandbox, potentially
misbehaving JavaScript.
Slower or problematic
code that's
running in the worker
in this emulated DOM
can't negatively impact
the AMP document.
And so for AMP, the
benefits they get out
of sandboxing untrusted code
far outweigh the latency
that they get from
transferring events.
So we wanted to summarize
when they use workers,
but it turns out there's
no perfect rubric for this.
So there's a couple of
hints you can use though.
If you have code that
blocks for a long time,
if you have code with
small inputs and outputs,
or something that follows the
simple request response model,
you might be in a position
to start off with workers.
However, if you have code
that relies on the DOM
or is directly in the
path of input response,
or just code that needs
really minimal overhead,
you might want to start off
with a different solution.
You could approach
workers later.
When adopting a threaded
approach to state management,
make sure that your state
management and business
logic outweighs the cost
of creating a worker
and sending and
receiving messages.
Make sure that your worker
is pulling its own weight.
So we're at the
beginning of a fairly
major shift in how applications
are developed for the web.
We're excited to explore
new possibilities
for effective scheduling
and threading.
And we hope that
all of you are too.
SHUBHIE PANICKER:
And so we just want
to leave you with some of these
key messages from our talk
today.
It's hard to achieve
responsiveness guarantees
because there's so much work
happening in modern apps.
And we think scheduling
is a compelling strategy
for tackling this.
There's an opportunity here
for improved scheduling
with existing primitives
as well as new primitives.
And frameworks are
in a good position
to play a big role here.
In terms of offloading
work from the main thread,
you can think of using
worker as an extension
to better main
thread scheduling.
Some types of work are better
suited to worker than others.
And we think new APIs
like Task Worklet
are going to be compelling to
utilize worker for scheduling.
So that's about it.
We'll have a blog post
coming with more details.
These are, again, the
links to the GitHub repos.
Issues on the repos are
very welcome and appreciated
and a great way too
for the feedback loop.
And do not hesitate to reach
out to us on email or Twitter.
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]