[MUSIC PLAYING]
HOUSSEIN DJIRDEH: Hi,
I'm Houssein Djirdeh
for the "Developer Show."
Chrome Dev Summit is back
again for another year
in San Francisco, and
there are a bunch of things
we're excited to talk about.
Here are the top five
juiciest stories.
To cover number one, the first
edition of the Web Almanac
has just launched.
The Almanac combines
extensive HTTP archived data
for millions of URLs
with the expertise
of many top contributors
in the web ecosystem.
It's an annual state-of-the-red
report containing 20 chapters
that covers every major
aspect of the web,
including page content,
user experience,
and content distribution.
For number two,
the Search Console
now includes a brand
new Speed Report,
which provides
information on how
groups of pages on your site are
performing against key metrics.
All of this information comes
from real user measurements
thanks to the Chrome
User Experience Report.
Currently, developers
use a whole suite
of different performance
metrics to assess how well
their site is performing.
Two brand new metrics make
up number three in this list.
When we talk about
time to first paint,
we don't really
have a very good way
to measure how quickly users can
see the most important content
on the page.
Well, now, that's changed with
the Largest Contentful Paint
metric.
This new metric can be used
to measure how fast users
see the largest, and usually
the most significant, content
on the page.
It is now available
in Chrome 77.
Have you ever opened
a web page and are
about to click a link or button,
but more content shows up
that actually changes
the layout of the page,
shifting the link or
button away from where
you intended to click?
Yep.
It's happened to me, too, and
it can be quite frustrating.
Cumulative Layout
Shift is a new metric
that you can use
to derive a score
on how much unexpectedly
layout shifting is happening
on a page.
Number four goes to a
number of new updates
to developer tooling.
Stack Packs, a feature that
extends Lighthouse to include
additional, actionable
advice, depending
on what tools are
detected on a page,
now supports more
than just WordPress.
If you run Lighthouse
or Page Speed Insights
on any site that uses either
WordPress, Magento, Amp,
Angular, or React, you will see
additional performance audit
suggestions that are relevant
for the detected stack.
Lightouse Bot was a
previously released library
that allowed developers
to run Lighthouse
in continuous
integration, essentially
being able to fail a build if a
specified score was not passed.
The MVP for Lighthouse CI,
an entirely new library
has just launched, which takes
this concept a step further.
With a collection of commands
to assert, save, and visualize
Lighthouse reports over time.
A number of framework
and ecosystem efforts
make up number
five on this list.
In terms of performance,
many frameworks and tools
have added a number
of optimizations
to make the process of
building faster sites easier
for many developers.
We've also been working
closely with the Next.js team,
improving the framework in
a number of different ways.
This includes a better web
patch [? trunking ?] strategy,
differential loading
with module or no module,
and a number of
JavaScript optimization.
A few major sites
already using Next.js
have begun to take advantage
of these new features
to reduce their amount
of JavaScript footprint.
We announced a framework
fund last year,
and we're excited to see
that many tools that we've
been supporting have taken steps
to improve their performance.
This includes libraries like
bundlephobia and bundlesize,
as well as fully fledged
frameworks like Nuxt.js.
For all announcements
and updates,
check out the links in
the description below.
Please remember to like,
subscribe, and share.
I'm Houssein Djirdeh for
the "Developer Show."
Thanks for watching.
[MUSIC PLAYING]