[MUSIC PLAYING]
KATIE HEMPERIUS:
Today, Houssein and I
are going to talk
with you about how
you can make your site fast.
We're going to focus on
three things, images,
web fonts, and JavaScript.
We've chosen to focus
on these three things
because they are
the three largest
components of most websites.
In addition, they're likely to
be the three largest components
of your performance budget.
We hope that after
this presentation,
you'll go home and make
changes to your website.
Know that during
this process, you
can lean on both
Lighthouse and web.dev
for additional resources.
Almost everything we cover today
can be audited by Lighthouse.
In addition, at web.dev can find
guides, code samples, and demos
of everything we cover today.
So let's start by
talking about images.
Images are taking over the web.
On many sites, images
alone would consume
the entire performance budget.
On some sites, it
would far exceed that.
I think the reason why
these numbers are so bad
lies in the fact that
performant images are
the result of many
steps and optimizations.
As a result, they're not
going to happen accidentally.
A performant image is
the appropriate format,
is appropriately compressed,
is appropriate for the display,
and is loaded only
when necessary.
To be successful
with images, it's
imperative that you automate
and systematize these things.
Not only is this going
to save you time,
but it's going to ensure that
these things actually get done.
There's much more to
images than meets the eye.
At a bits and bytes
level, an image
is as much a byproduct
of its image format
and its compression as
its visual subject matter.
You can think
about image formats
as choosing the right
tool for the job.
The image format
that you choose will
determine what features and
image has, for instance,
whether it supports
transparency or animation,
as well as how it
can be compressed.
The first image format that
I want to talk about today
is the animated GIF.
You should not be fooled by
their crappy image quality.
They're actually
huge in file size.
This 1 and 1/2 second
clip is 6.8 mgs as a GIF.
As a video, however, is 16
times smaller, at 420 megabytes.
This is not uncommon.
Animated GIFs can be anywhere
from five to 20 times
larger than the same
content served as a video.
This is why if you've ever
inspected your Twitter feed,
you may have noticed
that the content labeled
as GIF is not actually a GIF.
Twitter does not
serve animated GIFs.
If you upload an animated
GIF, they will automatically
convert it to video.
The reason for the
drastic difference
in file sizes between
videos and animated GIFs
lies in the differences between
their compression algorithms.
Video compression algorithms
are far more sophisticated.
Not only do they compress
the contents of each frame,
what they do what is known
as inner frame compression.
And you can think of
this as compression
that looks at the difs
between the different frames.
The first step in switching
from animated GIFs to video
is to convert your content.
You can use the ffmpeg
command line tool for this.
Next, you'll need
to update your HTML,
and replace image
tags with video tags.
The code I have up on the
screen is technically correct,
but it's probably not
what you want to use.
Instead, you want to make sure
to add the four attributes I've
highlighted up on the screen.
That's going to give
your video that GIF look
and feel even though
it's not a GIF.
Now, we'll switch gears and talk
about a much more modern image
format, and that,
of course, is WebP.
WebP is no longer a
Chrome only technology.
Last month, Microsoft Edge
shipped support for WebP.
In addition, Mozilla Firefox
announced their intent
to ship WebP.
Currently, 72% of global web
users have support for WebP.
And given these
recent developments,
you can expect this
number to only increase.
This is a big deal
because WebP images
are 25% to 35% smaller than
the equivalent JPEG or PNG.
And this translates into some
really awesome improvements
in page speed.
When the Trib united
support for WebP,
they found there was a 30%
improvement in page load times
on WebP supported browsers.
By far the biggest hesitation
I see around adopting WebP
is a fear that you can't
both serve WebP and support
non-WebP browsers.
And this is not true.
The picture and the
source tags make it
possible to do precisely this.
You can think of the picture tag
as a container for the source
and image tags that it contains.
The source tag is used
to specify multiple image
formats of the same image.
The browser will download the
first, and only the first,
image that is in a
format that it supports.
So in this example I
have up on the screen,
the Chrome browser would
download the WebP version,
a Safari browser would
download the JPEG version.
The great thing about
this is that even
though all major browsers have
supported picture and source
tag since 2015, however,
if say, a 2014 browser were
to encounter this,
it would still work,
because those
browsers would just
download the image
specified by the image tag.
If you haven't
noticed, I've been
talking about image formats.
But I want to kind
of go on a tangent
and squeeze in a mention
of the AV1 video format.
And the reason why I
wanted to squeeze it in
is that it is the future
of video on the web.
The reason why it's the
future of video on the web
is that it compresses video
45% to 50% better than what
is currently typically
used on the web.
It is still fairly new, so
it's not really practical
for you to be implementing
it on your site yet.
However, I encourage you to
attend Francois and Angie's
talk at 3:30 today,
where they're
going to be diving into
AV1 in more detail.
Image compression
is a topic that's
tightly coupled
to image formats.
Image compression algorithms
are specific to the image format
that they compress.
However, all image
compression algorithms
can be broken down into
lossless and lossy compression.
Lossless compression
results no loss of data.
Lossy compression does
result in loss of data,
however can achieve
greater file size savings.
At a minimum, all sites should
be using lossless compression,
no questions asked.
However, for most
people, it's going
to make sense to be
slightly more aggressive
and use lossy
compression instead.
The trick with
lossy compression is
finding that sweet spot
between file size savings
and image quality for
your particular use case.
Many lossy compression tools
use the scale of zero to 100
to represent the image quality
of the compressed image,
with zero being the worst,
and 100 being the best.
If you're looking for a place
to start with lossy compression,
we recommend trying out a
quality level of 80 to 85.
This typically reduces
file size by 30% to 40%,
while having a minimal
effect on image quality.
By far, the most popular
tool for image compression
is Imagemin, and it can be used
with just about everything.
Imagemin is used in conjunction
with various Imagemin plugins.
And you can think
of these plugins
as implementations of different
image compression algorithms.
Up on the screen, I've put the
most popular Imagemin plugins
for various use cases.
However, these are by no means
the only Imagemin plugins
available.
Image sizing is something
I think many sites could
be doing a much better job at.
We have so many
types of devices,
and specifically sizes
of devices that access
the web these days.
However, we insist on serving
them all the exact same size
of image.
Not only does this have
transmission costs,
but it also creates
additional work for the CPU.
A solution, of
course, is to serve
multiple sizes of an image.
Most sites find success
serving anywhere
from three to five
sizes of an image.
And in fact, this is
exactly what Instagram does.
Instagram uses this technique
throughout their site.
However, one use case where they
were able to measure its impact
was with their Instagram embeds.
For context, Instagram embeds
allow third-party sites
to display Instagram
content on their own site.
As a result of serving
multiple image sizes,
Instagram was able to
reduce image transfer
size by 20% for their
Instagram embeds.
Two popular tools for imagery
resizing are Sharp and Jimp.
The biggest difference
between the two
is that Sharp is faster,
and when I say faster,
I mean faster at
image processing.
However, it requires that you
compile C and C++ to install
it.
In addition to creating
multiple sizes of your images,
you'll need to update your HTML.
You'll want to add the source
set and sizes attributes.
The source set
attribute allows you
to list multiple versions
of the same image.
In addition to
including the file path,
you'll also want to include
the width of the image.
This saves the browser from
having to download the image
to figure out how large it is.
The size attribute tells
the browser the width
that the image will
be displayed at.
By using the information
contained in the source set
and sizes attribute, the
browser can then figure out
which image to download.
Lazy loading is the
last image technique
that I'll be
talking about today.
Lazy loading is a strategy
of waiting to download
a resource until it is needed.
In addition to images, it can
be applied to resource types
like JavaScript.
Image lazy loading
helps performance
by using that bottleneck that
occurs on initial page load.
In addition, it saves user
data by not downloading
images that may never be used.
Spotify is an
example of a website
that uses this technique
very effectively.
On this particular
page that I pulled up,
image lazy loading
was the difference
between loading a mg of
images on initial page load
and 18 mgs of an image
on initial page load.
That's a huge difference.
Two tools to look into
for image lazy loading
are lazysizes and lozad.
And you implement them both
more or less the same way.
Add the script
your site, and then
indicate which images
should be lazy loaded.
However, just because this is a
fairly simple to use technique
does not mean that's
not important.
In fact, it is so important
that native lazy loading
is coming to Chrome.
[APPLAUSE]
Native lazy loading
means that you'll
be able to take
advantage of lazy loading
without having to add
third-party scripts
on your site.
It'll be available
for both images
and cross origin I-frames.
And you can truly be lazy when
it comes to implementing it.
If you make no
changes to your HTML,
the browser will simply
decide which resources
should be lazy loaded.
If you do care, however, you
can use the lazy load attribute
to specify which attributes
should or should not
be lazy loaded.
Fonts can cause
performance problems
because they are typically
large files that are downloaded
from third-party sites.
As a result, they can
take a while to load.
This leads to the
phenomenon known
as the flash of invisible text.
And shockingly, this affects two
out of every five mobile sites.
Flash of invisible
text looks like this.
Instead of a user being
greeted with text on your site,
they're greater
with invisibleness.
Not only is this frustrating,
but it also looks bad.
What you want to
encourage instead
is the flash of unstyled text.
And this is when the
browser initially displays
text using a system
font and then
swaps it out for the custom
font once it has arrived.
The good news here is that this
fix is literally a one-liner.
Everywhere in your CSS where
you declare a font face,
add the line font display swap.
This tells the browser to
use that swapping behavior
that I just talked about
in the previous slide.
Now I'm going to
hand the mic over
to Houssein who's going to
talk with you about techniques
you can use with
your JavaScript.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
HOUSSEIN DJIRDEH:
So Katie showed
a number of
techniques that could
be quite useful for the images
and web fonts in your site,
as well the few exciting things
coming to the Chrome platform
in the near future, like
native lazy loading.
For the rest of this
talk, we'll go over
some other important
things you should
be doing before the JavaScript
that makes up your application.
Earlier in this
session, we saw how
images can make up the
majority of a site with regards
to number of bytes sent.
However, we also send
a significant amount
of JavaScript to browsers.
If we take a look
at HTTP archive data
once again, as of last
month, the median amount
of JavaScript that we
shipped to mobile web pages
was about 370 kilobytes.
For desktop, the
number was about 420.
Now JavaScript code still needs
to be uncompressed, parsed,
and executed by the browser.
So in reality, we're
looking at about a megabyte
of uncompressed code
that needs to be sent--
that needs to be for an
application of this size.
Users who try to access this
with low-end mobile devices
will notice a much
poorer performance.
But why are we, as
developers, shipping way more
JavaScript code than
we've ever done before?
There are a number of reasons.
One of them being the
amount of dependencies
that we pull into
our applications
and how easy that
process has become.
Front-end tooling has come a
long way in the past decade,
but there has been some cost.
So what can we do to
continue to try and build
robust and fully
fledged applications,
but not at the expense
of user experience?
The very first thing we can
and should consider doing is
splitting our bundle .
The idea behind
code splitting is
instead of sending all the
JavaScript code to your users
as soon as they load the very
first page of your application,
is to only send them what they
need for their initial state.
And then allow them to fetch
future chunks on demand.
The easiest way to get
started with code splitting
is by using dynamic imports.
Now dynamic imports
has been supported
in Webpack for quite some time.
And it allows you to import
a module asynchronously
where a promise gets returned.
Once that promise
finishes resolving,
you can do what you need to
do with that piece of code.
The idea behind
dynamic imports is
you want to make sure that
it fires on certain user
interactions.
And you want to do this to make
sure that you only fetch code
when it's actually needed.
If you happen to be using
another module bundler,
like parcel or roll
up, you can still
use dynamic import to code
split where you see fit.
Now, a number of JavaScript
libraries and frameworks
have provided abstractions
on top of dynamic imports
to make the process
of code splitting
easier with your
current tooling.
With view, for example, you
can define async components.
And they're just functions
that return a promise that
resolve to the set components.
By using that with
dynamic imports,
you can attach
async opponents into
your routing configurations.
So that only when a
certain route is reached,
only then will the code
and lives in that component
be fetched.
Angular has a very
similar pattern.
In its router, you can use
the load children attribute
and you can use it
to connect a feature
module to a specific route.
With load children, you
can define a dynamic import
with Ivy.
And Ivy's a new rendering
engine that the Angular team
is working on.
When you do this approach, all
the code, all the components,
all the services that
live in the feature module
will only get loaded when
that route is reached.
In the meantime, you
can use load children,
but you just need to
use a relative file
path to the feature module.
With React, libraries
like React Loadable
and loadable
components have allowed
us to code split on
the component level
while taking care
of other things,
like showing a loading
indicator, or an error state,
where applicable.
However, with React 16.6, the
lazy method was introduced.
And this allows you to code
split while using suspense.
Now suspense is a feature
that the react team has been
working on for quite some time.
And it allows you to suspend how
certain component trees update
your state or update
the DOM, depending
on how all of its
children components
have fetched their data.
Another very useful technique
that ties in well to code
splitting your bundle
is by using preload.
Preload allows us
to tell the browser
that if we have a late
discovered resource
or a resource that's fetched
late in the request chain
that we'd like to download it
sooner because it's important.
So by doing this, we're telling
the browser to prioritize.
To use preload, you only
need to add a link element
to the head of
your HTML document
and you need to
have a rel attribute
with a value of preload.
The as attribute is used
to define what type of file
you'd like to load.
Now as developers, it's
also important to make sure
that the code that
we write works well
in all the browsers people
use to access our site.
So if we happen to include ES
2015, 2016, or later syntax,
we also want to include
backwards compatible formats
so all the browsers can
still understand them.
This usually involves adding
transforms for any newer syntax
that we use and polyfills
for any newer features.
Now because
transpiling means we're
adding code on
top of our bundle,
or application ends
up being larger
than it was originally written.
One way to make sure that
we only transpile the code
that's actually needed is
by using babel/preset-EMV.
This preset takes
the hassle out of us
trying to micromanage
which plugins and polyfills
we need to add.
And it does this by
allowing us to specify
a target list of browsers and
letting babel handle the rest.
You can add this preset
into your list of presets
in your babel
configuration, and you
can use the target's attributes
to define that set of browsers
that you'd like to reach.
Now this is a
browser list query.
So if you use tools like
order auto prefix or before,
you may already be
familiar with it.
Using a percentage, like
here, is one type of query
you can use.
And it allows you to
target browsers that cross
a certain global market share.
The use built-in attribute
allows us to tell babel
how to handle adding polyfills.
The usage value means that
babel only automatically
include polyfills to
files when it's actually
needed for features that
need to be transpiled.
Now this is the behavior we all
want, to only transpile code
when it's required.
So although babel/preset-EMV
means that we can limit
the amount of transpiled code
that we have to make sure that
we only include what's necessary
for all the browsers we plan
to target, what if there was a
way to differentially serve two
different types of bundles?
One, that's largely
un-transpiled,
for newer browsers that don't
need nearly as many polyfills,
and another legacy bundle,
that contains more polyfills,
is a bit larger, but is
needed for older browsers.
We can do this by using
JavaScript modules.
Now JavaScript
modules or ES modules
allow us to write blocks of
code that import and export
from other modules.
But the amazing thing
about using modules with
babel/present-EMV is that
we can have it as a target,
instead of a specific
browser query.
One site that's actually using
this module approach today
is "The New York Times."
And they're using it for one
of their flagship articles
of the year, piling in real time
for the 2018 midterm elections.
They're using Sapper as their
client-side framework, which
contains a number of progressive
enhancements baked in,
like automatic code splitting.
But they're also using roll up
to emit module chunks as well.
They're using a fairly
simple heuristic
to make sure that users who
have older browsers download
a larger more polyfilled
bundle, but users who
are using newer browsers
can only download
smaller and slimmer module.
A very simple way to
make sure that users
who access your app only
download one or the other
is by using the module,
no module technique.
When you define a script
element with type module,
browsers that understand modules
will download that normally.
But they'll know to ignore
any script element that
has the no module attribute.
Similarly, browsers that
don't understand modules
will ignore any script
elements that have type module.
But since they can't identify
what no module means,
they'll download
that bundle as well.
So here, we can get the
best of both worlds.
Shipping the right
bundle to our users,
depending on what
browser they use.
If you happen to have
critical modules that you'd
like to download sooner,
you could do that
by also preloading them as well.
And you just need to specify
a module preload value
to the rel attribute.
So we've talked
about a few things
you can do to improve the code
that you ship to your users,
but if you're thinking of adding
any of these optimizations,
it could be useful to try
and keep an eye on things.
And there are tools out
there that could actually
make this easier.
The code coverage tab
within Chrome DevTools
allows you to see the
size of all your bundles,
as well as how much of it
is actually being used.
You can access it by
opening the Command menu
and just typing in coverage.
If you're using Webpack,
Webpack bundle analyzer
can be a very handy tool.
And it gives you a nice
heat map visualization
of your entire bundle.
You can zoom in, see which
parts of your bundle are larger
and which parts of your
bundle are smaller.
And if you've ever
wanted to find
the cost of a specific library,
you can use bundle phobia.
You could type the
name of a package
and see how large it is, as
well as how much of an impact
it can make to your application
in terms of download time.
You can also scan
your packages on file
to see how much of an impact
all your packages make.
Now as useful as it is to
use tools to manually keep
an eye on how things are
doing with your bundle size,
it can be especially useful to
also include checks into your
build workflow.
One tool that could
actually help here,
that can allow you to
set performance budgets,
is the Lighthouse CI.
So instead of only running a
Lighthouse in the Chrome audits
panel, or as a
Chrome extension, you
can also run Lighthouse
in CI and have
it included as a status
check into your workflow.
You could specify certain
Lighthouse categories and set
scores for them so that
merges and pull requests only
get included if
those scores are met.
Now a site that's
actually taking steps
to add a number of these
optimizations is UniQlo.
They're a clothing
retailer base out of Japan.
And they're taking steps
to improve their entire web
architecture, beginning
with their Canadian site.
They've identified a number
of critical resources
and decided to try and
download them sooner,
and they're doing this
by preloading them.
They've done this
with some images,
some core fonts, as well as a
number of cross origin fetches.
They then also
identified that they
can code split and try to get
some wins that way as well.
They took the correct first
step of code splitting
at the route level.
And just by doing
that alone, they
noticed an almost half size
reduction in their bundle size.
They also moved on to code split
their localization package.
And noticed that they can
get their bundle size down
to 200 kilobytes.
After this, they even
added more optimizations,
such as using a
pre-act compatibility
layer for the react bindings,
to get their bundle size
to about 170 kilobytes.
While doing all
of this, they made
sure to also set budgets
so their whole team can
stay in sync.
And they're using another
open source tool to help here,
called Bundle Size.
They've set 80 kilobyte budgets
for each one of the chunks,
and then allowed them to stay
under a 200 kilobyte total
for all of their scripts.
While adding these
optimizations,
they noticed a two-second
time to interactive reduction
for users that use
low-end mobile devices
and have weak connections.
Now you might think two
seconds is not that much.
But it can make an impact
for your customers.
After these
optimizations were added,
they notice a 14%
reduction in bounce rate,
a 31% increase in
average duration,
and a 25% increase in
pages viewed per session.
Now there were other
things also being
added to the site
at the same time,
but they know that performance
played a very huge factor here.
So we've talked about
quite a few things
that you can do today to
improve how your site performs.
But what can Chrome do
as a browser as well?
For users that opt in
to Data Saver mode,
Chrome will try show a
lightweight version of the page
where possible.
And it does this by
minimizing data used
as well as showing cache
content whenever it can.
Now as developers, you can
also tap into this as well.
And you could do this by using
the network information API.
If you look at the navigator
connection save data
attribute you can identify
whether your users actually
have data saver enabled.
And you could try and serve a
slightly different experience
to make sure things are
fast for them as well.
You can also use the
effective type attribute,
and use that to actually be
able to serve different assets
conditionally depending on what
connection your user is having.
The very last thing that
I do want to mention
is although me and
Katie have talked
about a lot of the
things that you
can do to improve your
site, every application
is built differently.
Every team is different.
Every tool chain is different.
So this isn't something
you need to start
doing wholesale and
including everything at once.
By setting budgets and keeping
an eye on your bundle size
from the very beginning,
you can include performance
enhancements as a
step by step procedure
and make sure your
site never regresses.
Performance doesn't need
to be an afterthought.
Almost everything we've
talked about is in web.dev,
so I highly suggest you take
a look if you haven't already.
We hope you enjoyed this talk
as much as we enjoyed giving it.
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]