[MUSIC PLAYING]
ALBERTO MEDINA: I'm Alberto.
I'm a developer advocate
in the Content Ecosystem
Team at Google.
And I'm super happy to be here
with my teammate, Weston Ruter.
We are going to
talk about bringing
the pillars of modern
web development
to the space of content
management systems.
But let's start with
the end goal in mind.
Our goal as web creators
is to maximize the joy
that our users get when they
go to the websites we build
or the content that we create
and publish on the web.
And although it is true
that user experience is
a complex matter, there
are certain elements
that are commonly found in
experiences that users love.
Specifically, users
love presentations
that work, number one.
They love sites that
load fast consistently
and offer good
runtime performance.
They love sites where they feel
safe when they trust their data
or they do transactions
when they decide to do so.
They like sites that
feel accessible,
and they are integrated
with the full capabilities
of their devices.
And they love sites that
offer great content quality.
The good news is that we can
build today experiences that
have these pillars if we take
advantage of the capabilities
that the modern
web has to offer.
Now, doing this is what we call
progressive web development.
In essence, progressive
web development
is developing
user-first experiences
using modern workflows
and modern web APIs,
following coding best practices
and performance best practices,
and taking advantage of
effective incentive mechanisms
and validation structures that
are available to all, to us.
Now, we can take advantage
of these principles
in different ways,
depending about how
we go through the
creative process,
how do we create
things in the web.
In general, the things
that we create in the web
follow in two categories.
On one hand, we can build
websites or web apps
from scratch, in
which case we have
full control of the
whole creative journey,
from the build process, to
the functionality of the app,
to the look and feel.
Or we can take advantage of
some kind of Content Management
System, or CMS for short, that
are software platforms that
add a layer of abstraction
on top of the open web
to offer capabilities to
create, publish, and consume
digital content on the web.
If we follow the first route,
we have full control and full
flexibility.
It's very powerful.
But also, it requires a lot
of expertise and resources
to follow it.
If we follow the
second route, we
can take advantage
of the capabilities
that the CMS has to offer to us.
But then at the end of
the day, the experience
that we can offer to our users
depends on the characteristic
of the CMS that we choose.
Now, it turns out that nowadays,
the majority of content
in the web is
created and consumed
via some kind of content
management system.
Specifically, 54%
of sites today are
built on some kind of
content management system.
And we saw this year 11%
year over year growth.
These are staggering statistics.
And there are other
systems that do not
think of themselves as
CMSes but also offer
the same capabilities that
make it very easy to create
and publish content.
So in reality, these
statistics are much higher.
So this basically means
that the CMS space
is very large and very complex.
CMS comes in many
shape and form.
And they vary according
to certain dimensions.
For example, you can have static
versus dynamic, open source,
closed source, special
purpose, general purpose.
But although there are
differences between them,
they also share a
lot of commonalities.
And specifically, many of
them face common challenges
when it comes to integrating
progressive web technologies
into their platforms.
So many of these systems
are very large and complex.
They have many
interacting components.
They have large code bases.
They have legacy code,
technical depth, and so on.
There are also,
some of them have
evolved on top of initial
architectural choices that
make it difficult for them to
evolve and become progressive.
They also suffer
from fragmentation
very often in terms of
things like the quality
of the components
that make them,
or the expertise of the
developer community,
or the type of users that
are creating and consuming
content on the platform.
And often-- and this
is very important--
CMSes lack the effective
incentives for developers
to do the right thing.
For example, exposing coding
and performance metrics
so that users of the
CMS can choose solutions
based on quality and
not just on popularity.
Now, we want to tackle these
challenges in the CMS space.
And in order to
reason about how to do
that, it is very useful
to do a [INAUDIBLE]
or thinking about these systems
in terms of the components that
make them, OK?
A CMS ecosystem,
one way or another,
has certain components that
form a unique ecosystem for each
of them.
There is usually a
core, a platform core,
that makes the
functionality of the system.
There is usually some kind
of extension mechanism
that allows you to extend
the core functionality.
These extensions
are usually called
modules in some CMSes, plugins
on another, also, themes,
if they have to do with the
look and feel of the system.
There is usually a
developers' community
that are in charge of
evolving both the core
and the extensions
of that platform.
And then there is the
user base of the CMS
that are either creating
content or consuming
content on the platform.
So when we talk about
progressive content management
systems, we are
talking about bringing
the principles of
progressive web development
to the components of each
of these ecosystems, OK?
For example, how do we
bring coding and performance
best practices to the
developer ecosystem
so that they can
do the right thing?
Can we bring tooling
so that it make it easy
for them to do the right
thing in the first place?
Or can we bring
incentive mechanisms
so that they are compelled
to do the right thing?
Now, Google is working
with many CMSes
to support them in
their effort as they
integrate progressive
technologies
into their platform.
So in the next
few slides, we are
going to show you the results
of a particular effort
that my team has followed in
the context of a specific CMS.
And then later on,
we are going to touch
upon some of the great
work done by other CMSes.
Our team has been
pursuing efforts
to bring progressive web
technologies to the WordPress
ecosystems.
The little fellow
here there is Wapuu.
That is the mascot of
the WordPress ecosystem.
It's not a mouse, although
it looks like a mouse.
So WordPress nowadays powers
about a third of the web.
So there's a lot of users
creating and consuming
content on this platform.
Now, given the size and
complexity of the WordPress
ecosystem, if we address the
challenges that they face,
we will not have only an
impact on a very large swath
of the web, but also we
will be able to shed light
on how to address these
challenges in other CMSes.
So our goal with these
efforts are twofold.
One is to tackle the
challenges that the WordPress
ecosystem faces, and also
to gather our learnings
that we get along the way and
bring them over to other CMSes
in the form of objective
guidance, tutorials, technology
transfers, and so on.
Now, the approach
that we follow to make
WordPress more progressive
consists of two parts.
The first part is leveraging
the capabilities of Accelerated
Mobile Pages, or AMP for short.
AMP provides basically
a well-lit path
to modern web
development in WordPress.
AMP is an open-source web
component library which
provides out-of-the-box a set of
capabilities and optimizations
that are essential to achieve
awesome web experiences
in the web.
For example, coding
and performance
best practices so that
you don't get things
like unresponsive content
when you are loading it,
or good usability so you don't
have this constant shifting
in front of your eyes
when you are trying
to engage with the content.
It also provides a incentive
mechanism-- for example,
the capability of getting
near instant loading
time when AMP content is
loaded from the AMP cache.
And it also provides
a validation framework
that helps developers
to bring their sites
to high-performance
states and to keep them
in that state as
the site evolves.
So if we enable AMP content
creation in WordPress,
that means that
WordPress developers
can take advantage of
all these capabilities
without deviating of the normal
content creation workflow
that they follow in
the platform normally.
We have achieved
this integration
by means of an AMP
plugin for WordPress.
Right now, it is in version
1.0 release candidate 2.
And the stable version
will be released
at the end of this month.
Now, this plugin has a lot
of capabilities and features.
And unfortunately, we don't
have time today to go over them
in detail.
But I want to mention a
specific important one--
one that assists WordPress
developers as they
build themes and plugins that
are fully AMP compatible.
The plugin comes with
a compatibility tool
that supports the development
of AMP content in WordPress.
In a nutshell, for
any URL on a site,
the plugin tells
us all information
about any error that
can exist in that URL
in very minute details.
It tells you even
the markup that
is generating the error and also
the component in the WordPress
site that generated the
markup in the first place.
We'll see the theme.
We'll see the plugin
with WordPress core.
What is it?
So if you are a
WordPress developer,
you can take advantage
of this tool and all
the other capabilities
that the plugin
provides to you to create
AMP content in your website.
If you are a developer
from other CMSes,
the good news is that they
are also implementing AMP.
And we are going
to tell you more
about this in a little bit.
Now, the second
part of our approach
of bringing progressive
[? net ?] to the WordPress
ecosystem consists on
integrating modern web
capabilities and APIs
into WordPress core.
We want things like
service workers,
streaming, background sync--
all the goodies that
you have seen today,
we want them to be
supported natively
in the WordPress platform.
So the goal of
the integration is
that there is a consistent
and unified approach
so that all WordPress developers
can take advantage of them
as they develop functionality
for either core or themes
or plugins.
Now, last year, our
colleague Surma,
where you have heard of
him, and who, by the way,
has a complete disregard
for the impossible,
he decided to show
that PWA with WordPress
is actually possible by building
a WordPress theme that does all
the things, as he called it.
He successfully proved his case.
And he presented his
work at CDS last year.
But he also faced many
challenges along the way.
And he recognized
that it would have
been super great if the
WordPress platform would have
provided him with
the building blocks
that he needed to build
his WordPress that
does all the things
in a much easier way.
So in addition to our
work on AMP for WordPress,
our team focused this year
on devising and implementing
the integration of some
of these building blocks
into the WordPress
core platform, OK?
And we emphasize the
requirement of doing
that in a way that is seamlessly
integrated with how WordPress
worked in the first place.
So I would like to call my
teammate Weston to tell us more
where we are in this effort.
[APPLAUSE]
WESTON RUTER: Gracias, Alberto.
Yeah, Surma certainly did
build a WordPress theme
that did a lot of things.
And he had a service worker
that was installed by the theme.
And that service worker powered
things like offline reading
and background sync.
It facilitated smooth
page transitions
as you navigate around the site.
And while his proof of
concept was compelling,
he faced a lot of challenges.
And it was because WordPress
didn't allow for doing things
that he wanted to do.
But these challenges are
not unique to WordPress.
They are common to
other CMSes as well.
So there are a few
fundamental challenges
that needed to be addressed.
The first challenge
is that there
needs to be a central
API in the CMS
for generating a service worker.
Because there wasn't
this in WordPress,
the theme itself had to
generate the service worker.
And this is a problem
because as with Highlander,
there can only be one
service worker at a time.
Multiple service workers
could be installed,
but only one is active.
And so a CMS like
WordPress needs
to be able to generate that
service worker centrally.
The next challenge is that
writing service worker logic
can be complex and that the
CMS should provide abstractions
as a part of it that eliminate
a lot of that boilerplate code
that has to be repeated
over and over again.
And the last challenge,
as Alberto referred to,
is that WordPress extension
system, and other CMSes
as well, don't have sandboxing.
And so a theme or [? flagging ?]
can do things that make it
difficult to maintain
advanced capabilities like
the [? actual ?] model.
So we implemented
abstractions in WordPress
to solve these challenges.
And what we did is applicable
to more than just WordPress.
First of all, we integrated
the service worker API
into WordPress so that themes
and plugins can each include
their own service worker
logic and to be installed
by the single service worker
that is generated by the CMS.
But this is just the
base requirement.
There also needs
to be, as I said,
those abstractions
to make it easier
to generate the complex
logic that is needed
to power a service worker.
So our integration includes
Workbox out of the box so that,
as you've heard
about earlier today,
you can take advantage
of all the complex logic
for generating caching
strategies and other advanced
functionality, like background
sync, that are part of Workbox,
and so that you don't have
to reinvent the wheel.
And since WordPress
developers have historically
been PHP first developers, we
have included PHP abstraction
that allows you to write
PHP instead of JavaScript
so that you can
have a PHP call that
gets translated into the
equivalent in JavaScript.
To give you a sense for how
this API is used in WordPress,
in this first example, you
can see a caching strategy
being leveraged-- here,
staleWhileRevalidate--
to match any request that is
made to the AMP project CDN
so that it will be then served
from the cache while being
updated in the background.
And here, you can see a image
being precached by the service
worker and then served
directly from the cache
without hitting
the network at all.
And if these two examples
here look familiar to you,
then that is no mistake
because they're essentially
PHP versions of what you
would be doing otherwise
in JavaScript via Workbox.
But if there is no abstraction
in PHP for you to do that,
you can also hook directly
into the service worker
to add your own arbitrary
JavaScript to do more advanced
functionality, if needed.
So given these service
worker capabilities,
one common application
is the App Shell model.
And App Shell facilitates
those seamless page transitions
and offline interactions
that you often see inside
of native applications.
But making a App Shell is often
very difficult and challenging
to do in WordPress because
themes and plugins can
add absolutely anything to
the page, like I just said.
And so this, again, is where
the AMP plugin plays a key role
because it enforces those
constraints to make sure
that the content behaves in a
way that doesn't break the App
Shell model.
And AMP is also
specifically designed
to be embedded inside of
these kinds of experiences.
Here is the
demonstration that we
built that shows the
standard theme 2017,
with a nice spinning
logo for fun.
Keep watching that logo.
Notice as I open the Nav menu
and start clicking around,
the content is changing.
But the logo keeps
spinning and is unchanged.
The header Nav menu
remains expanded.
And you don't lose that
context as you navigate around
the site.
So it's a single page
application built in WordPress
using a standard
theme as the basis.
And we could do it just with
a minimal amount of code,
thanks to the foundation
that the AMP plugin provides,
and the AMP project as well.
You can look at the pull
request on the AMP plugin repo
to see more specifics
on how you can
get started on your own themes.
To give you a glimpse
of that, here you
can see the theme just has
to declare theme support
to enforce those constraints.
To make sure that everything
is available in AMP,
you have to make sure that the
whole theme is able to serve
every page in AMP.
So you add this to your theme.
Next, you indicate the
region in the template that
contains the content that
dynamically changes as you
navigate around the site.
And lastly, you
tell the AMP plugin
that you're opting
into App Shell.
And then that then causes
the AMP plugin to generate
the service worker logic
to precache the App Shell
and to add the JavaScript
to the page that will then
intercept the clicks, and
do the history management,
and all that.
And the bottom line here
is that the theme developer
doesn't have to know the
complexities of building
App Shell.
They just extend what is
already in the platform.
But a service worker is
applicable to more than just
App Shell.
It also is useful for other
advanced capabilities,
including offline access.
Often, if you've developed
a WordPress theme,
you're familiar with
the 404.php template,
which is used to serve a page
to the user when WordPress
can't locate the site--
the content that
you're trying to load.
And in the same way, we have
extended WordPress's template
system to introduce
an offline .php,
which will then be served
to the user when the browser
can't access the site.
And so they get that
nice branded experience
from the theme
without the dinosaur.
And to opt into caching pages
that you visited while online,
you can opt into that
staleWhileRevalidate strategy
for navigation
requests so that those
will continue to be available
when you go offline.
And lastly, service worker is
useful for commenting offline
as well.
So here, if I try to submit
a comment while online--
or while offline--
then the service worker
can intercept that
request and then replay it
when the user comes back
online via background sync.
And here, the
developer doesn't have
to do anything because it's just
part of the integration itself.
So with that in mind, I'll
pass it back to Alberto
to talk about the road ahead.
[APPLAUSE]
ALBERTO MEDINA:
Thank you, Weston.
This is so very good to see
all these things running.
And we certainly have
made a lot of progress
in the context of WordPress.
And other CMSes have done
also a lot of progress.
But we are still not
quite where we need to be.
So in the context of
WordPress, the unplugging
is available to you today.
You can download it
from the GitHub link.
So please download this
[INAUDIBLE] with your site.
We are going to continue
expanding this work,
integrating AMP content creation
into WordPress, specifically
in the context of Gutenberg.
That is the new editing
experience in that platform.
In the area, you know, the
integration of PWA, the service
workers, and all the PWA
capabilities into WordPress
core, we have made
a lot of progress.
Right now that functionality
is available in the form
of a feature plugin that you
can also download and experiment
if you are a
WordPress developer.
And we are going to continue
working with the WordPress
ecosystem to help them to
integrate these technologies
into their work at all levels.
Now, one aspect that we are
working that is very exciting
is enabling content creators
to create content easily,
taking advantage of new powerful
format, such as AMP Stories.
As you can see in this
example, AMP Stories
is a mobile-focused format for
delivering rich information
in terms of visually rich
and tap-through stories.
We are building an
AMP Stories editor
for WordPress, which
is also integrated
with Gutenberg, the new editing
experience of WordPress.
To give you a glimpse of
where we are in this work,
these that you see here is
all the Gutenberg editing
experience.
And the good thing
about Gutenberg
is that everything
corresponds to a blog.
And that design premise
lends itself very well
to create AMP Stories that
also form my component.
So the goal of the editor is
to allow users to manipulate
all the components
of an AMP Stories,
control the
parameters, and so on.
We want powerful content
formats like this
to become available
across all CMSes.
And one interesting
development that is happening
is that Gutenberg
is being imported
to Drupal, which is another
popular open-source CMS.
and this is great
because then they
are going to be able to take
advantage of this editor
right away.
So much more on this
will be coming next year.
So stay tuned.
So to conclude, I can say that
the CMS space is moving forward
steadily along the
progressive web road.
Google is working and
supporting many of CMS platforms
to help them advance
in this path.
And we are seeing excellent
results on some fronts.
Here, we have some examples.
Drupal, which I mentioned, is
another popular open-source
CMS.
Their developer communities
is working on the AMP and PWA
modules.
They are available in-site.
So they are working
on enhancing them.
Magento, which is a popular
e-commerce platform,
they are releasing
Magento 2.3 this month.
And that release
includes PWS Studio,
that is a set of
guidelines and tools
to be able to create awesome web
experience in their platform.
Adobe Experience Manager,
which is a popular CMS
in the enterprise arena--
they have allowed the
creation of and publishing
of single-page applications
directly from the page editor.
And they are working on also
providing service worker
integration natively in their
platform early next year.
At the end we have EC-CUBE.
That is one of the leading
e-commerce platforms in Japan.
They are working with an agency
that is called [INAUDIBLE]
on an AMP plugin that would
also enable the creation of AMP
content on their platform.
So we want to extend
special thanks
to XWP, which is an excellent
WordPress agency that
has been partnering with us.
And they have made
awesome contributions
in the areas of bringing
AMP and PWA technologies
to the WordPress platform.
With that, I want
to say thank you.
And stay tuned for more progress
coming soon to a CMS near you.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]