[MUSIC PLAYING]
GRAY NORTON: Good
morning, everyone,
and welcome back from the break.
It's true.
My name is Gray.
And I don't think
my parents could
have known when they named
me all those years ago
that my hair would
prematurely match my name
or that I would be
a valid CSS color.
So I give them a lot of credit.
So I'm the engineering manager
for the Polymer Project
at Chrome.
And my team focuses mainly on
web components, and libraries,
and tools to help you use them.
But we're involved in
some other stuff, too.
And today I'm here to talk about
something a little different.
Or maybe we'll just stand
here, and look at my picture.
[CHUCKLES]
So shockingly, we're going to
be talking about performance.
As you may have
noticed, we're a wee bit
obsessed with that topic.
And by now, you've already heard
about speed tooling, and best
practices for doing
everything faster,
from loading, to rendering,
to responding to user input.
But for the next
half hour, we're
going to drill in on something
a little more specific.
And that's a proven pattern for
improving performance that we'd
like to see more of on the web.
[INAUDIBLE] mentioned
in yesterday's keynote
that today's web
platform is really
a high-performance machine.
And it's way faster in
almost every way than it
was even a few years ago.
But there are still some
surefire ways to slow it down.
And one of those ways is just
trying to render too much.
Especially on low-end
mobile devices,
you can bring
performance to a crawl
by piling on too much DOM.
And sadly, there are key parts
of the rendering process,
like styling and layout, that
just take longer the more nodes
you have in your page.
So for a certain class
of performance problems,
the best thing you can
do to speed things up
is to lighten your
load, minimize
the number of DOM nodes you have
on the page at any given time.
And there are various ways
to do this, of course.
But one of the simplest
and most effective
is to adopt a pattern
called virtual scrolling.
So for the last several months,
a couple of members of my team
have teamed up with some
of our Chrome colleagues
and some other folks inside
and outside of Google
to explore what it
might look like to add
first-class virtual scrolling
support to the web platform.
Today I'd like to share what
we've come up with so far.
It's early, but we're
pretty excited about where
the project is headed.
We'll start with a
quick introduction
to what virtual scrolling
is and how it's currently
being used on and off the web.
And then we'll take a closer
look at the performance
problems we're trying to
addressing, seeing firsthand
how too much DOM can impact the
responsiveness of your pages.
Next, we'll talk briefly about
the approach we're taking,
and we'll show you what
we've come up with so far.
And then finally, we'll
look ahead to what's next
and how you can get involved
if you're interested.
So without further
ado, let's see what
virtual scrolling is all about.
For the sake of
comparison, first we'll
look at ordinary scrolling.
So the blue box here
is our viewport.
And as you can
see, as we scroll,
the document moves behind the
viewport revealing content
further up or down.
But notice that all the content
was present from the start.
The only thing that
changes is what we see.
Now here's the same page
in a virtual scroller.
As you'll see, only part of the
content exists on the document.
As we scroll, nodes are
dynamically added and removed
keeping just enough
to fill the viewport.
Nodes is an obvious
one at load times,
since we only need to
render one screenfull.
But as we'll see, virtual
scrolling actually
also improves
performance in other ways
that might not be as obvious.
So when does it make sense
to use virtual scrolling?
It's clearly a natural
fit for anytime
you need to display
a lot of data
in a list or table
form-- for example,
like this address book.
And also, it's an
obvious call for content
feeds in cases like
social media or messaging.
But feeds have started showing
up in less traditional places,
too.
So some publishers have
started stitching together
articles in a way
that takes advantage
of the low friction
of scrolling.
And this may not look like your
garden-variety infinite list.
But nonetheless, it's
absolutely a case where
virtual scrolling can help.
And for that matter,
we actually think
there's a strong
argument to be made
for looking at virtual
scrolling in cases beyond lists
and feeds.
A single piece of
long-form content,
like this Wikipedia
article, might easily
contain tens of
thousands of nodes.
And the same techniques
that we use for lists
can also help us keep
the weight of documents
like this under control.
So virtual scrolling isn't
a new idea, of course.
It's widely used on
native mobile platforms.
In fact, both iOS and
Android put virtualized views
front and center in
their SDKs, making
this one of the
first concepts you
learn as a new developer
on one of those platforms.
And this is a big part of
why native mobile apps tend
to feel fast.
A basic native view is actually
heavier than the equivalent
chunk of DOM.
But the mainstream use
of virtual scrolling
on platforms like these
helps keep performance line.
Now you might be thinking,
virtual scrolling
isn't new to the web, either.
And you'd be right.
There are popular and effective
virtual scrolling solutions
for all the top
frameworks, including,
among others, react-virtualized,
and its younger sibling
react-window, the
virtual-scroll-viewport
in the Angular Material CDK,
and the view-virtual-scroller
library.
But these solutions
are currently
getting by without much
help from the web platform.
So in the age-old tradition
of paving cow paths,
we asked ourselves,
what might it
look like for the web to offer
first-class virtual scrolling
support?
How could we make things better?
And we came up with a few ideas.
First, virtualization
generally means
you can't link to locations
within the same document
since the browser can't scroll
to a node that's not currently
on the DOM.
Now, this may not be an
issue for many use cases.
You don't see a lot of links
between address book entries,
for example.
But in other cases,
it is a big deal,
and it breaks a fundamental
feature of the web.
And there's a similar problem
with the browsers Find
in Page feature,
which only sees text
if it's present in the DOM.
And then there's
search friendliness.
Since virtualized content
is added on the fly,
it's not generally visible
to search engine crawlers.
And again, this isn't
relevant for every use case.
But we'd love to
get the performance
benefits of virtual
scrolling without sacrificing
indexability.
Finally, and maybe
most importantly,
we'd like to see
if we can greatly
increase the amount
of virtualization that
happens on the web by adding
platform-level support.
While you could do it today,
virtual scrolling on the web
is basically a fringe feature.
You have to discover
you need it,
and then you have to jump
through some hoops to get it.
We'd like to put it
front and center--
the way it is in mobile SDKs--
making it easier to
discover and easier to use.
OK, so we've talked about
what virtual scrolling is
and why we're interested in
adding it to the web platform.
But to really understand the
nature of the performance
problems we're trying
to solve, it'll
help to look at some examples.
Since problems are the
worst on low-end devices,
we'll use a typical Android
Go phone for this exercise.
So I actually recorded a bunch
of real-world interactions
for this talk.
But I wasn't super happy with
the quality of the recording.
So I ended up creating dramatic
reenactments in Dev Tools
with CPU throttling turned on.
But what you'll see
here is representative
of the performance
on a real device.
And I'd be happy to show
you on the device itself
if you come find
me after the talk.
OK, so first, we'll look at
how the size of the document
impacts rendering
and what that means
for responding to user
interactions and content
updates.
So I created a simple
example to demonstrate.
It's a bit contrived, but it
exercises the browser engine
in the same way as
the real pages do.
So this mocked-up content feed
has just five items in it.
And it performs pretty well.
You'll see it has advanced
features like a dark mode
and a compact layout mode.
And these are all made just
using standard CSS techniques
changing classes.
And then lastly, we
have this slider here,
which lets us increase or
decrease the size of the items
by changing the base font
size in the document, which
is a technique that many
of you have probably used.
And layouts or the
items themselves
are based on [INAUDIBLE] so
that the whole thing scales.
As you can see, this
performed pretty well.
But again, it's only five items.
So let's see what
happens if we bump up
to 50 items on our feed.
So I'm scrolling here to
show there's more content.
But don't focus on the
scrolling performance.
We'll talk about
that in a minute.
For now, we want to focus
on the other interactions.
You'll notice I added
a jank indicator.
So the screen flashes red
when rendering gets slow.
And we're not too
bad here at 50 items
still, although there are
noticeable delays for the mode
switches.
And then you'll see
there's some sluggishness
as we start moving the slider.
But where we really
start feeling the pain
is when we get up to
500 times or more.
So the lagginess
in this example is
going to be impossible to miss.
So you'll notice
that, when we go
to dark mode or compact mode,
there's a very noticeable lag.
And the slider is going
to be virtually unusable,
it's so slow to update.
If anything, it
actually feels worse
on the real phone than this.
So again, this example
is a bit contrived.
You may not do exactly
this on your page.
But the effects it
illustrates are very real.
When you're rendering
any content on your page,
whether it's in response to user
interactions or changing data,
it gets much slower as
your document gets bigger.
And on devices like this,
it can kill your page.
So let's jump ahead of
it, and see how much
virtual scrolling might help.
So this is exactly
the same page with
our work-in-progress
virtual scroller swapped
in for the scrolling region.
And we've bumped all the
way up to 5,000 items.
But of course, only a
small effect fraction
are actually in the
document at any given time.
And as you can see,
we're pretty much back
to the same performance we had
in our original five-item list.
And this is essentially how it
feels on the phone, as well.
And remember, this is a very
low-powered Android Go device.
Next, let's see how virtualizing
might help us that load time.
So a quick caveat about this--
load time performance, how
quickly we get something
on screen, how quickly
we make it interactive,
depends on a lot of factors.
And virtual scrolling doesn't
directly impact many of them.
But to the extent that styling
and layout are slowing things
down at load time, virtual
scrolling can definitely help.
So being the big web
nerds that we are,
we'll use the single-page
HTML spec doc as an example.
So this thing is massive,
somewhere on the order
of a million words, I'm told.
And it's notoriously
slow to load.
So on my Android Go device,
with a "good but not great"
network connection-- because
I'd gone over my data allowance
for the month--
it took about seven seconds
to get something on screen.
So for comparison, we've
built a virtual scrolling
version of this page out of
duct tape and baling wire.
Basically, it loads the original
dock into a hidden iframe.
And then it populates
the virtual scroller
as the nodes stream
into the iframe.
And you wouldn't build
a real thing this way.
But it's an
interesting test case.
And it illustrates the impact.
So as this visualization shows,
we got something on screen
much faster--
just over three seconds
instead of seven--
and it actually gets
even better from there.
The original version on
this Android Go phone
was suffering from scroll
jank for well over a minute
after I started loading it.
Whereas, the virtual scrolling
version is usable right away.
As you scroll,
there's occasionally
a delay as it updates.
But unlike on the
original version,
you're never sitting
and waiting for seconds
while the screen is locked up.
OK, so before we move
on from performance,
one quick word about
scrolling performance--
because it seems a little
weird not to talk about that
in a talk about scrolling.
So because scrolling
is driven by the GPU,
even on our low-end
Android Go device,
you actually get pretty
decent scrolling.
It scrolls at a
reliably high frame
rate that actually looks
really good at normal scrolling
speeds.
But when you scroll quickly,
something funny happens.
The screen blanks out,
goes completely white
for long periods of time
while the rendering pipeline
catches up.
And this actually gets worse
as the size of the document
increases, just like
the other performance
problems we've been looking at.
So I did salvage one of my
original on-device recordings.
And we'll look at it here.
Our virtual scroller,
it turns out,
significantly reduced
the blanking problem.
It happens much less frequently.
And when it does
happen, the renderer
catches up much more quickly.
The trade off is that scrolling
is mildly but noticeably less
smooth overall.
As you would expect,
doing JavaScript layout
on a CPU-challenged
device like this
does impact the frame rate.
But as you can see
from the video,
it's a very good experience
nonetheless, even
on this low-powered device.
OK.
So we know what
virtual scrolling is.
We know why we want to
add it to the platform.
And we've seen firsthand
why we need it.
We see the performance issues
we're trying to overcome.
So I want to talk for a
moment about the process
that we're going through.
Because it's actually not
that common in recent years
for the web to add new
high-level features.
And so we had a bunch of things
that we really want to do--
and treat this
sort of as a Guinea
pig for how we might add
to higher-level features.
We'll start with some
basic principles.
Anytime you're
building something
in the web platform itself,
as opposed to in user space,
it's important to get the
very basic use cases right.
Because web APIs live forever.
And it's much more important
that we do the simple stuff
right.
So with that in mind,
we wanted to make sure
that we learned from prior art.
There's obviously virtual
scrollers on other platforms
and plenty of good work
in the framework space.
As I said, we want
to make it simple.
We want the feature
to be easy to use.
As much as possible,
we want you to be
able to create web
content that you just
happened to put in
a virtual stroller,
as opposed to picking
up a brand new API
and thinking
fundamentally differently
about the way you build stuff.
Make it work-- it
sounds trite, and it is.
But what I mean by this is
everything needs to work.
We talked about links.
We talked about finding page.
It's critical that
accessibility works.
We want tapping from
item to item to work.
And of course, it
needs to be fast.
After all, this is a performance
problem we're trying to solve.
OK.
The next thing we want to do
is we want to embrace layering.
And we'll talk a little bit
more about what we mean by that.
Nicole actually mentioned
this in the keynote.
One of the important things we
want to do out of this process
is identify and implement
any lower-level primitives
that the browser may
be missing in order
to support this
high-level use case.
We also want to
enable this thing
to be used right out of
the box, much like you use
a vanilla HTML and JavaScript.
We don't want you to have
to pick up a framework
to do a virtual scrolling.
We'd like you to be able to use
it on the web platform simply.
But with that said,
we also want to give
frameworks and libraries
a solid base to build on.
And certainly, the
low-level primitives
are things they can use.
But ideally, we'd like
the virtual stroller
itself to be something that they
can take, in whole or in part,
and layer features on top of
for their own virtual scrolling
solutions.
And as I mentioned,
this is all really--
with the idea of
blazing a trail.
We think that there's a lot of
room to improve the developer
experience and the user
experience of the web platform
by adding some high-level
features in coming years.
And with that in mind, we
want to use virtual scroller
as sort of a lens
or a testing ground
for us to examine what it means
to add new high-level features.
And so we'll talk about
some of these things
as we look at the
virtual stroller.
So with those
principles in mind,
we sat down to do our homework.
And the first thing
we did was we set up
what we called at that time
the infinite list study group.
And we basically had
a bunch of people
from across Chrome
who would get together
once every couple of weeks.
And each time, someone
would take the homework
of looking at a particular
virtual scrolling solution
and reporting back.
And we would discuss it.
And we'd learn about what
was working and what wasn't.
And we documented all
this here on GitHub.
Once we'd done that
for a while, we
came up with a set
of requirements,
and it was time
to start building.
Now I don't know what this is.
I think it's molding
or something.
But it looks like something
I'd really like to build.
So I put it on the slide.
And we have the same sort of
love for virtual scroller.
So once we started
implementation,
we did that on GitHub, as well.
And one of the things
you'll notice here
is that virtual
scroller is being
implemented in JavaScript.
And this obviously is sort
of unusual for something
that's under consideration
for a web platform API.
It's not typically how
we build platform APIs.
But this gets to the
layering concept.
We wanted to make
sure that we didn't
reserve any special powers
in adding these features.
And one of the best
ways to do that
is to develop things
on the same environment
that framework and app
developers develop in.
So the next important
thing about the process
is we wanted to be
in constant dialogue.
We talked about the fact
that we're doing these things
out in the open and GitHub.
But also, we've been
talking to people all along.
So we've been talking to other
browser vendors about the ideas
behind virtual stroller
and the principles
that we're trying to look at for
adding new high-level features.
We've been talking to
framework and library authors.
So along the way, we've talked
to members of the Angular team
who were working on the
Angular Material stroller.
We talked to the AMP team.
We've talked to members of
the Ionic team who are working
on their own virtual stroller.
And we've talked
with Brian Vaughn,
who's the author of
react-virtualized
and react-window, as well.
And we also have very active
discussions going on in GitHub.
So it's important to us that
this process be carried out
in the open and with the
input of the community,
including frameworks.
OK.
With that process as
backdrop, let's go ahead,
and look at what we've built.
So this is that example
we were looking at before.
And I show it here
in Dev Tools just
so you can see, as
we scroll, there
are just a few items in
the DOM at any given time.
And when we scroll, you'll
see them cycle in and out.
And so, even though we
have a list of 5,000 items
here, at any given
time, we're only
laying out, styling, rendering
a very small number of them.
And as you can see,
the virtual scroller
itself is a custom element.
And let's see how
you would actually
use that in vanilla style.
So starting from a
blank slate here,
the first thing that
we're going to do
is we're going to use the
browser's native module
loader to import this.
Now this is also a
new concept that we're
trying out as part
of the way we're
thinking about
higher-level APIs.
Typically, browser APIs are
sort of baked into every page.
You may use them.
You may not.
But there is a memory impact,
and the size of the browser
is impacted.
We'd like to explore
a pay-as-you-go model.
And so we already have, in
the form of the module loader,
a way to dynamically load
libraries and code at runtime.
And so we're using that here.
And you can see we have a
proposed syntax for requesting
something that would be part
of a standard library provided
by the browser.
And I won't go into
the details here.
But you can read about it.
So once we've
imported it, we just
put the virtual scroller
tag in our HTML document.
And this is what you get
without doing anything more.
You can see the virtual
scroller has a default
size, much like for an iframe.
And so it's not
doing anything yet.
Let's make it do something.
So first, ordinary querySelector
to find the virtual stroller.
We're just going
to fetch some data.
And then here's the first
bit of virtual scroller API.
It's an item source.
You can assign this
in an ordinary array,
as we've done here.
And then we'll call
our async function.
And we get that, which probably
isn't exactly what we want,
either.
So we wanted the
virtual scrolling
to do something by default.
And so what it does
is it just takes the
item, and it tries
to render it into the item.
And in this case, it's a string.
And it doesn't look very good.
So let's fix that.
So the next bit of API is
this update element hook.
So here we're basically just
going to take the contact name
and put that in
the text content.
And there we have something
that looks much more useful.
So just a few lines of code,
vanilla HTML, and JavaScript,
and we have a virtual scroller.
So let's take a look
at one more example.
You notice the virtual
scroller initially was empty.
And by default, it will just
create a div for each item.
You can actually override that.
In addition to the
update element,
there's a create element
hook, and you can give it
any kind of DOM you want.
But you can also put a template
inside the virtual stroller.
And whatever is
there will be what's
instantiated for each item.
So I'm going to go ahead.
And in my update
element function,
I'm going to assign the image.
And then lastly, I'm
going to specify that I
want a vertical grid layout.
So out of the box, it supports
vertical, and horizontal,
normal, and grid layouts.
Layouts are actually
pluggable under the hood.
It's TBD whether that
gets exposed in the API
as it eventually ships.
OK.
So as I mentioned, we're
taking a layered approach.
We're not building fancy
features like custom headers
and things in.
But it is important to us
that these things work.
Because again, we want layering.
So here's a case
where we have headers
interspersed with list items.
These are all examples that
you'll find in our GitHub repo.
So the other thing is, it's
important-- we want to support
various loading patterns.
So this is a common
one, where it's
sort of an infinite
scroll, and as you go,
each item gets loaded, and
you just keeps scrolling.
We also support the
other common pattern,
where you scroll to the bottom,
you explicitly ask for more.
So again, we're validating
that our basic constructs are
working for these use cases.
Fancier features-- if
you've ever built stuff
like this, worked
with the UX team,
inevitably they're going
to want fancy stuff.
So here's a proof
of concept that
shows that things
like swipe to dismiss
can work with this
virtual scroller, as well.
OK.
So we mentioned that
we thought there
would be some missing primitives
that we might discover.
And we think we found one.
Specifically, it's
called invisible DOM.
So you remember our
earlier examples.
In this one, you'll see it's a
lot like the virtual scroller,
except instead of
actually getting rid of
and adding nodes, it's basically
just making nodes invisible.
Invisible DOM is
in the document,
much like a display
none element But it's
different from display none,
in that it can be linked to
and it can be found by the
browser's Find In page.
And so here's an
example, where we
have non-traditional virtual
scroll type of content.
This is a document,
much like you
might find in Wikipedia or
a long-form news article.
And you can see--
here it is.
We get a certain
way down the list.
And all of the sudden, there's
nothing highlighting over
in the window.
Because some of these
DOM nodes are invisible.
They're just not there.
And as we scroll, we'll
see that they're basically
being flipped to visible.
And so when the virtual scroller
is working with invisible DOM,
this is how it works.
So you'll see here,
we'll do some resizing,
changing orientation.
And you'll see that the
layout is preserved.
Again, this is just
ordinary styling and layout
on these items.
And virtual scroller works
with them out of the box.
This is what we were
talking about when we said
we wanted to make it simple.
We don't want you
have to think hard
about using a virtual scroller.
So what we're looking at here,
though-- is the cool thing--
its links.
And this is what invisible
DOM is making possible for us.
So when I click on
one of those links,
the DOM nodes that
it's linking to are not
even in the document yet--
well, they're in the document,
but they're not rendered.
And so you get an event on them.
And by default, the
browser will actually
flip visible and scroll to it.
But in the case of
a virtual stroller,
we're capturing that event.
We're scrolling to it.
But in the process
of doing that,
we're rendering all
the context around it.
So it's perfectly seamless.
To the end user who's
using invisible DOM
with a virtual
scroller, it's exactly
as if the entire document had
been rendered the whole time.
And I am just about out of time.
But I wanted to show you one of
the exciting things about using
invisible DOM with
virtual stroller
is that it means you can
actually put invisible content
directly in a document.
And we're talking with our
friends over in Search.
And the idea is that you'd
be able to effectively
have your content be
entirely indexable
but to benefit from
the performance
wins of virtual scrolling
by not having a render it
all on first load.
So very quickly, I'll talk
about the path forward.
Again, very early days-- but
very encouraging results.
What's next?
More invisible DOM integration.
We've really just
started exploring
how the two play together.
Because thanks to
some great work
from [? Raquina ?]
on our DOM team,
we've just had a working
version of it become available
very recently.
In fact, it's available behind
the flag in Chrome Canary.
We think there may be
additional primitives, as well.
We've talked about some.
I won't go into detail here.
But invisible DOM
is just the first.
Framework collaborations--
so from the start,
we've actually in the repo had
proof of concept integrations
with lit-HTML and with Preact.
And for this talk--
but I'd end up getting cut--
I did a basic react
integration, as well.
But it's very
early there, and we
haven't worked closely with the
frameworks on that specifically
yet.
More advanced use cases-- so
we saw some of those examples.
But there are others that
we have not gotten to yet.
Performance optimization-- it's
pretty darn fast right now.
But there actually hasn't
been intensive optimization
done on it yet.
And then importantly,
down-the-stack explorations--
so one of the first questions
we get when we talk about this
is, why doesn't the browser
just do this stuff better
in the first place?
Why do you need a
virtual scroller?
Can't the browser just do this?
And these are
discussions that we're
having not only externally,
but also internally.
And it's a long,
complicated story.
Browser layout is complicated.
And in much
The way that AMP
simplifies building pages,
virtual scroller
can simplify layout
by locking you into
a much simpler model.
And there are some wins there.
But that being said,
it's very possible
that we can also pursue
other types of optimizations
further down the stack
that get you some
of the same types of
benefits without even having
to go to a virtual stroller.
And those are certainly
things that we're discussing.
The standards
process-- so again,
we've been talking to other
browser vendors all along.
But it's very early for this
and other similar high-level
features.
And the list could go on.
So if you're
interested, I invite you
to engage with us on GitHub.
We have a very active set
of discussions going on
in the issues here.
And here is the GitHub
repo where you'll find us.
And with that, I've been excited
to show you virtual scroller.
I hope you're as
excited as I am to see
it come into the web platform.