[MUSIC PLAYING]
CHRIS WILSON: So
I am Chris Wilson.
I'm here with my
colleague, John Pallett,
who will be out in a minute.
And we're here to talk about
the next great platform,
the Immersive Web.
And this is actually not
running off my laptop,
so hopefully I won't
have any problems.
At least they won't be mine.
Now we talk about this
word immersive a lot,
and I want to define what I
meant by the immersive web.
And at this point, I think
pretty much everyone has heard
of virtual reality at least.
Hands up, who saw
"Ready Player One "?
That's actually a
really small percentage.
You should go see it.
It's a good movie.
It's good entertainment.
So it's totally just like that.
Well, not really,
but virtual reality
is all about immersing yourself
in a completely alternate
reality, putting what I refer
to as the reality blinders on,
completely replacing everything
you can see and usually here,
and immersing yourself in
this totally different world.
That world may be a game.
It can be like
visualizing a data set.
It can be a virtual workspace.
My kids like to play this game
where I put on a VR headset
and they see how
close to me they
can dance before I notice that
they're there, which usually
it's pretty close.
But certainly, when
I'm at my desk at work,
this is my favorite place
to go into VR, because it
masks everything off around me.
The sea of cubicles
isn't there anymore.
And you usually
experience virtual reality
through a tethered VR
headset, like a Vive or Rift,
standalone devices
like the Oculus Go,
or smartphone VR systems,
like Daydream View, Gear VR,
or Google Cardboard,
my personal favorite.
And any of these devices
end up using a combination
of head tracking,
screen display, optics,
and controllers to make
you feel like you're
present in a totally
different world.
Now, at Google,
we've been working
on exposing this to the web for
really quite a long time on all
these devices, from high
end desktop headsets
on Windows to a polyfill
that supports WebVR
on any smartphone in Cardboard.
Yes, even Safari on iPhones.
And, in fact, you may not
even have a VR headset.
You might not even have this
$0.29 worth of cardboard.
WebXR and the XR polyfill can
actually view VR worlds just
on a mobile device using the
accelerometer and orientation
API.
So you can look
around a 3D scene.
And this lets the users
look around your 3D world
even if they don't want to drop
their phone into a headset.
Now, in addition to bringing
VR to the web, we also--
my team actually works on
bringing the web into VR,
at least on Daydream devices.
Starting with Chrome
67, you can actually
launch a VR version of Chrome
inside the Daydream home
screen, and we put a
lot of work into making
browsing the traditional 2D
web a really great experience.
But, of course, the really cool
part is when the browser in VR
can be used to browse
immersive worlds.
You can hop back and forth
between the 2D web and VR
content that's hosted
directly on the web.
So this gives you a really
great easy experience
and really, actually,
totally immersive.
It's like you're just
navigating inside that world.
Now, having a browser inside
the VR world is so useful.
It turns out 83%
of Daydream users
also regularly use
the browser in VR.
This was something we
added on after the fact.
Daydream shipped
without a browser.
And now this is a regular
occurrence for most of them.
It shows how important
the content from the web
is, even when you're just
living inside a VR world.
But enough about virtual
reality for a second.
I want to talk about when
you don't want those reality
blinders on.
I actually like to
interact with my kids.
I want to be able
to see them and not
have them dance in front of me.
And the most exciting extension
of the computing platform,
to me, is the concept
of augmented reality,
not just overlaying AR stickers
and animated characters
or being able to drop virtual
objects into your reality.
The key to understanding
AR's potential
is that it's really about
the concept of your computer
getting to see, getting
to see a world around you,
interpret parts of it, find
surfaces, in the future,
recognize objects,
and then augment
that reality with virtual
bits of user experience.
Instead of trying to totally
replace your reality,
we really want computers
to just convincingly blend
virtual and real experiences.
Now, for AR, there
are some headsets,
like the Hololens,
the Magic Leap One.
There are projection systems to
display on real-world surfaces.
But most users will
probably first experience AR
like I did, using a
camera passthrough
experience on a mobile
device showing things
like AR stickers.
And the cool thing is, if
you think of the things
the web is really, really good
at, the long tail of software,
content, products you expect
from the web, the experiences
that users will
probably happily click
on but they wouldn't
necessarily install
on their devices, the
massive success of the web
as a commerce platform
is a huge, huge benefit.
You can start to see
how enabling developers
to build immersive
experiences that
are delivered in this
really ephemeral fashion
is a fantastic idea.
You don't have to install an app
to see how that couch is going
to look in your living room.
You don't have to install an
app to view an immersive video
trailer.
The ephemerality of the
web makes the ability
to do these immersive
experiences a fantastic match.
And our mission,
John's and mine,
is really to enable web
developers to break that plane,
break out of the
flat design world
that we've been
living in for so long
to enable these truly
immersive experiences.
And to enable that,
we really needed
to start with the
baseline, being
able to connect immersive
displays and render to them.
And that's where the
WebXR device API comes in.
This replaces the old WebVR API.
It evolves those concepts to
expose not just VR but also AR
functionality, and in true,
extensible web platform
layering.
This is really the
underpinning only.
This lets us connect to those
devices, render displays,
understand which
way they're pointed,
interact with controllers,
that kind of stuff.
And this is a really
broad multi-year effort
by a bunch of
different companies.
Google, Mozilla, Microsoft,
Samsung, Amazon, Oculus,
a whole bunch of others
as well have been
working on this for a while.
And this has all been developed,
by the way, in the W3C.
In fact, we have a brand new
immersive web working group.
I personally co-chair this with
my colleague, Ada Rose Cannon,
who's sitting right
down here in the front--
I just had to make her blush--
from Samsung.
And we're tasked
with taking this spec
to an actual final status.
And this is why we
created a working group,
because we feel it's super
important to actually land this
now and not just keep
talking about how
cool it could be in the future.
This really shows the
maturing of this API,
because it's moving
closer and closer
to becoming a final standard.
And, of course, we also
continue to incubate new ideas
in the immersive web
with the community group.
Now, if you want to experiment
with WebXR API today,
you can enable it with Chrome's
flags, with the about flags.
If you want to try
out AR scenarios,
you have to enable
this second flag.
That should be going
away soon, because we've
done some new mode work in the
spec to make that work, too.
We have a currently
running origin trial, too,
if you want to try to deploy
this out to normal users,
and, of course, if
you're willing to accept
the responsibility
of making changes
as the spec and our
implementation change.
Now, finally, I've
mentioned the WebXR polyfill
a couple of times.
And this is something
I wanted to give
a little more detail about.
This is a polyfill
JavaScript library
that's maintained by
the community group.
It helps developers in a
couple of different ways.
First, it offers a
JavaScript-only implementation
that works for VR scenarios
in any mobile browser using
orientation events.
So even mobile Safari,
with cardboard devices
or flat displays,
you can actually
get a WebXR implementation
just through JavaScript.
Secondly, if a browser does
implement the older WebVR
API, like Firefox did this
and Microsoft Edge did this,
it can actually build
XR on top of that.
And you get the hardware
speed of their former WebVR
implementation.
So you can instantly
make your WebXR content
accessible to a much wider range
of users with just one script.
Now, with that, I want to
bring out my colleague, John,
who's going to drill down
into the augmented reality
possibilities in
a bit more detail.
Thanks, John.
JOHN PALLETT: Thanks, Chris.
So let's talk a little bit more
about augmented reality or AR.
As Chris mentioned,
augmented reality
is largely about being
able to overlay information
over top of the real world.
And if you've tried
out AR stickers,
or if you put masks on
your face on a smartphone,
you've already seen
augmented reality.
And the reason for
this is that there
are hundreds of millions
of phones and tablets
out there right now that
support augmented reality,
and the number is growing.
And most of those devices
have web browsers,
which means there is a big
opportunity for web developers
here.
And the lowest
hanging fruit, really,
is the ability to add a new
experience to an existing 2D
web page.
So it doesn't require
an entirely new site.
You can add AR capability
to an existing 2D website.
There've been a
number of partners
that have been experimenting
with this using the WebXR
device API and turning
on the hit test flag
that Chris mentioned.
They're doing this in
Chrome Dev and in Canary.
And as one example, Plattar,
which is an augmented reality
platform that lets
businesses put
virtual objects
in the real world,
they've done a couple of demos.
And there's some
interesting ideas here.
On the left, you can see that
users can learn about a product
by getting information in
context on the product itself
rather than having to
go through data sheets.
And it actually saves
shipping demo units
to businesses that are
thinking about buying
machinery or heavy equipment.
On the right, you
can see that looking
at objects from different
angles has a lot of value,
in this case, for
fashion, and generally,
for shopping, but also for
education where students
can explore the
object or artifact
that they're learning about.
Now, this doesn't all have
to be in augmented reality.
You could do both of these using
a 3D model on your website.
But if you can put it
into the real world,
you get a better sense of
context as well as scale.
Now, what's
interesting, though, is
that, from a user
experience perspective,
there are a lot of
interesting things
to learn about
augmented reality,
particularly how
it fits on the web.
And it's a good reason to
start experimenting with it
now if you're thinking
about adding it.
So by way of example,
West Elm, who
sells home decor and furniture,
did some in-store testing.
And what they did was they
went to one of their stores
and they picked four
shoppers at random.
And they showed them a
prototype shopping website that
incorporated augmented reality.
Now this isn't a huge study.
It's four shoppers.
But they had some
interesting findings.
And they gave us
permission to share them.
So the first thing
that they learned
is with these customers, the
terms AR or augmented reality,
it's not really a
common vocabulary.
Basic terminology,
like view in your room,
is a better way of
telling users what to do.
But even then, without a visual
showing what's going to happen,
that text can really get lost
with everything else that
is visual on the site.
So what they're
looking at now is
ways to add both an icon and
text so that the user has
a call to action.
They know what to do.
One approach might be
to have a rotating 3D
model so that the
user understands, hey,
this is more than just
another image on the page.
The next thing they learned
is that users get confused
without clear directions.
You can see here that there's a
delay while the user is trying
to figure out what to do.
Do I tap?
Do I move my phone around?
What is this circle
on the floor?
I've never seen this before.
You have to actually guide users
to the path of success here.
And West Elm is researching
clear directions as well
as things like progress
bars and loading indicators
so that users don't
get lost, and they
can see how to get to the
point that they're actually
placing furniture or an
object into the real world.
After that, once participants
successfully placed an object,
the most common
request was the ability
to move it or spin it or even
remove it from the scene.
The original placement wasn't
always where they wanted it to.
It wasn't always clear
to users how they
could do that, in this case.
Another thing that they heard
from their test subjects
as well was that
getting validation,
that the size of the virtual
object matched the real world,
would also be helpful.
Because if you're
shopping for furniture,
you want to make sure that
it fits into the space
that you have.
So from that
perspective, showing
some real-world dimensions
with the model could help.
And finally, there
was some feedback
on how real the assets looked.
And now this study was
particularly unique
because West Elm was
doing it in-store.
And so they had the opportunity
to put the virtual object right
next to the physical object
and get real shopper feedback.
Generally speaking,
the feedback on realism
here was only about 6 out of 10.
And you can see
clearly that there are
differences between the two.
So West Elm is looking at how
to handle typical lighting
scenarios and also make
sure that the shadows
underneath the object are a
little more pronounced and more
detailed.
So the key message
here really is
that there's a whole lot of
things that you can learn.
There's a lot of
streamlining going on here.
And fundamentally,
augmented reality on the web
has some differences from
apps where somebody might
be installing an
augmented reality app,
and so they're discovering it
in a completely different way.
Despite those
challenges, I think
a telling finding
from this study
was that three of
the four participants
said they would absolutely,
10 out of 10, use AR,
once they knew what
that term meant,
to do furniture shopping.
Now, if you're like
me and you grew up
with commercials talking about
three out of four dentists
recommend this
toothpaste, you probably
all wondered, what does
that fourth dentist think?
Does it rot teeth?
And the answer here
is actually maybe.
So three people absolutely.
One person maybe.
I personally visualize
that as these
are people shopping for
home decor, and they said,
would you use this?
And they're like maybe.
I'm here to buy a couch.
But I don't actually
think that's how it went.
But the point here is that
three people said absolutely.
Pulled from random, three
people said absolutely.
It's a strong signal.
It's also consistent
with what we've
heard from partners
and users who
see value and be able to
visualize 3D objects ideally
in the real world.
So if you're thinking
about experimenting this
and you're thinking about
adding this to your website,
let's talk a little bit about
how you can build things.
Chris mentioned the flags you
can enable a little bit earlier
in the presentation, but let's
talk about how you actually
add the immersive experience.
So you could write
WebGL code directly.
And if you're doing
augmented reality,
that would be over top
of the camera feed.
That's one way you can do it.
Generally, we recommend
using a library to help.
For example, three.js
is a helper library
for 3D graphics
on the web, and it
takes care of a lot of the
heavy lifting for 3D geometry
management and rendering.
And it makes it
so you don't have
to work with WebGL directly.
So let's look at an example
of how three and WebXR can
work together.
We're not going to cover the
whole process of creating
a WebXR session
and doing all that,
but we are going to look at
how a virtual object can be
placed into a real-world scene.
And we're going to do that
with a narrow use case,
in this case, putting a reticle
onto a real world surface.
For those who haven't
heard that term before,
a reticle is an indicator.
In this case, you can see
it as it moves around.
And it's typically
a user interface
construct so that the user
knows what they can do.
You saw some of this in the
West Elm screenshots earlier.
So what we're going to
do first in this case
is take the mesh for the
reticle, which, in our case,
is a flat circle, and we'll
add it to the three scene.
It's worth noting
we'd like the reticle
to be about half a meter wide.
And so it's worth noting
that the WebXR device
API locks the coordinate
system of the real world
to the virtual world.
And what that
means is that, one,
in WebGL or the virtual
space or in three,
one unit is one meter
in the real world.
10 units is 10 meters.
So in this case, if our
mesh is half a unit wide,
it means it'll appear as half
a meter in the real world.
Next, what we're
going to want to do
is actually render the
reticle over the camera
on real-world geometry.
But to do that, we need to
know where the real world
geometry is.
The WebXR device API
includes the capability
to do a hit test,
which is firing
a ray into the real world
and getting intersection
points with real-world
surfaces, so, for example,
taking a ray from my
eye, down into the stage,
and then getting the
intersection point of where I'm
looking on the stage, but
also the normal facing up,
so I know where the surface is
and what direction it's facing.
Now, in order to do
that, you need a ray.
And a good example of some of
the things three can help you
with is a ray caster function,
which I don't show here.
But it will let you get the
origin and the direction
of the ray that
you're going to fire
into the scene from the camera.
So we've already got that here.
And what we're going to do is
pass that into the hit test
API with WebXR.
And then what we'll do is
we'll take the return value.
We'll actually possibly
get a list of things,
because it might be
more than one object
behind the first hit.
We'll take the first
one, the closest,
and we'll convert
the position that we
got into a three.js
matrix, and then
we'll use that to set the
position of the reticle.
And at that point, you're done.
The reticle is now positioned
so that it will render directly
over the real-world object that
was detected from that ray.
Now, it's worth
reiterating that this
works because the virtual
coordinate system matches
the real world one.
And obviously, I skipped
over a lot of steps here,
but the point really is that
you can combine frameworks
like three js with WebXR.
And it's fairly straightforward
if you know 3D programming
basics.
But some of you might not
know 3D programming basics.
And the fact is
that if you've tried
to add a 3D model to
your site, you probably
know already it's
not super easy.
3D models can be pretty complex
both to read and to display.
We saw that, even in
the West Elm example,
there were user
experience considerations.
If you're starting from scratch,
you have to think about,
how do I want to rotate objects,
allow people to move them
around, and so forth?
And then there's also
responsive design.
If you want this to work
on mobile and desktop,
even if you're just
doing a simple model
and a turntable view, you have
to know how to handle resizing.
Do you need to display
a poster image on mobile
to prevent the download
of the 3D geometry
until the user
actually wants it?
For newer technology,
like augmented reality,
ideally, you'd be able to take
advantage and progressively
enhance and use some
of the capabilities
on different platforms
even if they're not
available in all browsers.
And as WebXR comes out and
starts moving to stable,
it's one more thing to learn.
It's one more thing to add.
So just know that if you've
experimented with this before
and you found it a little
bit tricky, you're not alone.
So to that end, the team has
been looking at this problem.
And we recently made public
an early version of a 3D
model viewer web component.
This is really,
really early, but it
does some things today to
make life a little bit easier.
And the reason we released it
early was to get your feedback.
To give you some context
for this web component,
there's three things
we're trying to do.
The first is we want
you to be able to add
3D models to your site without
having to learn 3D programming
or writing 3D code.
The second is we want it to
work well and responsibly
across browsers and across
different device form
factors with
progressive enhancement
to take advantage
of capabilities
on browsers where
they're available.
And then the third
goal is that as new API
ships, such as the
WebXR device API,
we want the component to
start taking advantage of them
so that you don't
have to keep up
to date with all of the
changes that are coming out.
So, like I said,
it is super early,
but we've made some progress.
And so I want to give
you a sense of what
the component can do today.
Let's run through
a few examples.
And this is the first one,
the simplest use case,
which is a static GLTF model.
For those who haven't heard GLTF
before, it is a 3D file format,
and it is a required
component of this model viewer
because it's a format that will
allow us to work across all
of the different browsers.
Here, you can see that if we
add a couple of attributes,
we can bring the model to life.
In this case, we set
the background color,
and we set it to auto rotate.
With the controls
attribute, we also
can allow the user to spin it
around and move it and take
a look at what's going
on, then look at it
from the back and the front.
We've also added a
poster image capability.
And you could delay the
loading of the model,
so you're not consuming
data on mobile,
if that's what you want to do.
And the attributes
are also dynamic.
So if you add a little script
which switches the poster
image back and forth, you
can animate it a little bit
to give the user a sense that
it's not just another image.
It's actually a 3D model
that they could click on.
It works in that way
similar to an image tag.
The component also handles some
forms of responsive design.
So you can see here that it
will scale up for desktop
and it will scale
down for mobile.
And it will manage the
staging and the lighting
and the rendering of
the model properly.
It can also manage multiple
instances on the same page,
so it will take care of
WebGL from that perspective.
And it uses
IntersectionObserver to make
sure it's not burning battery
and GPU when you can't actually
see the model.
Finally, the team is
experimenting right now
with some of the more
progressive enhancement
capabilities.
In this case, you
can see they're
experimenting with the WebXR
API and incorporating that,
so that you can add more
attributes to turn on AR
and do that across
different devices.
Again, this is really early.
The team is still
working on more features
for user interface and
responsive design features
to make it as easy as possible
to add a 3D model to a web
page.
Looking forward,
there's a lot we
can do on realism,
augmented reality use cases,
interactivity.
The whole reason
we made this public
is that we'd love
you to try it out,
and we'd like to get your
feedback in the GitHub.
So if this is something
you're interested in,
please do go to the
GitHub, take a look,
try it out, and then let
us know what you think.
And with that, we're done.
So we covered today a little
bit about the WebXR device API.
We talked about three.js.
And we touched briefly on this
new early release of the model
viewer web component.
If you're interested
in more, this
is the slide to
take a picture of.
The links are all on the screen.
If you're watching this
at home, you can rewind,
and you can check it out on
YouTube later, I imagine,
as well.
And with that,
thank you very much.
We thank you for your time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]