[MUSIC PLAYING]
TOM GREENAWAY: Good
afternoon, everyone.
I'm Tom Greenaway.
And I'm a developer advocate,
based in Google Sydney.
MARTIN SPLITT: And
I'm Martin Splitt.
I work out of the Zurich office.
And I'm a webmaster
trends analyst
which is just a fancy name
of being a developer advocate
for search and web ecosystem.
TOM GREENAWAY:
Today, Martin and I
are going to tackle this topic--
the best practices for ensuring
a modern JavaScript-powered
website is indexable by Search.
But what do we really
mean by this sentence?
Well, by best practices, we
mean what every developer
should know-- the techniques,
knowledge, tools, and approach,
and process.
And by modern
JavaScript-powered website--
I know it's a bit of a mouthful.
It means websites which use
modern JavaScript frameworks
for their front-end
and probably are
rendering their HTML in
JavaScript on the client side.
And they're typically,
like, single-page apps.
But this applies to any website
that uses front-end JavaScript.
And they might be, say,
powered with Ajax or web
sockets for content.
And lastly, what do we mean
by indexable by Search?
Well, by indexable, I mean
the content can be understood.
And by Search, we
mean Google Search.
But these rules-- they
apply to other web-crawlers
too such as, say, other
search engines or social media
services.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right, like
Facebook, Twitter, and all
the other wonderful ones.
TOM GREENAWAY: Exactly.
MARTIN SPLITT: Cool.
Cool.
So now that we know what
we want to address here,
how are we going
to split this up?
How are we going
to go through this?
Well, first things first, I
think it makes a lot of sense
to quickly go over how
Google Search actually does
the indexing and figures
out what content there
is in the web.
Then we're going to look
into something that,
as a web developer, I really,
really wanted all these years--
and we got that now--
the tools to help you all
and us to debug the things
that we are seeing.
And last but not least, we
don't want to just debug things
after they happen.
We want to make sure that we
are getting ahead of that.
And basically,
we're going to talk
about a few best practices--
TOM GREENAWAY: That makes sense.
MARTIN SPLITT: --for
indexable content.
Cool.
So with that out of the way--
[LAUGHS] it's good
that I have you here,
because I have got something
to talk to you about.
TOM GREENAWAY: OK, that
sounds a bit intense.
What do you--
MARTIN SPLITT: Don't worry.
It's not that intense.
It's just-- how do I put this?
I have a friend
who's called Marvin.
Let's call him Marvin.
And they are building
a single-page web app.
And they have done that.
And they have followed
most of the things
that you do these days,
like PWA and all that stuff.
But they have
issues getting users
to find their content online.
TOM GREENAWAY: I see.
MARTIN SPLITT: And
unfortunately, that's
not an isolated issue.
TOM GREENAWAY: Right, right.
So you ran a Twitter poll.
And other people are
encountering this as well.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah-- yeah.
I got a bunch of responses.
And it's like, so how can
I check if my stuff is
findable in Search?
Or hey, my stuff's not showing
up, but I don't know why.
And I think that needs a
little bit of a dive-in
and an explanation, right?
I guess that's a
good idea to do.
TOM GREENAWAY: Well,
there are a lot
of tools available for
debugging on Google Search.
But perhaps, before we get
into those, how about we just
go over how Google Search
sees and indexes the web.
[INAUDIBLE]
MARTIN SPLITT: I think
that's a fair point.
That sounds good.
TOM GREENAWAY: Well, here's a
basic diagram of how websites
were traditionally indexed.
Googlebot, our search crawler,
found pages, downloaded them,
and processed that content, and
then put them into an index,
and then performed
more crawling,
based on the links it found.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, OK.
But what happens in
the process step?
That seems to be where
the magic is, right?
TOM GREENAWAY: Well, when we
fetched a web page from a URL
and it was a traditional
website, that web page was
complete when it arrived.
And we called this the
rendering of the page
or the construction of the HTML.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right.
So when you say rendering,
you don't mean stuff
like putting the pixels
under the screen?
Or dealing with
the Dom transitions
and animations and stuff?
It's just, where does
the HTML go to construct?
Like, server-side rendering
versus client-side or hybrid
rendering.
TOM GREENAWAY: Exactly.
Traditionally, websites
were rendered entirely
on the server.
And then, any
JavaScript that was used
was probably just for
cosmetic purposes.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right.
OK.
Cool.
But now that we have
figured out that this
is about the dealing with
the constructed HTML,
it's no longer that way, right?
We have changed our
web architectures
quite substantially.
So what happens there today?
TOM GREENAWAY: In
the processing step?
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah!
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah,
it's a good question.
Basically, there's
now a renderer
inside the process step.
So more specifically, we
have a version of Chrome
that opens the content of the
page and runs some JavaScript.
And then it spits
out the final HTML.
But we also have a queue as
well, which is quite important.
And that leads into this next
point, which John Wheeler and I
revealed at I/O earlier
this year, which
is that, in a
nutshell, the rendering
of JavaScript-powered
websites in Google Search
is actually deferred
until Googlebot
has the resources available
to process that content.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right.
Deferred.
So what kind of timeline
are we talking about?
What's the delay?
TOM GREENAWAY:
Well, it could take
minutes or maybe an hour or
maybe even days or up to a week
before the render is
actually completed.
MARTIN SPLITT: A week?
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, I know.
MARTIN SPLITT: What?
OK, that's-- wow.
TOM GREENAWAY: It's
a bit of a shock.
I know.
But you have to understand that
the web is really big, right?
It's quite huge.
In fact, we found over 130
trillion documents on the web
so far.
[WHISTLING]
MARTIN SPLITT: OK,
that's a mouthful.
And this number
is two years old.
And I guess the web's growing.
So OK, I understand that.
Cool.
But is there anything
that we could
do to help the
crawlers a little bit?
If I remember correctly, when
I attended the session at I/O,
you said something
about dynamic rendering.
Is that something that
would come in here?
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, exactly.
So dynamic rendering
is a technique
that allows us to
short-circuit the rendering
pipeline by delivering a
service-side rendered version
of your normally client-side
rendered web-side
by rendering that
client-side JavaScript
on the server with a
mini-client-side renderer.
For example, a headless browser,
like Puppeteer, could be used.
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh, right, yeah.
That's pretty cool.
So how does that work in detail?
TOM GREENAWAY:
Well, here you can
see how a server identifies that
the device requesting the page
is a user browser.
And then it serves a payload
of HTML and JavaScript
that gets rendered
on the client, right?
So that's basic stuff.
But when a crawler like
Googlebot makes a request,
the server sends a
different payload.
And instead of sending the
HTML JavaScript directly
to the browser--
or in this case, the crawler--
we send what is normally
sent to the browser,
but we send it to the
dynamic rendering service.
And we run the payload
through that service.
So the dynamic
renderer then spits out
a completely statically rendered
HTML payload for the crawlers.
MARTIN SPLITT: Huh!
That's pretty smart.
OK.
TOM GREENAWAY: And to be
clear, that dynamic renderer
could be an external
service or it
could be running on the same
web server infrastructure.
MARTIN SPLITT: All right.
Yeah, that makes sense.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah.
MARTIN SPLITT: I guess,
for this kind of stuff,
you can use tools such as--
Puppeteer is one that
you mentioned already.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah.
MARTIN SPLITT:
But you could also
probably use Rendertron, which
is a higher-level abstraction.
Puppeteer is basically an
NPM module that you install.
And that remote controls
or programmatically
controls a Chrome
instance that runs
headlessly, which is great.
But I'd like something
more high level.
And I think Rendertron
steps in there,
where you basically just have
the server running, which
is a Rendertron server that
uses Puppeteer to steer that.
And you give it a URL to render.
And you get the rendered
static HTML back.
That's pretty cool.
OK.
It's fantastic.
I guess you can also
deploy that pretty easily.
I think there's
this thing called
Google Cloud Platform
that's probably
pretty easy to deploy too.
But I guess you can also deploy
it pretty much anywhere else,
right?
TOM GREENAWAY: Do
you have an example?
MARTIN SPLITT: I do have
an example actually.
So there's a NPM module that
is called the Rendertron
middleware.
So if you are using, let's
say, for instance, Express.js,
you can use that
as the middleware.
But what you're doing
here is basically just--
first step, you require it.
You need to get that
into your project.
And then what you're
doing is you basically
configure it to do the
right thing for you.
In this case, we want to
specifically jump the rendering
pipeline of the Googlebot.
Rendertron, by default, doesn't
do prerendering for Googlebot,
because the Googlebot
does run JavaScript.
But we want to get the
advantage here anyways.
So we can just use the
preconfigured and prebuilt list
of render agents that
they are rendering for
and add Googlebot in there.
And then once we have
that configuration ready
and have imported
it, we can go on
to actually use it in our
application middleware stack.
So we can basically point it
to the running server somewhere
and say, for all these user
agent patterns, prerender.
By the way, now that
I have got you here--
because you never respond to
emails timely, which is fine.
Neither do I-- no offense.
And Chrome Dev Sum
is a big event.
So this rendering does
cost a bit of resources.
So I'm wondering,
is there any way
to figure out what Googlebot--
like, what does Rendertron
really do to figure
out what's Googlebot?
And how can it
verify that is really
is Googlebot and not just
pretending to be Googlebot?
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, well--
MARTIN SPLITT: [INAUDIBLE]?
TOM GREENAWAY:
--the easiest way is
to do user agent sniffing
for the Googlebot string.
And here's an example
with the mobile user
agent for Googlebot.
[WHISTLING]
But you might want to do
this for other services
as well that you want to
serve prerendered content to,
like social media services.
And also, for Googlebot, you can
do, additionally, a reverse DNS
look-up, to confirm
that it really is
coming from the Google servers.
And like I said, this is
the mobile user agent.
So you can detect the
desktop user agent as well.
And that URL will give you a
list of all the different--
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh, cool.
TOM GREENAWAY: --user agents.
MARTIN SPLITT:
Right, that's nice.
That's [INAUDIBLE].
TOM GREENAWAY: Which
reminds me, actually--
I should sync with
John [? Muller ?]
and check if there are
new tools in Search
Console for this stuff.
Or maybe you can tell me.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, I was going
to say, why did you bring John
into this?
Come on.
TOM GREENAWAY: Sorry.
MARTIN SPLITT: I'm here.
I'm literally a
meter away from you.
Or I don't know how many miles
or foot or inches that is.
I have no idea.
But basically, we have a
bunch of stuff for you.
And I'd like to walk
you through that.
So you know the Google
Mobile-Friendly Test already?
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah.
MARTIN SPLITT: So this
is kind of useful.
It shows you if your
page is mobile-friendly.
It does give you a
screenshot of what
we are seeing in Googlebot.
And it's pretty easy to use.
You just paste
your URL in there.
But it does more than just that.
Because it also gives
you this, which is what
I always wanted to have.
And Googlebot does not render
what you expect it to render.
You get the JavaScript
log messages,
as you would get them
from the Chrome Dev.
TOM GREENAWAY: So
you can really debug
the JavaScript in the page.
MARTIN SPLITT: You
can really debug this.
And here's my
favorite-- we had this--
is it undefined
question earlier on?
Apparently, it is undefined.
And undefined is not a
function, which is unfortunate.
But that happens.
Also, do you know about
the new URL inspection tool
that we've got in
Search Console?
TOM GREENAWAY: I don't think so.
Can you remind me?
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, sure.
So if you have verified for
a property in Search Console,
you can basically
paste any of the URLs
that are belonging
to that property
into the Search Console
URL Inspection tool.
And you get, like, when we
crawled it, if it's on Google
or not.
And you have a bunch
of information.
And you can run
live tests as well.
So this blog post here is--
drumroll-- not on the index.
But that's fine-- whatever.
We also have something else.
It's actually a
pre-announcement that we're
going to make at
Chrome Dev Summit now.
TOM GREENAWAY: OK.
MARTIN SPLITT: So can we get
a little bit of a drumroll?
So we'll get the
live code editing
feature in Search Console.
TOM GREENAWAY: Oh, OK.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah.
TOM GREENAWAY:
What does that do?
MARTIN SPLITT: Fair enough--
yeah, OK.
So imagine you are
building a website.
Let's say, there's
an afterparty today.
So you built the website
for the Chrome Dev Summit.
And you want to check if
your structured data works
to get highlighted in
Search results, right?
You want to check that
as quickly as possible.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah,
that makes sense.
You want to be able
to iterate quickly.
And you don't want to have
to wait for deployments
from your [INAUDIBLE].
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, exactly.
I want a development cycle
that makes more sense.
So what you can do
is you can plot that
into this wonderful tool.
And here, we have an example.
We are using JavaScript to
create a script tag that
contains the structured data.
And we have all our
wonderful structured data
for the event here.
And then we can click on
the little Test Code button.
And what it gives us is this.
And we're like, yay!
Our event is available.
And this is a code
editor over here.
And what we see
over there is, it's
missing the performer
for the afterparty.
TOM GREENAWAY: Oh, wait.
That's a shame.
I think it's meant to
be the Chrome Dino.
MARTIN SPLITT: It's
the Chrome Dino.
So we should add this performer.
So what we can do is
we can go straight back
into the Code Editor and
click the button again.
And it live updates, as
we have retested our code.
So we can do all of this in
the browser in the single tool.
And I think that is pretty
fantastic really, right?
That's pretty good stuff
TOM GREENAWAY: OK, yeah.
That is definitely a neat way of
testing and trying our code out
and iterating quickly.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah,
but that's something
that Search Console
generally tries to do, right?
TOM GREENAWAY: Mm.
MARTIN SPLITT: So you have
this really nice flow.
So let's say, someone in
your company or agency
or wherever has access
to Search Console.
I don't have access to Search
Console as a developer,
normally, because I have so
much other things to worry
about really.
And then someone finds an issue
through one of the reports.
So how do they get
this information to me?
Well, one way of doing
so is, basically,
they can just go and see this
issue from the Reports page,
where-- there's a
bunch of samples here.
In this case, the content
is wider than the screen.
And in the second stage of
this, they can basically
just say, all right.
So our developers might
be an external developer.
We don't want to give them
access to all the data.
So we share this
particular issue with them.
And they get a link.
They don't have to
sign in or anything.
They can just use the
link that is shared here
to see what the
issue is, get access
to the documentation that
explains what the problem is
and how to fix it.
And then, last but not least,
when I, as a developer,
then go, I fixed this--
I have this under control--
we know that that's
often not true.
So what Search Console offers
us is this Validate Fix button.
So if I'm like, Tom, I gotcha.
I fixed this.
You or I can press
this button and go,
I got you in 10 minutes.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, right--
OK.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right?
TOM GREENAWAY: So it really
establishes a flow [INAUDIBLE]..
MARTIN SPLITT: It does.
It is really nice
workflow and works
across departments,
which I think
is pretty fantastic as well.
Yeah.
TOM GREENAWAY: Hm.
Yeah, that's nice.
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh--
TOM GREENAWAY: But
actually, there
is another addition
to our Dev tool.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right,
you were talking to me
about that earlier.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, exactly.
I'm sure everyone obviously
knows about Lighthouse.
They've been to the forum
space and they've seen the--
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, come on.
TOM GREENAWAY: --awesome
statue we've got there.
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh,
it's fantastic.
TOM GREENAWAY: But-- yeah.
What if I told you that
there are actually SEO audits
inside of Lighthouse?
MARTIN SPLITT: Huh!
TOM GREENAWAY: In fact, we've
got a few more coming soon.
So--
MARTIN SPLITT: Ooh!
TOM GREENAWAY: --basically, this
can automatically detect things
like whether your HTTP header
responses are accurate or not
and meta-tags as well-- like,
that you've got correct title
and description tags or that
you've got hreflang set up
correctly, if you're using
that for a localized--
MARTIN SPLITT:
Internationalization--
TOM GREENAWAY:
--international website.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah-- woo.
TOM GREENAWAY: And also,
descriptive link texts-- even
for anchors.
So if--
MARTIN SPLITT: Click Here.
TOM GREENAWAY: Exactly, you
want to avoid Click Here,
because it doesn't
really communicate
what is actually the thing
that you're linking to, right?
MARTIN SPLITT: Number five
is going to surprise you.
TOM GREENAWAY: And then
they're like, robots.txt.
And then the new
features we're adding
are, like, automatic detection
of the sides of tab targets
and the margin
around tap targets,
to make sure that they're
nice for users, and also
structured data testing, as
well, which you were just
talking about.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah.
Yeah.
TOM GREENAWAY: So
it's really great.
MARTIN SPLITT: It's going
to get more of that.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah.
MARTIN SPLITT: That's fantastic.
That's very good to see, yeah.
Cool.
All right, so I think,
from the tool side,
we have Lighthouse audits.
For SEO, we have
the Search Console.
We have the Mobile-friendly
test and the Rich Results
test with editing features.
I think we're pretty
good on that front.
But do you have any
recommendations,
in terms of best practices, that
I should tell my friend Marvin?
TOM GREENAWAY: Marvin--
your friend, right?
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, my friend--
no, I'm serious.
This is a friend of mine.
It's totally not me.
Any best practices that we
should recommend to them?
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, yeah.
Let's go through a few.
MARTIN SPLITT: OK, cool.
TOM GREENAWAY: Well, firstly,
it's important to know--
remember how I said
that Googlebot is
running like Chrome nowadays?
MARTIN SPLITT:
That is fantastic.
Finally, we have
a modern brows--
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah-- well,
actually, wait a second.
It is Chrome.
But it's not actually
the latest version.
So it actually runs Chrome 41.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right.
41.
It's not even 42,
the answer to life,
the universe, and everything.
It's just 41.
TOM GREENAWAY: It's
not quite there yet.
But Chrome is working on it.
[DEEP SIGH]
But seriously though, since
it's Chrome 41 and Chrome 41
was released in 2015, it doesn't
support all of the latest
features of modern browsers.
So for example, it doesn't
actually support ES6.
So the latest language
features aren't available.
And while it has
web components, it's
actually version 0 of the spec.
And another thing to note
is that it's actually
stateless, which I'll
explain in a little bit.
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh, OK.
All right.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah,
it's an interesting one.
I'll break it down.
For example, with this code, how
many ES6 features can you spot?
MARTIN SPLITT: Uh, a few.
TOM GREENAWAY:
That's a good answer.
Yeah, OK.
More than 0.
Yeah, exactly.
Now, we might forget
that some of these
are relatively recent features,
like advanced object literals
or const definitions, backwards,
and variable substitution.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah,
you use them every day.
Why--
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
So one way to deal with
this, if you need a solution,
is to use something
like Babel, which
allows you to transpile ES6
code down to ES5 automatically.
And you can easily compile a
set of files or a directory
and compile it into a
single file for serving.
And using presets, you can
also detect a minimum browser
version and use
that as a baseline.
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh, right.
TOM GREENAWAY: So you can
ensure that, like, ES6 features
and ES6 code go to browsers
that can support it.
And then browsers that can't
get the ES5 transpiled code.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right,
that makes sense.
OK.
TOM GREENAWAY: And
now, while Chrome 41
does have web
components, it's actually
an older version of the spec
than you're probably used to.
So after Chrome 41
shipped, several features,
such as Custom
Elements and Shadow DOM
actually had some changes
made to their specs.
So depending on exactly which
features you use in version 0,
it might be very
simple to migrate.
Or it might get
more complicated.
But the most important
thing is to be aware
that there are differences.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah,
there's differences in this.
Yeah, OK.
TOM GREENAWAY: And
lastly, this shouldn't
come as too much of a surprise.
Googlebot basically doesn't
really have any memory.
MARTIN SPLITT: Huh!
TOM GREENAWAY: And what I mean
by that is that, every time it
accesses a web page
or side origin,
it just always acts like
it's the first time it's ever
encountered that website.
And to achieve that, we
turn off a bunch of things.
So we don't have
service workers running.
So we don't have a
service worker cache.
And we don't have local
storage or session storage
and so forth.
So--
MARTIN SPLITT: It makes sense.
If you click on a search result,
that's like coming to that page
the first time.
So we want to make sure--
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, what is
the first-time user experience--
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah,
true [INAUDIBLE]..
TOM GREENAWAY: --when
you encounter it?
MARTIN SPLITT: Makes sense.
TOM GREENAWAY:
So, Martin, do you
have any suggestions for
how we can substitute
for some of these things?
MARTIN SPLITT: So
I think, if you
look at things like
the web components
and a few of these features,
like intersection, observe,
and all these things, I guess
polyfills is a good way,
once you've already
done your homework
and did the
progressive enhancement
or graceful
degradation at least.
But the problem with
polyfills, I feel at least,
is that there is a bit of a risk
to ship dead code to people--
like, give them a bunch of
stuff over the network which,
depending on where they are
and what plan they're on,
might be actually pretty
expensive and time-consuming.
So you want to reduce that.
And actually, I really like
this library called Polyfill.io.
So Polyfill.io basically
sniffs on the user
agent of the person requesting
or the browser requesting it.
So if the crawler comes
by and there's like,
ooh, this is a Googlebot
crawler, Chrome 41--
so I give them a bunch of
stuff that the normal user
on a more recent Chrome or
Firefox or Edge or whatever
doesn't need.
So basically, it tries to give
you the right amount of code
that you need to make this work.
So that's pretty
fantastic, I think.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah,
it's kind of cool.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah.
Is there any place where
I can figure out more
about these feature issues,
where, like, features
are missing in Chrome 41 that
are there in the modern one?
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, definitely.
If you check out
caniuse.com, it's
a great resource for
this sort of thing,
because you can check,
like, the features
across various browsers.
You can also specify specific
browser versions as well.
MARTIN SPLITT: Ah!
TOM GREENAWAY: So
you can say, hey,
what's different in
Chrome 41 specifically?
MARTIN SPLITT: Cool,
that's pretty nice.
TOM GREENAWAY: And
also, the golden rule
of any indexability and building
a website for search crawlers
and that kind of
thing is to just
make sure you test really
frequently as well.
MARTIN SPLITT:
Yeah, fair enough.
Yeah.
Test, test, test.
Fair enough.
Cool.
So going back to dynamic
rendering for just a second
and the tools discussion-- so
if I test my stuff and I figure
out, oh no, this feature is
really tricky to work around
and I want to not
change my code--
I guess I can use dynamic
rendering for that.
But I guess there's trade-offs.
And there's situations where
I shouldn't be doing that.
So what are the sites that
should, generally speaking,
look into dynamic rendering?
TOM GREENAWAY: Well, because the
rendering queue can introduce
some delay, if your site has
lots of frequently changing
content-- like a news publisher
or something like that
and you've got, maybe, breaking
news and articles that are
coming out and changing
very frequently--
you probably might want to look
into using dynamic rendering
to overcome those delays.
And if your pages use features
that aren't available in Chrome
41 and it's not possible to
work around those limitations,
maybe, in the short-term,
then using dynamic rendering
is a useful workaround until
either Googlebot catches up
or you have the
time to adapt that
in your own implementation.
MARTIN SPLITT: Right,
that makes sense.
TOM GREENAWAY: And
also, while Googlebot
is supporting JavaScript,
other crawlers might not.
So for example, if your site is
using social media interactions
a lot, those crawlers tend
to not run JavaScript.
So if I share a link and I'm
sharing it on social media
but I want a nice preview
card to be created,
it probably wants
to try and access
the image and the title and the
meta-description, or something
like that.
So if you're actually
using client-side rendering
for those things,
then you might get,
just, the variable templates
[INAUDIBLE] in the content.
MARTIN SPLITT: Ah, you use
an image, and it doesn't--
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah-- in the
preview, which would be bad.
[RASPBERRY SOUND]
So in order to get better
representations there,
you can also serve a dynamically
rendered version page.
MARTIN SPLITT: Cool.
Sounds pretty good.
TOM GREENAWAY: But
ultimately, dynamic
rendering-- it's a
powerful technique.
But it's still a workaround.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yes!
It's a workaround.
TOM GREENAWAY: So
Martin, do you have
any ideas on if we've got plans
to improve this on the Google
side?
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah.
Way to put me on the spot.
So I don't like to
make predictions
on that kind of stuff.
But definitely, the way that
our infrastructure is set up,
there is a bit of a gap
between when we actually
execute the JavaScript and
do the rendering and then
the indexing bits
and the crawling.
So we try to bring these
closer together, which
is an interesting
technical challenge.
And then, at the
same time, we are
trying to catch up with Chrome.
But we don't want
to just catch up,
because then we're going
to have the same frickin'
conversation in a few years.
Like, oh yeah, Chrome's
running version 70.
And everyone's
like, oh, when does
it get into three-digits land?
So we basically
work on a process
that we're, hopefully,
going to start very soon.
So I make no promises on when.
But we are working on
figuring out a process to stay
up-to-date with Chrome, so
that Googlebot does run with
the Chrome release schedule--
so that we are basically--
TOM GREENAWAY: That
would be awesome.
MARTIN SPLITT: --giving you
an Evergreen-- yeah, right?
That would be fantastic
if we could do that.
Yeah.
TOM GREENAWAY: And also
to shorten the [INAUDIBLE]
as well.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, exactly.
That goes hand-in-hand
really, because we
have to touch the rendering
infrastructure anyway.
So we might as well
do both things.
But I think we might get an
update quicker than we get
the two things together, but--
TOM GREENAWAY: OK, cool.
MARTIN SPLITT: --we'll see.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah.
MARTIN SPLITT: Cool.
All right.
So thank you so much
for all that talks
about how the indexing
works and bits and pieces.
That was pretty fantastic.
I learned a bunch of new stuff.
TOM GREENAWAY: Yeah, and I hope
this helps with Marvin as well.
MARTIN SPLITT: Marvin
is going to love
what I'm going to tell him.
I'm sure.
I--
TOM GREENAWAY: OK, yeah.
Well, thanks for
showing me all those
Search Console tools as well.
MARTIN SPLITT: Oh, yeah!
They are--
TOM GREENAWAY: They look great.
MARTIN SPLITT: --pretty fun.
Yeah.
TOM GREENAWAY: And if developers
need more support and help,
like Marvin, can they
go somewhere else?
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, so
I tried to get Marvin
to go to our documentation,
because the documentation is
expanding quite quickly.
And we have a bunch of core
documentation coming up
and good documentation
already there.
We have Webmaster Hangouts.
So you can pop by and
talk to us over a Hangout
and ask us questions
there as well.
They are recorded.
So if you want to go back
to one that has happened
and there was an
interesting question,
you can find it there as well.
We have what's called
the webmaster forum.
A bunch of fantastic
people are there
called product
experts, who are also
helping if there is anything
coming up with Search.
And last but not least, if
you've been to the forum space
before, we have a
Search Console booth
where you can try
our Search Console
and get stickers and stuff.
So definitely check
that one out tomorrow.
So yeah, that's a
bunch of resources.
TOM GREENAWAY: Awesome.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah.
TOM GREENAWAY: Cool.
Well, yeah.
Thanks, everyone.
MARTIN SPLITT: Yeah, cool.
Thank you very much for
staying with us for a moment.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]