[MUSIC PLAYING]
THOMAS NATTESTAD:
My name is Thomas,
and I'm the product
manager for WebAssembly.
ALEX DANILO: My name is Alex,
and I'm a software engineer
on Chrome OS.
THOMAS NATTESTAD:
And today we're
going to talk to you
about WebAssembly.
We're going to
start off by briefly
describing what WebAssembly is
and what you can use it for.
Then I want to show off some
of the amazing new features
that the WebAssembly team has
been working on to deliver
to you in this last year.
Then I'll showcase some of
the amazing applications
that have managed to
build with WebAssembly,
and our shipping and production.
All right.
So first off, what is
WebAssembly, actually?
WebAssembly is a new
language for the web,
and offers an alternative to
JavaScript for expressing logic
on the web platform.
It's important to note, though,
that WebAssembly is in no way
a replacement for JavaScript.
Rather, it's designed
to fill the gaps that
exist in JavaScript today.
Specifically, WebAssembly
is designed as a compilation
target, meaning that you write
in higher level languages,
such as C++, and then
compile into WebAssembly.
WebAssembly is also
designed to deliver
reliable and maximized
performance, which
is something that can
be difficult to get out
of JavaScript.
Most exciting,
though, is the fact
that WebAssembly is now shipping
in all four major browsers,
making it the first new
language to be fully supported
in every major browser
since JavaScript was
created more than 20 years ago.
All right.
So what can you
actually do with this?
Well, as I already mentioned,
because WebAssembly offers
maximized and
reliable performance,
you can now expand
the set of things
that you can feasibly
do in the browser.
Things like video editing,
complex application, codecs,
digital signal processing,
and many, many more
performance-demanding
use cases can now
be supported on the web.
Secondly, WebAssembly
offers amazing portability.
Because you can compile
from other languages,
you can port not only your
own applications and libraries
but also the wealth of
open-source C++ libraries
and applications that
have been written.
Lastly, and potentially most
exciting to many of you,
is the promise for
more flexibility
when writing for the web.
Since the web's
inception, JavaScript
has been the only
fully supported way
to execute code on the web,
and now with WebAssembly you
have more choice.
All right, so now that we
all know what WebAssembly is,
I want to jump in and show
off some of the new features
that we've been adding
in just the last year.
First off is source maps.
You likely all know how
important source maps are
when you're working with
something like TypeScript
or Babel, but it's
even more important
when you're trying to debug
your WebAssembly code.
Source maps let
you turn something
that looks like this into
something just slightly more
friendly, like this.
With source maps you can see
the specific line of code
where an error has
occurred and you can also
set breakpoints and have
the program actually pause
at the appropriate moment.
One of the big feature requests
that we've heard from users
is for better performance
when you're starting up
your application so that
your module can actually
get going faster.
And for that we've created
streaming compilation.
In the past, when you
wanted to compile a module
you had to wait for
the entire module
to be loaded off of the
network, and only then could
you move on and
actually compile it.
Now with streaming
compilation, you
can start compiling each
piece of your module
immediately, even before
the other parts have
finished downloading.
To show you what that
actually looks like,
here's a simple example where
we called a fetch function--
or fetch for a WebAssembly
Fibonacci module,
and then we just passed
that fetch promise directly
into WebAssembly.inst
antiateStreaming,
and it takes care of all
of this underlying bits
and pieces for you to
deliver this experience.
We did some profiling at
different network speeds
to see the impact of this.
We found that all the
way up until 50 megabits
per second network
speed, the network
was actually the
primary bottleneck,
and that the compilation was
done as soon as the module was
loaded.
It wasn't until you hit the
100 megabits per second speeds
that you actually needed
additional time past the time
it took to download the
module in order to fully
compile and get it going.
To make startup
time even faster,
the team built and launched
an entire new compiler
that we called the
Liftoff compiler.
This Liftoff compiler takes
the WebAssembly byte code
that comes down off of the wire
and then starts executing it
immediately.
The WebAssembly module is
then taken off the main thread
and optimized further by the
TurboFan optimizing compiler.
When TurboFan is done
optimizing the WebAssembly code,
it's then hot
swapped in directly
without any need for
explicit developer action.
Unity did some benchmarking on
the effects that Liftoff had.
On a benchmark where they tried
to load a very large game,
they found that it went from
taking seven seconds to load
the game to less than
one second, which
makes all of the difference
when you're waiting
to get into a game experience.
Probably the biggest
feature that the team's
been working on this year
is WebAssembly threads.
WebAssembly threads lets you
run fast, highly paralyzed code
for the first time
across multiple browsers.
It also lets you bring existing
libraries and applications
that use threaded code such
as Pthreads to the web.
This is such a big
feature that I'm actually
going to leave most of the
explanation to Alex later on.
But before I get
into that, I want
to show off some of the
cool new applications
that have already been building
and launching with WebAssembly
this last year.
First off is SketchUp.
SketchUp is a 3D
modeling software
that you can learn and
start using really quickly.
Unlike traditional
computer-aided design,
most people can learn
SketchUp almost right away.
SketchUp lets people draw
in perspective and then
push-pull things into 3D.
In no time, people can draw
and redesign a living room,
plan out a
do-it-yourself project,
or create and export a
model for 3D printing.
This app is a lot of fun and
you should all check it out,
which you can do right
now instantly, just
by going to app.sketchup.com.
SketchUp has been around
for a desktop application,
but the team's
strategy has always
been to expand and
broaden the market
of people who can
use 3D modeling,
and by making it
simple and easy to use
and accessible to everyone.
Delivering the app over
the web was a critical step
in that strategy,
and the team knew
that they wanted to
use the same code
base as their
desktop applications,
because rewriting their entire
application in JavaScript
was just simply not an option.
The team's approach was to use
the WebAssembly and Emscripten
compiler to compile
their core 3D modeler
and bring it to the web.
The initial port took two
engineers only three months
to bring to the web, which
is pretty phenomenal when
you realize just how
drastically it expanded
the reach of their application.
The early focus for
SketchUp has always
been on the next
generation of 3D modelers,
and today SketchUp
is already one
of the most popular apps on
the G Suite for education
marketplace.
At the same time, the app has
opened up a subscription model
for SketchUp, and in
just over six months,
the team has increased its
paying customer base by 10%.
SketchUp has also
seen consistent growth
in session time, returning
visitor percentage,
and active users.
Moving on, the next application
that I want to mention
is Google Earth.
I'm happy to say that Google
Earth has successfully
gotten their application ported
to WebAssembly, including
the newly added support
for WebAssembly threads.
The best part is
that they actually
got this threaded build working
in both Chrome and Firefox,
making Google Earth
the first WebAssembly
multi-threaded application to
be running in multiple browsers.
Google Earth did
some benchmarking,
comparing their single
threaded version
to their multi-threaded version.
They found that the
frame rate almost
doubled when they went to
their threaded version,
and the amount of jank/dropped
also reduced by more than half.
All right, so the
last big company
and launch that I want
to mention is Soundation.
Soundation is a
web-based music studio
that enables anyone
to make music
online with a wide selection
of instruments, loops, samples,
and effects.
No additional hardware or
installation or storage
is required.
Everything is accessible
instantly and everywhere.
Soundation's mission is to
facilitate musical creativity
in the world, and they
do this by offering
a powerful, accessible,
and affordable service
to the growing demographic
of casual producers.
As an online web app,
Soundation streamlines
the ability for producers
to connect with peers,
get feedback, enter
competitions, and even get
record deals.
Soundation is using
a wide variety
of advanced web features to
deliver this smooth experience.
And the first of these
is audio worklets.
Launched in Chrome
66, the audio worklet
brings fast performance and
extensible audio processing
to the web platform.
It could be used in conjunction
with other cutting edge web
technologies such as WebAssembly
and SharedArrayBuffer.
Soundation is also one of
the world's first adopters
of WebAssembly threads,
and they use these threads
to achieve fast parellelized
processing to seamlessly mix
songs.
So let's have a look
at their architecture
and see if we can
learn anything.
On the JavaScript
side of the world,
they have their application UI.
That application UI then talks
to an audio mixing engine.
This audio mixing
engine then spawns off
multiple different worker
threads in WebAssembly,
and each of these
worker threads can
talk to the same piece of
SharedArrayBuffer memory.
This SharedArrayBuffer
memory is then
passed on to the mixing
threads, which further passes it
to the audio worklet, which
produces the final result.
Here's a visualization showing
the performance improvements
on rendering a song as they
added multiple threads.
Adding just a single
additional thread doubled
their performance,
and by the time
they've added five
threads, they had more than
tripled the performance
of their application.
So that's a great visualization
showing the performance
improvements that
thread can bring,
but since this is Soundation,
I thought we would instead
try and listen to it.
So here is us trying to
render a song in Soundation
in the single threaded
version of WebAssembly.
And fair warning,
this is not going
to be an entirely
pleasant experience.
[STATICY MUSIC]
So as you can imagine,
this is not the experience
that you want when you're trying
to create beautiful music.
But luckily Soundation succeeded
in launching with WebAssembly
threads, and now
they're able to deliver
an experience that sounds
just a little bit better.
[SMOOTH MUSIC]
So as you can see, not
only is this a much more
pleasant experience,
but the CPU also
has additional cycle
for other work.
All right, so I want to close
off my segment by just talking
about some of the
amazing community
projects that we've seen
people working on out there.
And the first of these
that I want to mention
is the awesome work that's
been done by the Mozilla
team and the Rust community
to bring Rust to the web
through WebAssembly.
They have an awesome set
of tools and materials
to help you get started,
and you can check those out
at rustwasm.github.io.
Speaking of
languages, we've also
seen more than 30
different projects
trying to bring other languages
to the web through WebAssembly.
These languages include ones
like Perl, Python, Ruby,
Kotlin, OCaml, Go, PHP,
and the .NET framework.
Many of these languages
require garbage collection,
which isn't currently
something that's
supported in WebAssembly,
though we are working on it.
These languages come to
the web by actually taking
their garbage collection
system and other runtime bits
and compiling that itself
down to WebAssembly,
and then shipping everything
down to the application page.
This is a great strategy
for getting started
and experimenting with some
of these languages on the web,
but because of some of
their performance and memory
characteristics, these
aren't currently suited
for production applications.
The fully supported languages
today are C, C++, and Rust,
but everything else should still
be considered experimental.
And there are so many more
amazing community projects
that I don't have
time to do justice.
We've seen people porting
Gameboy emulators, GNU
libraries, digital signal
processing, and even
entire operating system like
Microsoft Windows 2000 now
available in a
browser tab, which
is, if not a exactly
pleasant experience,
definitely interesting.
You can check out
all of these demos
and much more at the forum
where we have multiple demos
set up for you to check out.
And with that, I want to
hand it back off to Alex
to talk to you more
about WebAssembly threads
and how to use some
of these features.
[APPLAUSE]
ALEX DANILO: Thank you, Thomas.
One of the kind of big
things at the conference
here, when we talk
about the browser,
we talk about
using the platform.
And quite often people think
of the platform as the software
stack that's inside
the browser, but I
like to think of it a
little bit different.
I like to think about the
hardware, the platform that's
actually in your machine.
So here is an artist's
rendition of the inside
of a desktop microprocessor.
This is what you
see today if you
take the plastic off the top.
So at the top, we
have the green bit,
which interfaces to
the PCI bus, used
to be called the northbridge.
The left and right, you
have memory interfaces.
These little yellow boxes are
integrated memory controllers.
And you see all these
blue tiles here.
And what they are is cores.
So each of those is a CPU
core in its own right.
So this may be a desktop
microprocessor, but even
in your pocket, if you have an
iPhone or an advanced Android
phone, you'll have
something like six
to eight cores in
there, ready to be
used to do good computing work.
So when you write a
normal web application,
you're looking at
something like this.
You have one core
running and so you have
all this silicon doing nothing.
So you're not really
using the platform.
Now we've seen people come
along and do something
like spawn a web worker
to do the hard work,
and have the main thread for UI.
In that case, you're running
a double threaded application.
And so you're using the
platform a bit better,
but you're not really
doing everything you could.
Now since we have introduced
WebAssembly threads,
you can do stuff like this.
You could actually use many
cores for your application.
And as we saw with
the Soundation demo,
there's visible improvement
in the user experience.
So I'd really like
you to start thinking
about how you can
adapt your application
to use all these cores.
Now when you create
a web worker,
you have to understand that
that is a threading primitive
and they run concurrently.
So you can do
compute in parallel.
And this is a primitive that
we all know pretty well.
But one of the things
about when we do something
like this, if we have
an app, on the left,
we have what we call
the main thread--
we're all familiar
with the main thread--
that interacts and
talks to the DOM.
The worker that we
generate is what
we call the background thread.
So it's running in parallel
but it doesn't actually
have the ability
to call web APIs
and interact with the
DOM and stuff like that.
But when you create
workers, and you create them
normally with a JavaScript
thing, it creates an instance.
So these instances kind of
sit on their own on the side,
they're running
parallel, they don't get
to do anything with the DOM.
So they kind of run on the side.
So if you create one,
you get V8 hanging off
the top of your main thread, and
you get an instance hanging off
your worker.
So then if you go and
create a bunch of workers,
you get a bunch
more V8 instances.
Now each of these
instances consumes memory.
So that means that if you start
spawning lots of JavaScript
workers to make your application
do stuff more complex,
it will actually consume
more and more memory
and you might run out on a
phone, or something like that.
But I'll let you in
on a little secret.
They don't talk to each other.
So you've got separate
bits of JavaScript
running in all these
parallel threads,
but they don't communicate.
They don't have
any shared state.
They're literally another
copy of V8 sitting in memory.
The way these things
can talk to each other,
though, is with postMessage.
And postMessage is kind of like
sending a paper plane over.
I'll send it from this
worker to that one,
I'll sit around and
wait for it to arrive,
and there's no
predictability about when
that will be delivered.
So it's not a great experience
for a true multi-threaded
application.
Now, when the team built
WebAssembly threads,
they implemented something that
looks a lot more like this.
So what happens is, this
is an example of, say,
having three threads.
So under the hood, we actually
spin up the three web workers
but the difference here is
that the WebAssembly module
is shared between the workers.
So there is one
copy of the code,
so you're not consuming
nearly as much memory.
But more importantly,
they share state,
and the way they share
state is through a thing
called SharedArrayBuffer.
So if you're a
JavaScript engineer,
you probably know what a typed
array is, because you use them
day to day.
So SharedArrayBuffer is
basically the exact same thing,
except that it can be
shared across workers.
And so what that
means is the state
of the execution of the
application is visible to any
of the workers in parallel.
Now if you farm off something
into a pool of workers
and you have it hanging
off your main app,
it will look
something like this.
You'll have your main thread
for your main application that
can talk to the DOM, it
can use all the web APIs,
and it can see the
SharedArrayBuffer,
and that
SharedArrayBuffer is being
manipulated by all the parallel
threads in the WebAssembly
module.
OK, but by now you're
probably thinking,
this is all well
and good, but how
do I use this stuff in
my actual application?
So I'll start with a
very simple example.
We'll do an example which is
just a little Fibonacci program
that runs in two threads.
So it will look a bit like this.
There'll be the main thread,
the background thread,
the WebAssembly
module, all talking
to the SharedArrayBuffer.
So we just take
some source code,
which will be
something like this,
which is just a bit of C code.
And what we want
to do is we want
to compile that into a form that
we can use in parallel threads.
And the way we do that is with
the Emscripten tool chain.
So it has a compiler
called EMCC,
and there are a
couple of flags here,
though, I want to point out.
The first one is
-s USE_PTHREADS=1.
What that does is turn on
the multi-threading support
when you're compiling
your WebAssembly module.
The second flag that's
interesting is -s
PTHREAD_POOL_SIZE=2.
What this does is
tells the compiler
that I want to pre-allocate
two threads for my application.
So when I actually start
the WebAssembly module
it will pre-create two threads
and get going with that.
Now this is kind
of visualization
what would happen.
If you set PTHREAD
pool size to two,
you get the picture on the
left, you get two workers,
and if you set it to eight
you get eight workers.
And that happens at startup
time of your web app.
Now you may be wondering why
you care about the number.
Well, the thing is that you
should really try and set it
to the maximum
number of threads.
If you say I only
want two threads,
and then suddenly
your application needs
three or four, it's
a bit of a problem.
So what happens is that
the WebAssembly module
has to yield to the
main thread before it
can create that worker.
So if you're relying on
all the threads being
there at the startup, you need
to set the number high enough.
But of course, if you
set that number too high,
you're wasting memory.
So this is something to tune.
So in Soundation's case
they used five threads
and it works really
well for them.
So when you're tuning your apps
you need to think about it.
OK, so if you want to get
out there and actually try
this stuff, which
I'm sure you're all
dying to, if you
fire up Chrome 70
and navigate to Chrome flags and
search for WebAssembly thread
support, change the
setting here from default
to enabled, and at
that point, you'll
have to restart your browser.
And then you can start building
stuff and testing it locally.
Now once you've built a
working WebAssembly thread app,
you probably want to deploy
it out to the public.
And the way you do that is by
getting an origin trial token.
So an origin trial token
is tied to your domain
and you get it from us.
And you basically--
it's just a meta tag
that you put on the page.
And that tells the
browser, hey, these people
are trying WebAssembly
threads and let's use it.
So if you want to go
ahead and do that,
and I encourage you all to do
so, just go to this short link,
and there's a form
you can fill in, put
in your URL, the reason
you want to use this stuff,
and go start building
something really cool.
Now of course, as developers,
we spend most of our times
in DevTools trying to debug
things, which is how it is.
So in Chrome 70 at the moment,
which is released to stable,
you can single
step instructions.
And that is a
WebAssembly instructions.
So it looks a little
bit like this,
like not friendly, as
Thomas pointed out.
So you can see this
little box up here,
which is showing
you the threads.
So this is a two thread
application running.
And this box is the actual
WebAssembly disassembled code.
So it's not the binary, it's a
text form of the instructions
that are in the module.
And you can single
step those and it's all
very well and good, but
realistically, we don't really
like that debugging experience.
So Chrome 71 brings
source map support,
as Thomas mentioned earlier.
So source maps lets you
change what you saw before
into something--
oop, next slide--
something that looks like this.
So this is the source code of
the Fibonacci function sitting
in Dev Tools, and you can
single step over instructions,
you can set breakpoints, you
can do all stuff like that.
Now, if you want to
actually do this yourself
and you want to
generate the source map,
you just need to set two flags
on the EMCC compiler command
line.
The first is -g, which says
generate debug symbols,
and the second is
--source-map-base,
and that points to a URL
where it will actually
find the source map file.
In this case, I'm
using local host,
so I'll be using it
on my own workstation.
OK, so I'll just recap on
what we've talked about today,
just so you can remember
what we talked about.
The first thing is it's
streaming compilation,
which lets the browser
compile the WebAssembly
module as it comes over the
wire, which is launched now.
It's in Chrome 70,
which speeds things up.
The second is Liftoff, which
is the tiered compiler,
so you get the first compile
really fast so your app starts,
and then hot swaps in the
better code a bit later on.
Then we have, of course,
WebAssembly threads shipping
now in Chrome 70, and you can
use it with an origin trial,
so you can ship it
to your customers
and they can use it
and play with it.
And of course, Chrome 71,
which will be out really soon,
contains source
maps, which means
that it's a lot easier
to debug your code.
And so I'd encourage
all of you people
out there to start writing
using WebAssembly threads,
because it unlocks the power
of the supercomputer that's
sitting in your
pocket right now.
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]