[MUSIC PLAYING]
BEN GALBRAITH: Welcome
to Chrome Dev Summit.
I'm Ben Galbraith.
I lead product for the
Chrome platform teams.
DION ALMAER: And
I'm Dior Almaer,
and I lead product for our
developer ecosystem efforts.
BEN GALBRAITH: Thanks
for joining us here
at the Yerba Buena Center for
the Arts here in San Francisco.
And a special shout-out
to those of you
watching on the livestream.
DION ALMAER: We look
forward all year
to this opportunity to
gather with developers
from around the world to
celebrate the web platform.
And of course, it's an
opportunity for the Chrome team
and others here at
Google to provide updates
on our latest work and get
feedback from the community.
BEN GALBRAITH:
2018 marks 10 years
since the launch of
Chrome, but it also
marks Android's
10-year anniversary,
and 20 years since Google
was founded, back in 1998.
So this is a really
big year for us,
and it's got us reflecting
on these past 10 years.
Back in 2008, Dion
and I were at Mozilla
working on developer tools
when we received probably
the most unique product
announcement we'd ever seen,
the Chrome comic, which walked
through Chrome's new features,
like the Omnibox, and
architectural innovations
like the multi-process
architecture,
and the high-performance
V8 JavaScript runtime.
DION ALMAER: And
years later, it's
really fun to note the
V8 was reused by Node.js
and plenty of other open
source projects out there.
BEN GALBRAITH: Chrome
launched in this time,
in the midst of a
web renaissance,
back in the Ajax movement
that saw developers
pushing the boundaries of
what was possible on the web,
doing things that we
just hadn't seen before.
And it's amazing to see
just how far the web has
come in these 10 years, with
publishers like Huffington
Post transforming the
typical documents of the web
into rich, interactive
experiences--
DION ALMAER: --and Google
Maps, an early pioneer
of that Ajax era, had gone
from maps of tiled images
to a street-to-space continuum
combining 360-degree photos,
vector maps, 3D models,
and satellite imagery,
all just in the browser.
BEN GALBRAITH: And productivity
apps have come into their own
on the platform, with pro tools
like the incomparable AutoCAD
and the collaborative
design platform, Figma.
And because they're
on the web, you
can get right into these things.
And when you're done
being productive,
you can pop into high-quality
games like Crossy Road
for, you know, just a
minute-- just a couple.
Just a quick minute.
[LAUGHTER]
DION ALMAER: And
Chrome has changed
quite a bit over
this time, and more
than just these subtle
changes to the logo.
BEN GALBRAITH:
Earlier this year, we
highlighted Chrome's
new refreshed design,
and updated usability
enhancements such as better tab
treatment for people like
Dion that have 500 tabs
open at a time.
DION ALMAER: It's true.
[CHUCKLING]
BEN GALBRAITH: And also a
smarter Omnibox and auto-fill
features.
But the most important
update was clearly--
DION ALMAER: --the birthday
mode and the Dino game,
which run for the entire
month of September.
Do you know this is played
over 270 million times a month?
BEN GALBRAITH:
That's incredible.
DION ALMAER: It kind of is.
[CHUCKLING]
BEN GALBRAITH: But
here at CDS, it's
really the
platform-related features
that we want to talk about.
So let's highlight a few.
DION ALMAER: So
back in 2008, Chrome
launched with process
isolation, an architecture that
put each tab in its own
operating system process,
making Chrome exceptionally
stable, but also exceptionally
secure.
The process boundary acts as
a line of defense in the event
malicious code is
able to exploit a bug
and attempt to read
data from another tab.
Over the past 10
years, this model
has become the
industry standard.
BEN GALBRAITH: This year,
desktop Chrome browsers
took this model further with
the launch of Site Isolation.
So now, Chrome ensures that
even within a single tab,
content from different
Domains is isolated.
So in this example,
in the iframe,
this news site is
using a display ad,
and it's running in
a different process
than the rest of the page.
We've wanted to extend
process isolation this way
for some time, and we think
it's an important protection
for the web.
DION ALMAER: Now we've also
been continuing our efforts
to encourage developers to
use HTTPS for all web traffic.
This ensures that
the content of a site
isn't maliciously
modified while in transit,
and also that user data
is transferred securely.
BEN GALBRAITH: In
the latest Chrome,
we mark pages as not secure
when they're served from HTTP.
And when the user begins to
interact with form fields,
we further emphasize the
point with a stronger warning.
DION ALMAER: The HTTPS movement
is a collaborative effort,
with organizations
like Let's Encrypt
playing a big role in lowering
the barriers to upgrading
sites.
And it's working.
In Chrome itself, we're
seeing big shifts to HTTPS.
And over 80% of the top 100
sites are now all HTTPS.
We think this is actually
a major accomplishment
because the web is such
a massive ecosystem.
BEN GALBRAITH: All right.
In addition to
security and stability,
speed was a big theme
for Chrome at launch.
And V8 is a big
part of that story.
The team recently posted a
retrospective highlighting
its improvements over
this period, including
significant gains in
JavaScript execution speed,
and a 100x decrease in
garbage collection jank.
And the team is looking
forward to the next 10
years of improvements by
optimizing V8 for the latest
JavaScript language features,
like promises and async/await,
supporting the Node.js
server-side community,
and being responsive to
the needs of the framework
ecosystem.
DION ALMAER: There's a fun
recent example of this--
how the team rapidly responded
to JavaScript inefficiencies
related to the react framework's
recently announced hooks
feature, finding ways
to make this feature
work much faster on V8.
Now V8 has also expanded
to support WebAssembly,
also called Wasm, a
cross-browser standard
for executing low-level
code, like C and C++,
at very high speed.
Earlier this year, the team
launched the new Wasm compiler
called Liftoff, and the
popular Unity game engine
found that it resulted in a
10x reduction in the load time
for their Wasm code.
BEN GALBRAITH: And
WebAssembly threads
are now available
in a Chrome origin
trial, which opens the
door for more complex code
to come to the web.
DION ALMAER: Now
it's been really
fun to see the community explode
the power of WebAssembly,
both through new creations and
by bringing old code bases--
BEN GALBRAITH: Actually, I think
I prefer the term vintage code
bases.
DION ALMAER: Vintage-- vintage,
high-quality code bases
to the web.
This tweet was one
of my favorites, kind
of a in inception
moment, because now I
think you can run IE on Windows
95 on Chrome on Android.
BEN GALBRAITH: It's crazy.
[LAUGHTER]
DION ALMAER: What a
world that we live in.
BEN GALBRAITH: It's
hard to believe,
but back when Chrome
launched, video on the web
wasn't a thing.
We had to use plugins.
And now, of course, HTML
video is ubiquitous.
This year, Chrome
landed support for AV1,
which is the next generation
media codec, completely
royalty-free, that provides
a 30% bitrate reduction,
even over each HEVC, which
makes streaming video on the web
faster as this becomes adopted.
And because AV1 has
major industry backing,
we can expect to see it receive
significant adoption over time.
DION ALMAER: Now one constant
over the past 10 years
is the importance of
optimizing images.
This is sort of like
flossing for the internet--
vital for your site's
health, yet plenty of us
don't really seem
to do it enough.
And as a Brit, trust
me on that one.
[BEN CHUCKLING]
Now a few years ago,
Chrome added support
for WebP, a new
image format that
results in an average 30%
savings over other formats
like PNG, JPEG, and GIF.
BEN GALBRAITH: "Jiff."
DION ALMAER: What was that?
BEN GALBRAITH: No.
DION ALMAER: Oh, sorry.
BEN GALBRAITH: I didn't talk.
[LAUGHTER]
DION ALMAER: And this
year, Edge and Firefox
ship support for
WebP, so make sure
your images are fully squooshed.
BEN GALBRAITH: All right, so
the web and Chrome have come
a long way these past 10 years.
So where do we go from here?
We've just spent the
last few minutes talking
about the importance of speed,
and the enhancements to the web
platform that make
that more possible.
And we think this will continue
to be a major focus for all
of us into the future because
speed is one of the defining
features of the web platform.
It's what makes it so magical
to go from a link right
into a rich experience,
seamlessly, without any delay.
DION ALMAER: Now
delivering speed
is a partnership between
the browsers and developers.
Because no matter how fast
and efficient browsers become,
a poorly optimized
site will always
ruin the fast
loading experiences
that our users want.
And increasingly, JavaScript
can also become a major factor
in slowing down sites.
BEN GALBRAITH: It's
because since 2001, sites
use an average eight
times more JavaScript
than they did before.
And that's a problem,
because in addition
to having to be
downloaded, all this code
needs to be compiled by
the browser and executed.
And with mobile,
many of the devices
that our users are
using are slower
than they've been before.
And so increasingly,
performance can include the CPU
as a bottleneck.
DION ALMAER: Now
we've created tools
like Lighthouse,
PageSpeed Insights,
and the Chrome User
Experience Report
that can provide deep insights
into your site's performance
and how it can be improved.
BEN GALBRAITH: However, as
helpful as these tools can be,
a pattern we've seen is that a
site's performance will degrade
over time because we're
constantly adding new features
to enhance our site.
And these new features
create pressure for the site
to get bigger and bigger.
And that includes more
script an more resources
that have to be downloaded.
Of course, we're not
saying that we shouldn't
be constantly enhancing our
sites and adding features,
but as we do so, we
have to take care
that as we add these features we
ensure that our pages continue
to load fast.
DION ALMAER: So an
approach that we've
seen that's led to
great results here
is the practice of establishing
a performance budget.
And popular tools
and frameworks,
like Angular,
Preact, and Webpack
have built-in support to define
budgets and enforce them.
These budgets can
be based on the bite
size of your
resources, or they can
ensure you hit target
metrics and scenarios.
For example, you can specify
that your site should
load in under five seconds
on a mid-range smartphone
and a high-latency 3G network.
BEN GALBRAITH: The
team at Pinterest
have set a great example
of using a budget to guide
their optimizations efforts.
We'd love to share a video
that explains this process.
now.
Let's roll the video.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
ZACK ARGYLE:
Pinterest's mission is
to help people discover things,
collect them, organize them,
and then find ways to
apply them in your life.
[PAGE TEARING]
LUDO ANTONOV: With more
and more people on the go,
the mobile web has become
central at providing
our discovery experience.
But our mobile web
experience in the past
was basically an upsell
for the native app.
ZACK ARGYLE: Which brought
us to the realization
that we needed to fix it.
LUDO ANTONOV: The technology
was already in place for us
to be able to do so.
ZACK ARGYLE: And so we
brought a team together
to rebuild the mobile
web from scratch.
Having a fast mobile web
was crucial to the success
of the project.
We made sure that we split out
what was sent down to the user
to be only the crucial
things to start,
and then everything else that
wasn't immediately important
sent down later on.
We made sure to test out
on average devices on 3G,
just like our users
would be using.
And we could see the
dramatic difference
that there was on that
initial time-to-interactivity.
By using modern caching best
practices in Service Worker,
even if you're on
a bad connection
or have no connection, we
were able to preload the user
interface for follow-up visits.
LUDO ANTONOV: Like
the native app,
our site was optimized
for touch interactions.
This immersive experience
resulted in mobile web
becoming our top platform
for new sign-ups.
ZACK ARGYLE: We
wanted to make sure
that the users
for our mobile web
continued to use the
product as time goes by.
And one of the most
important technologies
that's been added to
browsers was the ability
to add that site to
your home screen.
Pinterest is not just
about the content,
but about what you do with it.
LUDO ANTONOV: The browser
is a discovery platform.
So making it easier for pinners
to use our own discovery
service is really a perfect fit.
[PLAYBACK ENDS]
BEN GALBRAITH: Cool.
DION ALMAER: Thank you.
Pinterest is a great example
of doing performance right,
and Zack from their
team is here to share
more with us later today.
Now let's talk about
another example, Wayfair.
After experiencing some
performance regressions,
they created an
internal dashboard
that provides a simple stoplight
system for their developers,
and keeps performance
top of mind.
Since they implemented
this system,
they've seen consistent speed
gains across their sites,
and their year-over-year
conversion rate
has increased by over 10%.
BEN GALBRAITH: OK.
While we're talking
about speed, we'd
like to tell you about two
new web platform features
that we're implementing
in Chrome that we
think may lead to more instant
and seamless web experiences.
Web Packaging is
a new feature that
allows developers to sign a web
page with a special encryption
key that proves the
page's original domain,
and creates a sort
of package that
can be served from anywhere, and
that the browser can securely
represent with the
page's original domain.
DION ALMAER: Now Portals--
Portals adds a new
iframe-like element
to HTML that allows users
to seamlessly transition
into the Portals content,
making it a new top-level web
page in the process.
Taken together,
these new standards
enable the browser to securely
preload pages, and deliver
experiences like this that
transition to the new site
instantly.
Let's try it again.
BEN GALBRAITH: Sure.
Tap, and you're right
there, instantly.
Tomorrow, we'll talk
through more of the details,
and explain how you
can start experimenting
with web packaging right now.
We're pretty excited
about this and the impact
that we think it
can have on the web.
Loading fast is
important, but so is
delivering a buttery-smooth
UI once the page is displayed.
Buttery means responding to user
input-- like taps and typing--
instantly, and ensuring
that the page doesn't
jank, or sort of skip
around as the user
scrolls and interacts with it.
DION ALMAER: Now traditionally,
this hasn't maybe
been the strong
suit for the web,
but we think that
things are changing.
So today, we're
releasing Squoosh,
and it is an example of how
responsive complex apps can
be on today's web.
It demonstrates a really
fast loading experience using
WebAssembly to compress images
using C and C++ libraries,
and employing Web Workers
to handle long-running tasks
in the background,
enabling a smooth UI,
even while the app
works really hard.
Now this is a full PWA.
It works across mobile, desktop,
tablet, and offline, too,
thanks to Service Worker.
BEN GALBRAITH: Let's
use Chrome's DevTools
to go under the covers
of Squoosh for a moment
and take a look.
Here on the screen, we can see
different browser processes
at work in the app.
And if we zoom in
to three of them--
the main process
and the workers--
we can see, in the main process,
all these vertical lines.
And each vertical line indicates
when the main thread's busy,
and the app can't
respond to user input.
And you can see here they're
all generally pretty narrow.
And then you can
see in the workers,
we have these really long bars,
representing these long running
tasks that would jank
the snot out of the UI
if they weren't
in the background.
DION ALMAER: Now if Jake
can get his nerves back,
he and Mariko are going
to join us later and do
a session on how they're able
to build this application.
So sometimes there are tasks
that you can't naturally
move off of the main
thread, such as code
that updates the UI.
With the recently released
Offscreen Canvas feature,
now in Chrome and behind a
flag in Firefox and Opera,
helps you by letting you paint
to image surfaces like Canvas
and WebGL in a worker, and
then copy the image buffer back
over to the UI in a
single, fast operation.
The video here shows how
Offscreen Canvas maintains
a smooth UI even after
we artificially add code
to make the painting process
expensive using that jank
bottom in the middle.
BEN GALBRAITH:
It's pretty smooth.
Tomorrow, we're
going to tell you
about more features that
are coming to the web
to help with smooth, buttery
UIs, such as new APIs
for background code, called
worklets that make tasks
like animation, audio, custom
painting, and custom layout
easier; a new web component
called a Virtual Scroller that
makes it easy to develop
really smooth scrolling
views over large datasets;
and a Task Scheduler API that
gives developers more control
over how the browser spends
its time.
DION ALMAER: That's a
lot, but as Mariko said,
you can never add enough butter.
BEN GALBRAITH: How true.
[DION CHUCKLING]
DION ALMAER: So having a
fast-loading, responsive
website is key, but so are the
things that it actually does.
So on that note,
let's talk about some
of the web's latest integrations
with the underlying device
and operating system.
BEN GALBRAITH: Let's take the
Spotify PWA as an example.
With it, users can go straight
from a link right into Spotify
without even
installing anything.
And with the web's full support
for background audio, DRM,
and offline, Spotify can provide
a full-featured web experience.
DION ALMAER: And now Chrome
supports desktop PWAs,
letting apps like Spotify
run in their own windows
and be easily installed on
Chrome OS, Windows, Linux,
and soon on the Mac.
BEN GALBRAITH: I think desktop
PWAs are really handy when
you've got lots of
tabs open-- like Dion,
as I mentioned earlier--
and you want to keep your
favorite stuff really easy
to get to, like
with the Twitter PWA
that we're showing here
running as a desktop
PWA in Chrome Canary on the Mac.
And what's really
cool about Twitter
is that they've got
experimental support that
enables their mobile PWA to
run at desktop screen sizes,
as we're showing here, which has
kind of been the dream of web
development for a long time.
DION ALMAER: While we're on
the topic of desktop web apps,
we also recently
implemented new web APIs
in Chrome that enable unfettered
access to input devices.
So web apps can receive full
keyboard input elements,
sample games' pads
at high resolution,
and enter immersive
fullscreen modes.
All of this is
perfect for apps like
the recently-announced Google
Project Stream shown here.
BEN GALBRAITH:
Speaking of media,
we've also taken the
recently-released
picture-in-picture
feature that we
have on mobile video over
to the desktop, which
makes web video on desktop more
of an integrated experience.
DION ALMAER: And then
another important new web API
is WebAuthN, which enables
websites to integrate
with biometric sensors
and other forms
of multi-factor authentication.
It's currently implemented
in Firefox, Opera, Chrome,
coming soon to Edge, and
it can make web checkout
a seamlessly secure experience.
BEN GALBRAITH: Seen here with
the checkout, and with PayPal.
And it displays the
authentication challenge
as integrated with the device.
So as the web's
capabilities increase,
it's also important to augment
the security and the privacy
of the platform, and ensure
that everyone has an opportunity
to participate in the
open digital economy.
This is why we've been
leading the development
of advanced new
privacy techniques,
like federated learning and
secure aggregation, that
enable personalized
digital experiences that
also have the strongest
privacy guarantees.
And we've been hard at work
reviewing the fundamentals
of how the web
works with respect
to privacy and personalization.
And in the next year, we'll
be shipping new features
into Chrome as well as new
server-side technologies that
help us uphold the highest
standards of user privacy
with regards to data
collection and usage.
DION ALMAER: Now
as the web evolves
and we get new
capabilities, we're
constantly focused
on interoperability,
on how well web apps
work across browsers.
And we know this topic is top
of mind with developers, too.
To this end, we've
been collaborating
with other browsers on an
open source comprehensive web
platform test project.
And we're pleased to share
that the browsers are becoming
more interoperable as
measured by these tests,
and we're continuing
to collaborate
with the other browsers
on reference docs
for the web on the
Mozilla develop network.
BEN GALBRAITH: These
efforts are resulting
in a less fragmented developer
experience for all of us,
which frees us to spend our time
not chasing down compatibility
bugs, but on adding more
features to the platform
and performance budgets.
We also think it's more
important than ever
for us to make it easier
to create high-quality web
experiences.
So to this end, we've been
working on a new learning
website called web.dev.
DION ALMAER: On
web.dev, we start out
by explaining the
principles that we've
found lead to top quality sites,
such as speed, discoverability,
and reliability.
And we follow these
up with guides
that explain why you should
care about a given concept.
They provide clear tutorials
and offer plenty of sample code.
BEN GALBRAITH: We've also
partnered with Glitch
to embed their
popular coding tool
right into the
experience, which provides
an interactive learning
environment for getting
hands-on, and letting you
remix and test your code.
And we've integrated Lighthouse
into the web.dev experience,
giving you a platform
that lets you
track the scores of
your websites over time.
And if your site isn't quite
at a perfect score yet,
it also gives you
instructions on how
to resolve the specific issues
that it's found with your site.
DION ALMAER: So that's web.dev.
We'd love to get your feedback,
especially while we're here
together at CDS.
And by the way, if you
like that .dev domain,
check out get.dev for details
on how you can register one
for yourself in the future.
BEN GALBRAITH: We also have
another fun learning project
that we want to share with you.
We've collaborated
with Dave Geddes,
who's created interactive
tutorials like Flexbox Zombies
and CSS Grid Critters--
these are real things,
and they're really cool--
to develop--
DION ALMAER: --Service
Workies, an online adventure
that helps you really
deeply understand
Service Worker, soup to nuts.
It's a fun, free,
engaging way to learn.
So please head over to
ServiceWorkies.com to sign up
and start the preview
levels that launch just now.
Now we've also got
plenty of updates
to our developer
tools and libraries
that we're going to share
over the next two days.
But there's one new tool that
we'd like to tell you about.
BEN GALBRAITH: We
call it VisBug,
and it puts a new spin on how
developers and designers can
interact with web pages.
We'd like to give you a demo.
And to do that, let's invite
Adam Argyle up to the stage.
Please welcome Adam.
[MUSIC PLAYING, APPLAUSE]
ADAM ARGYLE: What's up, guys?
Thanks for this opportunity.
So, developers, you
got a lot of tools.
And whoa, your keynote
was amazing so far.
You're spitting fire.
I'm back there laughing, and
I'm-- anyway, it's awesome.
So I wanted to give some tools
to people that don't generally
feel like they have a whole
lot of power on the web
unless they open up
the Chrome DevTools.
Chrome DevTools, of course,
are like omni-capable.
But oh, that's right.
I got my screensaver came on.
Let me just take my huge
password here, because--
DION ALMAER: That's
a cool screensaver.
ADAM ARGYLE: Oh, for sure.
Gotta love that.
OK, so I'm going to hit
play on this site, because--
OK, so I wanted
more people to be
able to contribute to
good web experiences,
and be able to inspect
and dissect things.
And so considered like what
Zeppelin is as a designer
developer handoff.
I've created this thing
called VisBug that essentially
gives those tools in reverse.
So this first tool here
is the Guides tool.
Have you ever held a piece
of paper up to your screen
and been like, ooh,
is it lined up?
Here you go.
There's even, I think,
a Chrome extension
that just does this one thing.
And so you can come
down here, you're like,
oh that footer, that
looks generally aligned.
Yeah, let me just
kind of hover-- yep,
yeah, it looks great.
This is kind of interesting.
Look, I can go into
a nested hover state,
and still check
what's going on there.
So that's just the Grid tool.
There's a whole bunch of tools.
I'm to do my best to show you
more what's going on here.
This is the Accessibility tool.
I really want Accessibility
to be something
that more people are aware of.
It's a little-- there's
just too many steps
to find what is there.
So this, you just hover now.
You just hover for
color contrasts.
You hover for surfacing
ARIA rules and tap indexes.
So basically, the things that
you're generally looking for
are now a hover away instead of
maybe it's five or six clicks.
And the same sort of
thing is for styles.
So you can hover over SVG.
You can hover over buttons.
Nothing is off-limits
to Pixelbug.
It's kind of punk rock.
It's like, hey, is
there DOM there?
I'll look at it.
I'll tell you what's there.
And so here's what you--
and so let me go through
a couple more tools.
I really like the
hue shift tool.
And so if you go download
this Chrome extension,
you just have to
hover over a tool
and it will show
you how it's used.
I'll do my best to walk
through the keyboard shortcuts
that I'm doing.
But it's kind of like
design vim at the moment.
Anyway, it's super fun.
So what I'm going to do, I'm
going to select this path.
I want to make sure I've
got my hue shift tool
I'm going hit Command-E
to expand my selection.
I'm just going to hold it.
Whee.
And look at that.
So I selected all
of those path nodes.
So the way that
worked is it expanded
based on the node name
and the class name,
and found similar elements
that were siblings.
And I'm just going to
add some black here.
Is that magical.
It feels magical.
If I hold Control, I can
make my selections go away.
So I could be like,
ooh, don't you like it?
And in this case, I
think black's wrong.
I'm going to add some white.
I'm going to hit Shift
and Right to add some hue.
And then I'm going
to rotate the hue
with Command-Shift and Down.
So I'm rotating the
hue by values of 10.
And now I can explore
color palettes.
I love this particular tool.
It's HSL-based.
It's awesome.
So another thing I want to
show you really quick too
is the Move tool.
You can just move things
in the DOM around.
You click stuff, and you
move it with the keyboard.
Duh, right?
Why haven't you had this before?
It seems to make so much sense.
So I'm just going to kind of
rearrange it here a little bit.
I'm going to hit M for margin,
and then I hit Shift-Up.
So Shift-Up, Shift-Up, Shift-Up.
I'm just adding 10 pixels
of margin to the top.
So consider that these little
quick tasks were things
that you had to sort
of nest and find,
and now you can do
them in the chaos
of the browser in production.
I wanted the DOM to be
the source of truth.
I wanted a design
tool that treated
the DOM as a source of truth.
Anyway, I like this site because
it's like, ooh, super-flashy,
and this tool doesn't care.
Let's get a little meta, and
take a quick look at Squoosh,
which was just introduced.
It's super-rad.
And the first thing
I want to do is
talk about some of the
additional tools in here.
But I want to troll Jake a
little bit while I'm up here.
So what I'm going to do first,
I'm going to grab this image,
and I'm going to
turn it into myself.
So have you ever
wanted to just swap
a pinned image on a web page?
It's just drag and drop, right?
Why hasn't that been there?
A lot of the stuff, I had to--
here's another one,
Double-Click for text editing.
Let's just make
this drag and plop--
because again, I'm trolling him.
We'll go back here to
my little inspect tool
we'll look at what
styles he's got in here.
Ooh, nice.
Some good Flexbox.
So I'm going to
select this image.
I'm going to hit
Command-E again.
Here's a fun idea
I borrowed from XD.
So I'm very inspired from
XD, and Figma, and Zeppelin,
and even Developer Tooling, too.
So watch this one.
I love this one.
I'm going to go in here.
I'm going to grab two images.
I want to grab a picture of me.
I wish I had other pictures.
Who wants to see my
face multiple times?
Anyway, I want to
drag in two images.
And if you remember we had--
oh, hey, come on.
Take focus, take
focus, take focus.
Oh, good.
I was just impatient.
Here you go.
And I'm going to hover there.
Boom, they ping-pong.
[LAUGHTER]
It just sort of was
like, hey, how many?
I don't care.
And it will just fill it up.
It's super-fun.
OK, so we're done kind of
like trolling his home page.
Let's actually go do
something meaningful.
He asked me to do
a design review.
OK, so I hid my tools.
The site doesn't even
know I changed it.
Let's drag in something fun.
I like this Christmas
eggnog picture.
Yeah, this is good.
Me and my wife--
hello.
And so we have this
very complex website.
It's packed with Wasm.
And you know, maybe
conceptually, you're just like,
there's no way I could
kind of help design that.
Well of course you can.
It's [INAUDIBLE].
It doesn't care.
So I'm going to expand it.
I'm going to get some things
into a nested state, something
that's theoretically
harder to design with.
And I'm going to
darken this side up.
I'm a fan of retro
wave right now.
And I love those like purples,
pinks, and stuff on dark.
Let's do that to the
site really quick.
So I'm going to
launch [INAUDIBLE],,
and we're just going to use
a couple of features here.
So I'm going to hit
this header because I
think these need to
be a little bit more
pronounced with
some accent color.
I'm going to expand my selection
by clicking a class name.
So what's cool is BEM and
just dynamically generated
class names.
What they do is they
create a consistency
between related nodes.
And so I leveraged those.
You just make a selection.
And you can hover
on the classes too,
and it will pseudo-highlight.
Anyway, this tool is
so full of features.
I'm having a hard
time talking slow.
OK, so anyway I
got these headers.
I just want to spoof these up.
So I'm going to get
rid of their opacity
by doing Command-Shift
Right and Left.
You can manage opacity.
I'm going to add some
white by hitting Shift-Up.
I'm going to add some hue
by adding Shift-Right.
And I'm going to change the
hue to (SINGING) hot pink.
Right?
Super-rad.
OK, so then I'm
going to go in here.
And I'm going to darken this up.
I like how transparent
it is, but I've
got this darkness vibe.
I just-- dark.
So let's darken it up, right?
OK, and we'll come down here.
And you know, this should
look like magic right now.
So I'm just doing Shift-Down.
I'm just adding black.
Now this particular node,
he's a little tricky.
Look, he's a number input.
So you can navigate the
entire DOM with your keyboard.
So I'm going to hit tab.
It just tabbed me
to the next child.
Hit Shift-Down.
I'm going to black that out.
Mm-hmm, that's fine.
Then we'll grab this, and I'm
just going to black that out.
And we'll get rid of the tool.
And I will send a
screenshot to Jake,
and be like, this is how
it should look, dude.
It should be pink and blue.
Come see me in the forum.
I've got more stuff to show you.
I mean, there is--
like, it's weird.
It does a lot of weird stuff.
And it's really fun.
Nothing is off-limits
to this tool.
And I hope content writers, web
designers, just people finally
have a tool that helps
empower them in the DOM.
It should feel like a document.
It should feel like an artboard.
That's the illusion
I'm trying to go for.
So--
BEN GALBRAITH: Awesome.
ADAM ARGYLE: Thanks, guys.
[APPLAUSE]
DION ALMAER: Give it for Adam.
BEN GALBRAITH: That was awesome.
DION ALMAER: Thanks.
BEN GALBRAITH: It's
been a pleasure
to reflect with you
on the past 10 years
and what's new for the web.
Before we go, we want to give
a brief mention of Chrome OS.
It's a great way to
engage with the web.
And with support for
Linux and Android apps,
it's also ready for
web development.
We're offering a 75% discount on
the Google Pixelbook to all CDS
attendees so you
can check it out.
The vouchers will be
available tomorrow morning
before the first
session begins--
DION ALMAER: --so don't
party too hard tonight.
BEN GALBRAITH: And with
that, thank you very much
for joining us
here this morning.
And let's all work together.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]